<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China,
                    1969-1980</title>
                <title type="short">China Conference</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt xml:id="U.S_DOS">
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China,
                            1969-1980</title>
                        <date from="2006-09-25" to="2006-09-27">September 25-27, 2006</date>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>"Transforming the Cold War: The United States and China, 1969-1980"</head>
                <p>Co-sponsored by <hi rend="strong">The U.S. Department of State</hi> and <hi
                        rend="strong">The Institute for European, Russian, and Eurasian Studies, at
                        the Elliott School of International Affairs, The George Washington
                        University </hi>
                </p>
                <p>Washington, DC<lb/>September 25-27, 2006</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="program">
                <head>Program</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Monday, September 25, 2006</hi>
                    <lb/>2201 C St., N.W., Loy Henderson Conference Room, U.S. Department of
                    State<lb/>1:00-1:40 Registration - Enter from 23rd Street<lb/>1:40-1:45 Welcome
                    and Introductory Remarks: <ref target="#opening-remarks">Dr. Marc J.
                        Susser</ref>, The Historian, U.S. Department of State <lb/>1:45-2:30
                    Scheduled Keynote Speaker: <ref target="#zelikow">Dr. Philip D. Zelikow</ref>,
                    Counselor of the U.S. Department of State <lb/>2:30-4:30 <ref target="#panel"
                        >Scheduled Panel of Former Diplomats and Government Officials</ref>: <list>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#lord">Ambassador Winston S. Lord</ref> (ret.), Member of
                            the National Security Council Staff, 1969-1973; Special Assistant to
                            Henry Kissinger, 1970-1973; Director of the Policy Planning Staff,
                            Department of State, 1973-1977</item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#smyser">Professor W. Richard Smyser</ref>, Operations
                            Staff, National Security Council, 1970-1971 and 1973-1975; Deputy
                            Assistant Secretary and Assistant Secretary for Refugee Programs,
                            Department of State, 1980-1981</item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#scowcroft">Lt. General Brent Scowcroft</ref>, U.S. Air
                            Force (ret.), Deputy National Security Advisor, 1973-1975; National
                            Security Advisor, 1975-1977</item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#brzezinski">Dr. Zbigniew Brzezinski</ref>, National
                            Security Advisor, 1977-1981</item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#freeman">Ambassador Charles W. (Chas.) Freeman, Jr.</ref>
                            (ret.), Office of Asian Communist Affairs, Bureau of East Asian and
                            Pacific Affairs, Department of State, 1971-1973; Director for Chinese
                            Affairs, Department of State, 1979-1981</item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#comments">Panelist Comments</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <ref target="#qa">Question and Answer</ref>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Tuesday, September 26, 2006</hi>
                    <lb/>2201 C St., N.W., Loy Henderson Conference Room, U.S. Department of State
                    <lb/>8:30-9:15 Registration and Continental Breakfast - Enter from 23rd
                    Street<lb/>9:15-9:30 Welcome<lb/>9:30-10:00 Scheduled Keynote speaker,
                    Christopher R. Hill, Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific
                    Affairs <lb/>10:00-10:15 Break<lb/>10:15-12:00 Session 1: Roundtable - Foreign
                    Relations of the United States, 1969-1976, volume XVII, China, 1969-1972 and
                    Scholarly Interpretations of Establishing Relations With China, 1969-1980 <list>
                        <item>Professor Steven Phillips, Department of History, Towson University
                            (Chair)</item>
                        <item>Professor Chen Jian, Department of History, Cornell University</item>
                        <item>Professor Warren I. Cohen, Department of History, University of
                            Maryland, Baltimore County</item>
                        <item>James Mann, FPI Author-in-Residence, School for Advanced International
                            Studies, Johns Hopkins University</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>12:00-1:30 Lunch<lb/>1:30-3:00 Session 2<lb/>Chair: Dr. Chris Tudda, Office of
                    the Historian, U.S. Department of State <list>
                        <item>"Musical Diplomacy in the Opening of China, 1971-1972"<lb/>Professor
                            Adam Cathcart, Department of History, Hiram College</item>
                        <item>"Communication and Miscommunication in Sino-Soviet-American Relations,
                            1969"<lb/>Professor Lorenz Lüthi, Department of History, McGill
                            University</item>
                        <item>"The Romanian Efforts to Facilitate a Sino-American Rapprochement,
                            1969-1971"<lb/>Mircea Munteanu, Woodrow Wilson International Center for
                            Scholars/The George Washington University</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Comments: Professor Gregg Brazinsky, Department of History, The George Washington
                    University<lb/>3:00-3:15 Break<lb/>3:15-5:00 Session 3<lb/>Chair: Dr. Ding
                    Xinghao, President, Shanghai Association of American Studies and Shanghai
                    Institute of American Studies <list>
                        <item>"Mobilizing for War: China's Limited Ability to Cope With the Soviet
                            Threat, 1969-1972"<lb/>Professor David Bachman, School of International
                            Studies, University of Washington</item>
                        <item>"Between Historical Determinism and Anxiety: The Soviet Union and
                            Sino-American Rapprochement, 1969-1973"<lb/>Dr. Bernd Schaefer, German
                            Historical Institute</item>
                        <item>"From Zhenbao Island to Beijing: The 1969 Sino-Soviet Border Conflict
                            and U.S.-China Relations"<lb/>Professor Dong Wang, Department of History
                            and Political Science, York College of Pennsylvania</item>
                        <item>"The Sino-American Rapprochement and Chinese-Vietnamese Relations"
                            <lb/>Professor Qiang Zhai, Department of History, Auburn University
                            Montgomery Comments: Professor Thomas Schwartz, Department of History,
                            Vanderbilt University</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Wednesday, September 27, 2006</hi>
                    <lb/>1957 E St., N.W., Lindner Family Commons, 6th Floor, Institute for
                    European, Russian, and Eurasian Studies, at the Elliott School of International
                    Affairs, The George Washington University (This portion of the conference is
                    funded by the Henry Luce Foundation)<lb/>9:00-10:15 Session 1<lb/>Chair:
                    Professor Hope M. Harrison, History Department and Director of the Institute for
                    European, Russian and Eurasian Studies, The George Washington University <list>
                        <item>"U.S. Relations With the People's Republic of China, 1969-1974: The
                            Polish Perspective" <lb/>Malgorzata Gnoinska, The George Washington
                            University</item>
                        <item>"Economic Problems in U.S.-China Rapprochement, 1972-1975"<lb/>William
                            Burr, National Security Archive</item>
                        <item>"The Chinese Perspective on the U.S.-China
                            Rapprochement"<lb/>Professor Chen Jian, Department of History, Cornell
                            University</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Comments: Patrick Tyler, Woodrow Wilson Center<lb/>10:15-10:30
                    Break<lb/>10:30-11:45: Session 2<lb/>Chair: Dr. Christian Ostermann, Woodrow
                    Wilson Center <list>
                        <item>"Zbigniew Brzezinski and the Carter Approach to China: 'The United
                            States Has Made Up Its Mind.' "<lb/>Professor Patrick Vaughan,
                            Jagiellonian University, Krakow, Poland</item>
                        <item>"The False ShuffleCyrus Vance and the China Card"<lb/>Breck Walker,
                            Department of History, Vanderbilt University</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Comments: Professor David Shambaugh, Department of Political Science and
                    Director, China Program, The George Washington University<lb/>12:00-1:00
                    Lunch<lb/>1:00-2:15 Session 3<lb/>Chair: Professor Gregg Brazinsky, Department
                    of History, The George Washington University <list>
                        <item>" 'Maximum Flexibility for Peaceful Change': Jimmy Carter, Taiwan and
                            the Recognition of the People's Republic of China"<lb/>Brian Hilton,
                            Department of History, Texas A&amp;M University</item>
                        <item>"The Carter Administration and China: The Culmination of
                            Self-Determination as a Human Right"<lb/>Professor Itai Sneh, Department
                            of History, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, City University of New
                            York </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Comments: Dr. Richard C. Bush, Director, Center for Northeast Asian Policy
                    Studies, The Brookings Institution<lb/>2:15-2:30 Break<lb/>2:30-4:00 Session 4
                    <lb/>Chair: Professor Edward McCord, Department of History, The George
                    Washington University <list>
                        <item>"The Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan and its Effect on Carter's Policy
                            Toward China"<lb/>Todd Rosa, Department of History, The George
                            Washington University</item>
                        <item>"'The Vietnamese Lesson': The Carter Administration and the Chinese
                            Attack on Vietnam"<lb/>Professor Scott Kaufman, Francis Marion
                            University</item>
                        <item>"The Chinese 'Punitive Invasion' of Vietnam as the 'Baptism of Fire'
                            of a New Strategic Partnership With Washington and its Repercussions on
                            the end of the Cold War"<lb/>Enrico Maria Fardella, Department of
                            Political Sciences, University of Florence</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Comments: Professor James G. Hershberg, Department of History, The George
                    Washington University<lb/>4:00-5:00 Session 5, Wrap-Up Session: New Evidence on
                    the International History of the Normalization of U.S.-China
                    Relations<lb/>Professor William Kirby, Department of History, Harvard
                    University<lb/>Professor Robert S. Ross, Fairbank Center for East Asian
                    Research, Harvard University and Department of Political Science, Boston
                    College</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="opening-remarks">
                <head>Opening Remarks</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">MARC SUSSER (Historian of the Department):</hi> Thank you. As
                    Amy said, I am the Historian of the Department. I'd like to welcome all of you
                    here to the Department to this conference on "Transforming the Cold War: The
                    United States and China, 1969-1980." This is the fourth annual historical
                    conference sponsored by the Department of State and we are pleased to be
                    co-hosting this with the Elliott School of George Washington University.</p>
                <p>As with our previous conferences, this one is linked to the release of several
                    volumes in our official historical documentary series <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                        Relations of the United States</hi>. As some of you may know, the Foreign
                    Relations series was started by President Abraham Lincoln and Secretary of State
                    William Seward back in 1861. In that era, when the United States was in the
                    midst of its greatest crisis, all the important documents fit into one volume.
                    Today, the series has grown to over 400 volumes with the Office of the Historian
                    now planning to publish 57 volumes covering just the Nixon and Ford
                    administrations alone. And we will do that at just over 30 years after the
                    events.</p>
                <p>Several weeks ago, the Department published the first volume on the Nixon
                    Administration's policy toward China. Today, we are adding to that material with
                    a new publication, an electronic volume which is now available on the internet,
                        <hi rend="italic">Documents on China 1969-72</hi>, which supplements the
                    documents that are found in the print volume. The combination of print and
                    internet publication allows us to deal with the ever greater number and variety
                    of documents that are now available to historians. This melding of the two
                    formats allows the Department to provide a comprehensive account of the
                    evolution of U.S. policy toward China during these crucial years.</p>
                <p>The 1991 law that governs the Foreign Relations series requires that it be a
                    thorough, accurate and reliable account of U.S. foreign policy, and we believe
                    that is exactly what we provide in these two volumes. Although the broad
                    outlines of the Nixon-Kissinger policy and opening to China are well known, our
                    volumes include many new details not previously available to the public and many
                    not previously available even to scholars in the field. Our historians have had
                    full access to the files of all the agencies and departments involved in the
                    foreign policy process during the years of the administrations of President
                    Nixon and President Ford, and we have selected for publication the key documents
                    that best tell the story of the evolution and development of U.S. policy during
                    this period.</p>
                <p>These volumes fulfill the requirements of the law that the published record shall
                    omit no facts that were of major importance in reaching a decision and that
                    nothing shall be omitted for the purpose of concealing a defect of policy. The
                    publication of the Foreign Relations series provides an unrivaled example of
                    transparency and of a government making its business open to public scrutiny.
                    For more than 140 years, the Foreign Relations series has provided a powerful
                    tool enabling the American public and indeed people all over the world to
                    understand our country's foreign policy process.</p>
                <p>We do this because we and our Congress believe that in a democracy a government
                    has an obligation to tell its people the truth. We believe that it's important
                    that the American people know what their government has done in its dealings
                    with the rest of the world once sufficient time has passed and still-classified
                    material has been protected. We believe that the best way to maintain the
                    delicate balance of secrecy and trust between citizens and their government is
                    to ensure that the actions of the government are not hidden forever. And that is
                    why the Department of State publishes the Foreign Relations series.</p>
                <p>The complete text of this new electronic volume is now available on the internet.
                    The print volume that was released a couple of weeks ago will soon be available
                    for sale from the Government Printing Office and I believe we have CDs of that
                    volume included in your folders today.</p>
                <p>We made extensive efforts to ensure broad participation in this conference and we
                    are pleased that we have several scholars with us here today from China. The
                    opening to China and the later normalization of relations dramatically altered
                    the international landscape of the Cold War and set the framework for U.S.-China
                    relations until today. We have with us today some of the key policymakers from
                    the Nixon, Ford and Carter administrations who will share their recollections of
                    these key years.</p>
                <p>Also with us today to formally open the conference and to put this period in
                    U.S.-China relations in historical perspective is one of the Department's most
                    senior officials, the Counselor of the Department, Dr. Philip Zelikow.</p>
                <p>Dr. Zelikow was appointed Counselor of the Department in February of 2005 and he
                    advises the Secretary of State on a wide range of issues. Before his
                    appointment, he was the staff director of the 9/11 Commission, a trial and
                    appellate attorney, a former career Foreign Service officer, a member of the
                    National Security Council staff and the Director of the Miller Center for Public
                    Affairs at the University of Virginia. He is also a former member of the
                    President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board, and from our perspective here
                    in the Office of the Historian, even more important, a former member of the
                    Department's Historical Advisory Committee.</p>
                <p>Dr. Zelikow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="zelikow">
                <head>Keynote Speaker: Dr. Philip D. Zelikow, Counselor of the U.S. Department of
                    State</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">PHILIP ZELIKOW (Counselor of the Department):</hi> Ladies and
                    gentlemen, it's an honor to be here today to address this conference. I'd like
                    to begin by acknowledging the Office of the Historian, by acknowledging their
                    patient and determined scholarship from year to year, decade to decade,
                    preserving and publishing the record of American foreign relations.</p>
                <p>You'll note that this volume is not just about the record of the Department of
                    State. Increasingly, the Historian's Office has assumed the responsibility of
                    providing a foreign policy record that extends beyond the State Department to
                    include the records of the White House, our intelligence agencies. It really is
                    one of the treasures of our nation's government that just happens to be lodged
                    in the Department of State.</p>
                <p>I also want to note in commenting on the role of the Historian's Office and on
                    the role of a conference like this that this is not about official history. A
                    lot of the historians who are at this conference don't like this administration.
                    Why, some of the premier historians of Sino-American relations, like Warren
                    Cohen or Michael Hunt don't like this administration. And that's okay. Their
                    scholarship has earned them the kind of honor and attention that it continues to
                    receive today and it is perfectly normal and natural that scholars should
                    criticize the administration, have different views and provide a wealth of
                    perspectives.</p>
                <p>Indeed, when I served on the Historical Advisory Committee I was appointed to
                    that role by a Democratic Secretary of State and members of that committee were
                    involved in constant strife with whichever administration was prevailing at the
                    time, usually pushing harder and harder for more declassification, placing more
                    material in the public records, to always be sure that those values were given
                    attention to.</p>
                <p>In other words, the Historian's Office in a conference like this is not about
                    official history. It is instead about an official duty to history that is being
                    discharged. I hope this conference can serve as an example to other historian's
                    offices and other governments elsewhere in the world, including our friends in
                    China and even our friends in Japan on various ways that one can approach
                    sensitive problems in contemporary history.</p>
                <p>I want to acknowledge too the quality of scholarship and expertise available to
                    students of U.S.-China relations in particular, the outstanding quality of the
                    primary sources, a tradition of careful documentation that I think is influenced
                    by Chinese culture and traditions in this particular field.</p>
                <p>There is something disciplining about the fact that when you believe people
                    really will scrutinize what you say word for word, you're more careful in how
                    you write it down. There's also a rich tradition of interchange of scholarship
                    between public and private work. Stanley Hornbeck, journeying from Harvard with
                    the gentle permission of President Lowell back to join the State Department and
                    serve in public service. Or people like the late Jim Thompson or Ezra Vogel or
                    Ken Lieberthal or many, many others, including the newly appointed Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary of State Tom Christensen, coming to us from Princeton
                    University.</p>
                <p>Finally, as I turn to this subject, I want to note that it's really appropriate
                    we're holding this conference on this date to me because it's almost exactly one
                    year since Bob Zoellick spoke last September, September of 2005, about America's
                    relations with China today and the way those relations have really entered a new
                    phase, a phase made possible by the developments and policymakers whose work we
                    are studying today and in the succeeding days.</p>
                <p>Of course, American historical memory in these matters can be questioned. I was
                    looking at some different works on this and I stumbled across a wonderful quote
                    after then Defense Secretary Harold Brown visited China in the beginning of
                    January 1980. A Chinese intellectual told the delegation of American China
                    specialists that the potential in Sino-American relations should not be
                    overestimated. The quote from the New York Times article is that, "You Americans
                    are so charming," a Chinese scholar said, "for you have such short memories. We
                    can't forget so fast or so easily what happened between us in the past." Well,
                    this conference is trying to at least contribute to the slight lengthening of
                    our traditionally short national memory.</p>
                <p>Let me offer some questions and policy reflections: first, on why normalization
                    occurred when it did; second, what did the United States want from
                    normalization; third, on what I think is a striking continuity in American hopes
                    for China; and fourth, some of the lingering consequences of this history
                    today.</p>
                <p>First then, why did normalization occur when it did? It's an interesting question
                    because, of course, the State Department had long wanted to normalize U.S.-China
                    relations and had equally long been ambivalent about what would happen if we
                    did. So there was a constancy of State Department desire to normalize and a
                    constancy too of State Department ambivalence towards the actual prospect
                    because of reactions from Japan, from Southeast Asia, from the Soviet Union and
                    so forth, that naturally were caveats that would have to be taken into account
                    before you actually made such a move.</p>
                <p>So then when one looks at the American variables, in addition to that constancy,
                    I think it is interesting to look at the role that Richard Nixon himself played.
                    Nixon's role is interesting in this matter because Nixon was more interested in
                    Asia than many American national leaders were even of his time. It's important
                    to remember that Nixon, for example, in contrast to the life story of Henry
                    Kissinger before 1969, that Nixon was a man of the west and a man of the Pacific
                    Rim in some distinctive ways. Nixon grew up in California. His World War II
                    service was in the Pacific, not in the European theater. The Republican Party in
                    which he had spent his formative years, the Republican Party of the late 1940s
                    and early 1950s was actually a Republican Party that was extremely interested in
                    Asia. One of the characteristic stereotypes of, say, Bob Taft, a leader of the
                    Republican Party on that issue, is to think of these people as isolationist
                    because of their opposition to NATO. In fact, it's important to remember that
                    Taft Republicans may have been isolationist with regards to American engagement
                    in Europe, but they were anything but isolationist when it came to American
                    engagement in the future of East Asia, where their policy prescriptions were
                    very activist and Nixon very much internalized that. Indeed, one of his
                    signature issues when he became Vice President to Dwight Eisenhower was Asia,
                    was an intense interest in the fate of Indochina, for example, in 1953 and 1954,
                    and in the Taiwan Straits crises later in the Eisenhower Administration.</p>
                <p>So Nixon comes into office as President as a person conditioned to a constancy of
                    interest in Asia and with a lot of knowledge and interest in America's
                    traditions there. So in his very first foreign trips, when literally he's been
                    in office only weeks, he's already talking about the idea of opening to China.
                    In his meetings with President DeGaulle, for example, he noted -- and this is in
                    the Foreign Relations documents -- that there existed "considerable sentiment in
                    the State Department not only in favor of a Soviet-U.S. détente but also for a
                    lineup of the Soviets, Europe and the U.S. against the Chinese." By the way, in
                    this instance I believe that this is a false allegation against the State
                    Department, setting up a straw man to which Nixon could then comment. Because
                    Nixon's comment was such a détente against the Chinese might be a good
                    short-range policy, but in the longer term it was in the U.S. interest to
                    recognize that China and the Soviet Union were "great powers" and that we should
                    "build parallel relationships with them." Nixon then conceding that this was
                    "largely theoretical as it was difficult to have relations with the Chinese,"
                    which begins to suggest that the critical variable in the opening was less in
                    Washington and more perhaps in Beijing.</p>
                <p>It's not, of course, the place of an American government official to speculate in
                    depth from this podium about the motives and attitudes of Chinese leadership,
                    but it is important to recognize, as many historians have, that this was a
                    period in the late 1960s and especially the beginning of the 1970s when Chinese
                    revolutionary activism and domestic turmoil was appearing to subside, that
                    China's role in the Vietnam War was changing as the Soviet role in supporting
                    the North Vietnamese became primary and the Chinese role becoming secondary, but
                    also a period in which China must have felt an increasing sense of isolation
                    from the communist world and in the world more generally. Relatively few fast
                    friends for China back then, among them countries like Pakistan and Romania,
                    which then both provided back channels to try to facilitate a normalization of
                    relations with the United States. And then there was the Soviet factor, the
                    invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968, border clashes, a lot of ominous talk in
                    public and in private.</p>
                <p>So why normalization occurred when it did -- yes, there's an American factor,
                    Nixon being important, but also very important to look at the Chinese variable
                    as perhaps even being the critical variable. But as that variable changed, the
                    opportunities for normalization opened and we turn to my second subject, what
                    did the United States seek from normalization, or to put it even more plainly,
                    what did we want from them?</p>
                <p>The answer to this question is interesting and I think thought-provoking. Let's
                    start with what Kissinger wanted. There is a lot of evidence and fragments of
                    evidence about Kissinger's views on this subject. I think it's fair to say that
                    for Kissinger the opening to China was very much part of the foreign policy
                    perspective he had focused on the Soviet Union and the broader geopolitical
                    balance of power.</p>
                <p>For instance, in October 1971, Kissinger, returning from having met with Zhou
                    Enlai -- again, out of FRUS volume -- Kissinger telling Nixon, "The China trip's
                    the keystone of your foreign policy, Mr. President. You get a good reception in
                    China, which I know you will, you come out with a decent communiqué, you're in
                    business with the Russians. Then the Russian trip will be a great success,"
                    which they were already thinking about for the spring of 1972.</p>
                <p>Or for instance, in an exceptionally revealing meeting that lasted for hours
                    between Nixon and Kissinger on the eve of their departure for China, a meeting
                    that fortunately was caught on tape and painstakingly transcribed by the State
                    editors of the FRUS volume, Kissinger remarks that for the next 15 years, we
                    have to lean towards the Chinese against the Russians; we have to play this
                    balance of power game totally unemotionally; right now, we need the Chinese to
                    correct the Russians and to discipline the Russians.</p>
                <p>And then going on, in the very same conversation, Nixon makes some remarks about
                    the Chinese reception for a visiting African leader. Kissinger comes back to his
                    main subject: "Our concern with China right now in my view, Mr. President, is to
                    use it as a counterweight to Russia, not for its local policy." President Nixon
                    says he agrees. Kissinger adds, "As a counterweight to keep it in play in the
                    subcontinent for the time being, but above all, as a counterweight to Russia and
                    the fact that it doesn't -- that China doesn't have a global policy is an asset
                    to us, that it doesn't have global strength yet, and to prevent Russia from
                    gobbling it up. If Russia dominates China, that would be a fact of such
                    tremendous significance."</p>
                <p>That gives you a little bit of a sense, some fragments of Kissinger's
                    perspective, of his orientation, but not to what people then wrote about Nixon's
                    orientation, which was different and in some ways more fundamental, more
                    inchoate. For instance, Marshall Green recalling ways that Nixon had expressed
                    himself to him on this subject, especially in 1969 when Green spent a lot of
                    time with Nixon, recalled that "Nixon said to me," Green, "We simply cannot go
                    on indefinitely in a hostile relationship with one-quarter of mankind,
                    especially as the PRC grows in military power."</p>
                <p>Or try the recollection of John Holdridge, who was working at State, then went to
                    work with the NSC staff along with Win Lord and others who are here. Holdridge
                    recalled Nixon rationale, which he says he often heard Nixon express, was "It's
                    far better to talk to the Chinese than to fight them," given China's huge
                    population, key geographic location, and important influence. And this is
                    interesting because then, when you look at what did America want from China from
                    the normalization process instrumentally, if the question is, what did we want
                    from them, the answer is not very much. A lot of the agenda was a defensive
                    agenda, how to avoid giving away too much on Taiwan.</p>
                <p>It was not an agenda -- unlike the agenda with the Soviet Union, where we really
                    expected dramatic results on, say, Vietnam; why, after the February 1972 summit,
                    shortly thereafter, the Vietnamese launched the Easter Offensive that began on
                    March 30th, 1972 and neither Nixon nor Kissinger appeared to feel betrayed by
                    that. They didn't think they had a deal with the Chinese. Indeed, if anything,
                    the Chinese were kind of urging the Americans to be tougher on the North
                    Vietnamese because of their growing estrangement from the North Vietnamese that
                    was already evident.</p>
                <p>But you go through issue after issue, it's hard to find anything that's concrete
                    and instrumental that the Americans are really seeking from the open. There is
                    the balance of power argument put showing that America and China could work
                    together and the chilling effect that would have on the Russians that Kissinger
                    emphasizes. But then it's hard to resist the sense that there is just this more
                    fundamental, inchoate concern which Nixon articulates that's less instrumental
                    and more about, such an opening is an end in itself.</p>
                <p>In other words, that to Nixon, he would be earning his place in history simply by
                    ending what Warren Cohen has called "the great aberration," the period of
                    rupture in US-China relations that had lasted for about 20 years. That point is
                    important because it brings us to the third one. If you think about "the great
                    aberration," you think that, for Nixon, in a way, he was returning to a sense of
                    good relations with China that, for him, was part of the natural, normal
                    American context. He was returning to normalization, not creating it new. Then
                    you really capture the sense of the continuity of American hopes for China,
                    which I think is worth dwelling on in some detail.</p>
                <p>It is asserted by some Chinese nationalists, not necessarily by the Chinese
                    Government, that the recent tradition of American relations with China is a
                    desire to keep China down, to limit China's power, to limit China's influence.
                    In contrast, I think it's fairer to assert that as long as it has been involved
                    in Asia's politics, for more than 100 years, America's leaders have sought a
                    strong, united, and independent China.</p>
                <p>Year in and year out, from one generation to the next, America pursued this goal
                    with a constancy of purpose unique among all the major powers in the region. Of
                    course, America did so to serve America's interests. But America conceived of
                    its interests in a rare harmony with the long-term interests of the Chinese
                    people. And America thus played, again and again, an indispensable historical
                    role in the evolution of a strong and independent China.</p>
                <p>Let me offer just a few illustrations. In 1899, immediately after America
                    realized that it is an Asiatic power, Hay and William Rockhill authored the Open
                    Door. The Open Door Note, as I'm sure many of you here know, is commonly
                    remembered for the goal of being sure that the door was not closed to American
                    commerce, as some of the imperial powers were moving to carving up China in the
                    waning years of the Manchu Dynasty.</p>
                <p>But it's also worth remembering when one reads the Open Door Note that it had two
                    goals, not only the goal of not excluding the United States and keeping the door
                    open in that sense, but also asserting that China should be allowed to continue
                    to have control of its finances, the issue of control of China's customs
                    revenue. Because if China lost complete control of its finances, its effective
                    independence would come to an end, and the United States had already decided
                    that it was very much in America's interests for China to preserve its
                    independence.</p>
                <p>That kind of persistent view of the need for a stable, stronger and more
                    independent China is carried forward in the administration of Theodore
                    Roosevelt, carried forward in the way America distinctively approached the
                    settlement of the Boxer rebellion claims, Roosevelt's own article on the
                    awakening of China. It continues on through the Taft Administration and then on
                    into the Wilson Administration. Remember that after the Chinese Revolution of
                    1912, the Wilson Administration rushed to recognize the new Republic of China
                    and did so unilaterally before the other great powers were willing to go along.
                    Wilson once expressing, as Josephus Daniels noted in his minutes of a cabinet
                    meeting -- Wilson saying his desire to help China was so strong, "that I prefer
                    to err in the line of helping that country than otherwise."</p>
                <p>All this coupled with a growing concern about Japan, all of it limited by a keen
                    sense of how little American power there was to project in East Asia and how
                    little one could do to safeguard China or promote China. But America would do
                    what it could.</p>
                <p>In 1922, when in the Harding Administration, Charles Evans Hughes, the Secretary
                    of State and Elihu Root decided to create a Washington system for East Asia
                    organized around the Washington conferences. By the way, again, the stereotype
                    of American isolation after the failure of the League of Nations, not at all
                    true when it comes to American policy in Asia. That Washington system they
                    crafted had at its core a Nine Power Treaty designed to secure Chinese
                    independence in a period of disorder, guaranteeing its independence,
                    guaranteeing its territorial integrity, with America as the lead sponsor of
                    those provisions to ensure the Nine Powers respected them.</p>
                <p>Not enough for the Chinese nationalists, not enough for them that America
                    couldn't overthrow the regime of unequal treaties that the other powers insisted
                    on; yet even on that score, by 1926, again ahead of the other powers, the United
                    States was ready to discard extraterritoriality and wanted to grant China tariff
                    autonomy. By the way, over active protests from within the Department of State
                    and protests from both London and Tokyo because of American dedication, here now
                    the role of Secretary Kellogg and Nelson Johnson, to this need to preserve a
                    strong and independent China once China could sort out its internal disorder and
                    its internal weaknesses.</p>
                <p>Then American interests, while they remained the same, were not so actively
                    pursued until finally, as Japanese aggression on the Chinese mainland grew in
                    the period from 1938 to 1941, the United States of America took supreme risks to
                    protect the strength and independence of China. Finally, at the end of 1938, as
                    the activist Secretary of the Treasury Henry Morgenthau found at last an ally in
                    the Department of State, hitherto preferring to do nothing about these problems
                    except to refuse to recognize either side's claims and not intervene.</p>
                <p>Morgenthau over again, asking for another embargo on some Japanese trade. Hull,
                    of course, as usual, disagreeing with Morgenthau. Hull then sending for Stanley
                    Hornbeck. And then Hornbeck arrives and Morgenthau noted in his diaries, "I
                    almost fell out of my chair when Hornbeck agreed that this ought to be done."
                    Hornbeck said, "As a matter of fact, we're working on several other ways to put
                    the screws in the Japanese, and this is just what we ought to do," ushering a
                    period of financial and economic aid to China, then fighting for its life, and
                    financial and economic sanctions against Japan of growing strength and gravity
                    until by 1940 and '41, the risks that were being undertaken by these sanctions
                    flew in the face of America's grand strategy which was, after all, Germany
                    first.</p>
                <p>So with a Germany first strategy, you do not want to provoke a war in the Pacific
                    before you come to grips with the main problem in Europe. Yet that is exactly
                    the kind of risk that was being courted by the policy and in fact, the risk that
                    materialized finally in the attack on Pearl Harbor in December 1941. And you are
                    then left with this extraordinary dichotomy of risk and principle that's worth
                    noting because some of the ideas involved have resonance to the present day.</p>
                <p>Stanley Hornbeck, reaching the end of his life in the early 1960s, asked about
                    what America should do to meet its present challenges, said -- and here, I'm
                    indebted to the late Jim Thompson for noting this -- "Well, I am sure about some
                    things," Hornbeck said, "our national concern for and regarding principles and
                    practices of freedom, independence, justice and security is greater than is that
                    of any other nation. We should be prepared to go further and to make greater
                    efforts in defense of those principles and practices than is to be expected of
                    any other country."</p>
                <p>At the same time, drawing to a close, Hornbeck files a little note in a box
                    marked "Pearl Harbor," in a way leaving a record for posterity, "Did I,"
                    Hornbeck, "underestimate Japan's strength? The answer is: Yes, both in absolute
                    terms and in comparative terms. And so did practically everyone else in the
                    United States, both in the government and out of the government in varying
                    degrees." The results were that America then found itself in a war, a war it had
                    been drawn into in conflict with its grand strategy, in great part because of
                    its stubborn dedication to trying to preserve a united and independent
                    China.</p>
                <p>Another key moment arises as the war goes on; who will make up the permanent
                    membership of the United Nations Security Council that will have such an
                    extraordinary role in the postwar order? There was only one voice in the
                    councils of the great powers that said such a seat must be held for China. And
                    that voice was, again, that of the United States. Franklin Roosevelt, for
                    example, insisting on it with Anthony Eden in March of 1943 so that in 1945,
                    that seat is there, the seat which the Peoples' Republic of China now holds, a
                    seat which it could take in 1971 because that seat had been built for it in
                    1945. Had that seat not been there, China might today be, along with other
                    countries, joining the ranks of those asking for the reorganization of the UN
                    Security Council to recognize China's role. But instead, the United States had
                    worked to preserve that role as early as 1943, successfully.</p>
                <p>And in 1946, another extraordinary choice that America had to make; as the war
                    came to an end and American policy was fluid on its attitude toward the Chinese
                    communists, the great choice facing the United States Government was: Do you
                    side completely with Jiang and the Guomindang against the communists? And
                    instead, a series of American leaders, especially Byrnes, Acheson, Marshall and
                    John Carter Vincent decided instead to choose mediation and restraint in China's
                    civil war.</p>
                <p>There was an extraordinary opportunity for the anti-communists. After all, Stalin
                    had already made his deal with Jiang Jieshi in 1945 as to how he would come to a
                        <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> with Guomindang rule in the new China,
                    and Mao knew it. There were a lot of Americans, Patrick Hurley among them and
                    others, who would have argued that the United States should come down 100
                    percent on the side of the Guomindang, and that the United States chose not to
                    do. Or indeed, in 1947, as the civil war deepened into complete strife with the
                    result that here, where the future of East Asia was arguably at stake, perhaps
                    the most important contest in the emerging Cold War, where a quarter of the
                    world's population was on the table, the United States fundamentally chose not
                    to intervene with its full military might at the time when victory for the
                    Guomindang could have been assured.</p>
                <p>We can argue about whether those decisions were right, but the reason for their
                    choice of mediation and restraint was because of their hopes for a strong,
                    united and independent China and that somehow, this was the only way to achieve
                    that unity. We can fault the way they went about it, we can decry the naiveté,
                    but the purpose is important to understand. And even that lingering purpose
                    going on in the Korean War, when in 1950 and 1951, Mao essentially invited
                    America to join World War III, an invitation that, despite the recommendations
                    of some, such as his commander in the Far East, President Truman chose to
                    decline.</p>
                <p>In the Taiwan Straits crises, despite Chinese intervention into the Vietnam War
                    in the early and mid-1960s and its threats to the United States that if they
                    sought to solve the Vietnam War by dealing with North Vietnam, they would face
                    war with China, and the American decision therefore to accept the limited war
                    that China insisted on as the choice between that and war with China; again and
                    again, the United States chooses the path of its consistent interests and regard
                    for China, which then brings us back to the issues of the 1970s.</p>
                <p>So for America in the 1970s, there was a constancy of interest that now seemed
                    enabled and possible in new ways. And the question is whether that constancy is
                    now coming to fruition. Therefore, I want to turn fourth to the consequences of
                    that normalization and that constancy today.</p>
                <p>Looking back at 1969 again, one of the many studies that the White House
                    commissioned was National Security Study Memorandum 14, commissioned in the
                    spring and summer of 1969 to look at U.S. policies towards China. Kissinger
                    famously remarked that these studies were make-work projects to keep the State
                    Department busy. I think this is Kissinger in his more puckish moment. In fact,
                    at the time, I think this particular study was taken quite seriously. A lot of
                    people worked on it, especially at the State Department, and there was a
                    prescient question asked in the State Department's paper answering that
                    study.</p>
                <p>In August 1969, the State Department paper responding to NSM 14 posed the
                    following question, which I think was probably written by Marshall Green, John
                    Holdridge and their colleagues, Holdridge at State before he then went over and
                    received the paper on the NSC staff.</p>
                <p>"A question can legitimately be posed as to whether or not it is in U.S.
                    interests for Peking to become more engaged in the international scene. If
                    Peking should choose to pursue a more pragmatic and moderate foreign policy,
                    pressures by the nations of Asia for accommodating Peking and for accepting the
                    PRC into international organizations would build rapidly. Peking's emergence
                    from its self-imposed isolation would thus pose new challenges for U.S. policy
                    in Asia and would probably result in certain short-term losses to ourselves and
                    our allies."</p>
                <p>And to that prescient question, it is interesting to note a prescient answer. The
                    answer then offered in August '69 was that over the long-term, however,
                    "evolution of Peking's policies toward moderation would offer the prospect of
                    increased stability in East Asia. Since it does not lie within the United
                    States' power to prevent Peking from breaking out of its isolation, the issue
                    posed for the U.S. is whether this evolution will take place in spite of U.S.
                    resistance or whether the U.S. will be seen as willing to accept and live with
                    Peking's entry into the international community and do what it can to take
                    advantage of the change."</p>
                <p>Those words do indeed ring true today, as do further cautions in that same
                    memorandum, cautions about limited U.S. power. To what extent, one can ask, can
                    America actually influence the way China approaches the international system if
                    it has these new opportunities? Here again, the study's authors in the summer of
                    '69 wrote, "Future Chinese leaders' perspectives may be altered, however, by
                    considerations of domestic political control, by the need for economic
                    development, and by China's relations with third countries. U.S. actions to
                    alter what Peking perceives as the U.S. 'threat' could contribute to this. This
                    need not be hostile to U.S. interests in the long-run if it allows for
                    continuing U.S. political and economic relations with these countries throughout
                    Asia, even though at a reduced level of intimacy than previously," because we
                    would sacrifice some quality of intimacy because of the growing role of China
                    and their decreasing reliance on us as protection against Chinese influence.</p>
                <p>In other words, America made that choice that was forecasted for it in the summer
                    of 1969. It made the choice to embrace the growth of Chinese power. So for
                    example, when Zoellick gave his speech a year ago, he said that "For the United
                    States and the world, the essential question is, how will China use its
                    influence? To answer that question, it is time to take our policy beyond opening
                    doors to China's membership into the international system. We need to urge China
                    to become a responsible stakeholder in that system."</p>
                <p>It is essential, then, to understand the historical record and see the continuity
                    across more than a century of the American belief that a strong, independent and
                    united China could contribute to the stability of East Asia and that that role
                    should be welcomed. The address that we gave a year ago on behalf of the
                    Administration made it clear that the argument about whether the United States
                    wanted to contain Chinese power or encourage Chinese power had been settled. The
                    paradigm that we put forward cannot be reconciled with a paradigm of
                    containment. It is a paradigm that welcomes the growth of Chinese power and
                    urges the Chinese to take on their role in strengthening the international
                    system that has enabled its success.</p>
                <p>Now the choice is that of China. China has choices it will make about how it
                    approaches its own historical record and its own view of its past, but China
                    also has important choices to make about the future. And when I was trying to
                    think about words with which to talk to the Chinese Government or its people
                    about its choices, about its future, I was very drawn to some lines that Dean
                    Acheson used more than half a century ago in a very different context.</p>
                <p>And so paraphrasing Acheson, I will just close by saying: And by no means least
                    of all, it rests with our friends to see that this relationship reaps its true
                    fruits. And I say to them: A great broad highway to a position of equality, of
                    honor, of friendship in the world lies open to you. All the obstacles on that
                    highway have been cleared away so far as governments can clear them away. The
                    obstacles that remain, only you can remove, and you can remove those if you act
                    with other peoples, with understanding, and with generosity and with kindness.
                    All those qualities are inherent in the nature of your people and what we urge
                    you to do is to make those qualities, which are so inherent in your people, the
                    policy of your government.</p>
                <p>Thank you.</p>
                <p>(Applause.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Thank you, Counselor Zelikow. We'll now take a
                    moment for our first panel to assemble up here. (Pause.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" xml:id="panel">
                <head>Panel of Former Diplomats and Government Officials</head>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="susser">
                    <head>Introductions</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> All right, we're going to get started. We are
                        fortunate to have with us several men who were, in Secretary of State
                        Acheson's phrase, present at the creation during the key turning points in
                        U.S. policy toward China during the period between 1969 and 1980. We've
                        asked each of them to provide us with some initial impressions, for no more
                        than ten minutes each, and then we hope that they will both engage in an
                        informative dialogue with each other as well as respond to some questions
                        from the audience.</p>
                    <p>You each should have in your folders index cards on which you can write down
                        questions for the individual panelists or for the panel as a whole. Several
                        of our staff will be circulating through the room to collect them. The
                        complete biographies of our panelists are listed in your programs so I will
                        not repeat them at length, and perhaps we should begin with the two men who
                        were on that first trip to China with Henry Kissinger, then National
                        Security Advisor.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="lord">
                    <head>Ambassador Winston Lord</head>
                    <p>Ambassador Lord, would you like to start off?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR WINSTON LORD:</hi> Thank you. Let me begin by
                        explaining why I'm going first on this panel, and in so doing I will,
                        knowing my fellow panelists who have heard this story before, but this is a
                        conference on scholarship and history and there's a gaping hole in the
                        volumes released; namely, it does not demonstrate that I was the first
                        American official to go into China after 22 years of mutual isolation and
                        hostility. Most people know it was not Nixon, they figured it was Kissinger.
                        That's absolutely false. I was with Kissinger along with Smyser on the
                        plane, a Pakistani plane flying from Islamabad to Beijing. And as we got
                        close to the Chinese border, no American having been there for 22 years, I
                        went to the front of the plane and as we crossed into China I was first.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>So now that we got that straight, let me do the following in ten minutes. We
                        have a huge amount of material to cover, so what I will do is focus on the
                        '69 to '72 period and with broad strokes try to give us a framework for
                        subsequent presentations and discussion.</p>
                    <p>One week after his inauguration, President Nixon, on February 1, sent a memo
                        to Kissinger saying, in effect, he wanted to move ahead with the Chinese.
                        What were our motives? What was China's rationale? Our motives -- and
                        Zelikow touched on this, I disagree with some of his emphasis. But in any
                        event, there was a variety of reasons we wanted to move toward China:
                        generally give us more diplomatic flexibility on the world stage, including
                        with the communist world so Moscow wouldn't be the only spokesperson to deal
                        with one-quarter of the world's population; to improve relations with the
                        Soviet Union to help end the Vietnam War and to promote stability in
                        Asia.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese, in turn, were isolated during the Cultural Revolution
                        diplomatically. They sought security by dealing with the far barbarian to
                        balance off the near barbarians, above all the Soviets but also the Indians,
                        the Vietnamese, Japanese, other traditional hostile neighbors. And they
                        wanted to move ahead, figuring if they moved with us other countries would
                        follow.</p>
                    <p>We faced two challenges to move ahead, one public and one private. The
                        private one was how do you communicate with the Chinese since we were
                        totally cut off. And here we tried several secret channels, including
                        Romania and France, and ended up with Pakistan, a mutual friend.</p>
                    <p>The public problem was to send an audience -- send signals to various
                        audiences, the American audiences and also others around the world, that our
                        policy was indeed shifting. So in addition to statements and foreign policy
                        reports and toasts and speeches, we unilaterally lifted some trade and
                        travel restrictions as a signal to the Chinese they didn't have to respond
                        immediately. We took our ship out of the Taiwan patrol and we made clear
                        that we would not support Soviet pressures against the Chinese.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese, in turn, over months and years, responded. They released a
                        couple of American yachtsmen that drifted into their space. The Edgar Snow
                        interview, the famous one about inviting Nixon. And of course the ping pong
                        diplomacy in April 1971.</p>
                    <p>It was decided through the Pakistani channel that Kissinger would be the one
                        to go, that it would be secret that he would go to Beijing, and I can
                        elaborate on all these points. The big sticking point to fix on a secret
                        trip was to make sure that the agenda went beyond Taiwan, which the Chinese
                        first insisted upon, to broader issues, and once that was settled, we were
                        off.</p>
                    <p>It was a public trip to Southeast Asia and South Asia and the cover story for
                        Kissinger's secret journey to China was that he was going to get a
                        stomachache in Pakistan. The problem is he got a stomachache before he got
                        there in India and he had to keep that secret so as not to mess up his later
                        cover.</p>
                    <p>On the way to Pakistan, I got a call from the Deputy National Security
                        Advisor Al Haig telling us that once again the Soviets had turned us down
                        for a summit. We were prepared to go to Moscow first. They didn't know we
                        were going to China, of course, and so that clinched the sequence of the
                        summits.</p>
                    <p>On that plane, you may think that Kissinger was worried about dealing with
                        Zhou Enlai, the James Bond secret aspects, the geopolitical earthquakes. No,
                        he wasn't. He was worried about the fact he had no shirts. His assistant
                        forgot to pack any shirts for Henry. I, of course, quipped to him that he
                        hadn't even sat down to negotiate with the Chinese and he had already lost
                        his shirt. (Laughter.) So he borrowed one from John Holdridge, who was about
                        6' 3" and he went around looking like a penguin. (Laughter.) And the shirt,
                        of course, said on the collar, "Made in Taiwan." (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>We spent 48 hours in Beijing, over 17 hours with Zhou Enlai, four more hours
                        on a communiqué announcing the President's forthcoming summit, 110 pages
                        with Smyser, Lord and Holdridge taking notes. We agreed we would go ahead;
                        there was mutual interest. We went over the agenda for the President's trip
                        and we worked out the announcement, very sparse because it was dramatic in
                        and of itself. But that was delicate negotiations with the Chinese. They
                        wanted to make clear that Nixon was eager to come to China and we wanted to
                        make clear that China was eager to have Nixon. We split the difference and
                        we also made sure that the communiqué said that we would talk about issues
                        of mutual concern and not just normalization, i.e., Taiwan.</p>
                    <p>On the way back from this trip, by the way, we stopped in Paris for secret
                        negotiations with the Vietnamese. The announcement was made in mid-July in
                        San Clemente. The reaction was overwhelmingly positive in America, although
                        some of the right were concerned, obviously a shock to Taiwan and Japan. And
                        from then on we began to communicate with the Chinese both through Paris and
                        through the UN ambassador in New York.</p>
                    <p>This brings us to the October '71 public trip. We went back again for two
                        reasons: to arrange the logistics for the President's February '72 trip --
                        security, media, where he would go, what he would do; and also substance,
                        again further elaborate the agenda and above all to begin negotiating what
                        became to be known as the Shanghai Communiqué. We went in with the usual
                        traditional draft of stressing harmony and agreement. Zhou Enlai almost
                        literally threw this on the floor and said this is ridiculous, it's got no
                        credibility, we've been enemies for 22 years, this will shake up our
                        friends, it will confuse our domestic audiences, let's each state our own
                        positions, and then when we can't agree on certain areas then they'll have
                        more credibility. He was, of course, right and, as a result, that communiqué
                        is still invoked today after 22 years, which is very unusual for a
                        diplomatic communiqué. It involved some hair-raising drafting overnight in
                        which I stayed up till 3 to redraft entirely the communiqué and then
                        Kissinger took it at 3 am. But it came out quite well, but leaving aside, of
                        course, the key issue of Taiwan where there's still a major gap.</p>
                    <p>By the way, there was heightened security in Beijing in this October trip. We
                        did not realize at the time that the Lin Biao incident was going on. And as
                        we left China, unfortunately in terms of timing, the UN vote admitted China
                        and kicked out Taiwan.</p>
                    <p>This brings me to the Nixon trip itself in February '72. It was a period of
                        great drama in U.S. diplomacy generally -- the Moscow summit a few months
                        later, ending the Vietnam War, et cetera. I've worked with several
                        presidents. I've never seen any president prepare as hard or as thoroughly
                        for a trip as Nixon did on this. We put together six huge briefing books. He
                        marked up every page. He kept asking questions as we flew across the
                        Pacific.</p>
                    <p>Mao asked to see us within an hour of our arrival, putting his stamp of
                        approval on the process. I was fortunate enough to be in that meeting but I
                        was cut out of all the pictures and communiqué because, unfortunately and
                        wrongly, Secretary Rogers was not at the meeting. This would have been a
                        further humiliation.</p>
                    <p>At first the discussion with Mao, which lasted an hour, seemed a little
                        disappointing to us. It seemed casual. He was using broad strokes and
                        allusions and anecdotes. We didn't quite get everything he was saying. But
                        as we reflected over the coming days and hours and hours of talks with Zhou
                        Enlai, we realized that Mao in a seemingly casual way had established the
                        strategic framework on all the key issues, most notably that the Taiwan
                        issue could wait and that we had a mutual concern about the polar bear to
                        their north.</p>
                    <p>In the remainder of the summit we fleshed out the rest of the communiqué,
                        including the key issue on Taiwan. And we can come back to that, but the
                        point is that both sides made concessions here. The Chinese had to put off
                        the resolution of this issue. We maintained diplomatic relations, a defense
                        treaty and arms sales, and the Chinese had to live with that. We, in turn,
                        had to make some assurances. We can come back to that.</p>
                    <p>And then the other key aspect of the communiqué was the anti-hegemony clause,
                        namely our common concern with the Russians.</p>
                    <p>So let me conclude with the impact of this trip or series of trips. It's fair
                        to say that even flying back from China, Kissinger and Nixon were worried
                        about the reaction in the United States. We didn't realize how dramatic and
                        positive the television images were and it was overwhelmingly well received
                        in the United States. Other countries begin to move quickly in our wake,
                        most notably Japan, and of course this helped Nixon get reelected but it was
                        not a major portion of that, I don't think, and that certainly wasn't his
                        reason.</p>
                    <p>But for the United States, the most immediate impact was a dramatic
                        improvement with Moscow within weeks and months, a Berlin agreement, an arms
                        control agreement, another summit meeting with the Russians. Taiwan was
                        shocked, of course, and it was painful for all of us, but in subsequent
                        years, thanks to their own efforts, they became a flourishing economy, a
                        flourishing democracy and they have de facto security independence. And
                        meanwhile we've moved ahead and established this extensive relationship with
                        China. I think seven presidents of both parties have performed a significant
                        and very skillful balancing act to promote both of these objectives.</p>
                    <p>With Japan it was a shock, but I would point out that we convinced in our
                        conversations Zhou that the U.S.-Japan alliance was in China's interest in
                        terms of stability in Asia and generally the U.S. military presence was in
                        China's interest. So that was a plus. Asia was more stable. Vietnam, modest
                        help, but it did help us somewhat in the agreement. And psychologically for
                        the American people, this dramatic opening put in context the necessarily
                        and inevitable sloppy close to the Vietnam War, which was a downer to say
                        the least. So while we were extricating ourselves from a corner of Southeast
                        Asia, we were opening up with this great power and one-quarter of the
                        world's people.</p>
                    <p>China, of course, got security out of this, stability around its borders,
                        allowed it concentrate on its economy, and you now see the fantastic results
                        as a result of that. And we both got out of this a more stable Asia and a
                        very rich relationship.</p>
                    <p>So, in close, I would say that the opening to China I think will stand as one
                        of the three or four most important and most positive geopolitical events
                        since World War II. Thank you. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="smyser">
                    <head>Professor Richard Smyser</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Professor Smyser, you were also on that
                        plane. I won't ask if you were second into China, but if you can give us
                        your thoughts.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">PROFESSOR RICHARD SMYSER:</hi> No, I was not even anxious
                        to be the first or the second. I was quite comfortable sitting in the plane.
                        And when Win moved up to the front of the plane, I said to Henry, "Is he
                        trying to cozy up to Mao's niece," who was sitting at the front. And Henry
                        said, "You never know what Win is up to." (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>As it turned out of course, his purpose was even more sinister and so we
                        always have congratulated him on that. But I don't even know whether I was
                        the second or third or fourth, but I did know, and I remarked on this to
                        Kissinger, that the fact that Mao had sent his niece to meet us in Pakistan
                        and to accompany us on the plane, even though I should tell you she said
                        very little and did very little on the plane, I thought was of great
                        significance and Henry obviously also took that on.</p>
                    <p>For your amusement, I did have a chat with her, sort of as casual as one
                        could be, and I said to her, "I hope that all this means that someday you
                        will visit the United States." And, "Do you have any particular places you
                        would like to go?" I was kind of intrigued to see what she would say. And
                        she replied, "I am sure a program will be made for me." (Laughter.) Which is
                        a very interesting kind of comment of the kind of tension that still existed
                        in the relationship. She had to be very, very careful what she said.</p>
                    <p>Now, I had a special role for Henry in this particular thing and that was
                        that he wanted me along in case Vietnam came up. He was going to talk about
                        Vietnam and about the war in Vietnam, and he wanted me to be there to help,
                        of course, with any comments and also to answer any questions that Zhou
                        Enlai might have. The latter purpose really turned out to be not so
                        necessary because all the questions could be answered by Dr. Kissinger
                        himself, but still it was a kind of reassurance.</p>
                    <p>And I think if you don't mind, I'm going to talk mainly about the Vietnam
                        aspect of this trip, which was I thought an important aspect. At the time
                        that we took this trip, the U.S. had been involved heavily in a war in
                        Vietnam for a number of years. To you this is ancient history. To those of
                        us who were involved in it at the time, it was a pressing issue that
                        occupied all television stations every night and all our concerns every day.
                        And we had been trying to find a negotiated settlement. In Paris there were
                        some talks, negotiations which were mostly fruitless because there was a
                        delegation led by a man called Xuan Thuy who was kind of a Vietnamese
                        version of Andrei Gromyko, if this gives you some idea of how useful it was
                        to talk to him.</p>
                    <p>But from time to time, somebody else would appear. His name was Le Duc Tho.
                        Le Duc Tho, whom we called "Ducky," was a member of the North Vietnamese
                        Politburo. He was one of its principal ideologues and he would appear in
                        Paris from time to time. and we decided -- Henry and Nixon decided that they
                        would want to meet with him. And so beginning in 1970, we began meeting with
                        Le Duc Tho, and those meetings had two marks to them. First of all, of
                        course, the discussion was much more open, much more frank; and secondly,
                        you had the feeling that you were talking to somebody who was serious and
                        who was in a position to take on what you said and to do something about
                        it.</p>
                    <p>One of the interesting things about this negotiation is that after we had
                        been doing it for about, oh, six to nine months or a year, all of a sudden,
                        instead of sitting in easy chairs like these opposite each other in the
                        living room of the Vietnamese residence in the suburbs of Paris, we found
                        ourselves sitting around a green table, which was a sign that the Vietnamese
                        were beginning to realize that the negotiations were serious.</p>
                    <p>Now, the problem for us was the relationship to all this of the Soviets and
                        of the Chinese, or at least this was one of the problems. And the Soviets
                        were playing a double game. They would come to us and say, oh yes, we want
                        to help you negotiate, we're trying to do everything we can, we're using our
                        influence. They said this consistently to Ambassador Averell Harriman, who,
                        for a long time, tried to lead the negotiations and who thought there might
                        be an opening there.</p>
                    <p>But at the same time that they were doing that and making nice noises, they
                        were also providing the Vietnamese, the North Vietnamese, with the weapons
                        that destroyed our aircraft and with the weapons which enabled them to
                        conduct massive warfare in South Vietnam. They had anti-aircraft missiles,
                        the SAMs and other weaponry which enabled the Vietnamese to continue the war
                        and also, of course, enabled them to inflict heavy casualties upon us.</p>
                    <p>This was a double game. The Chinese were not playing a double game. The
                        Chinese message was very simply. This is "people's war." Lin Biao even wrote
                        a booklet about it which everybody read for a long time in the State
                        Department. People's war meant a war that would end when the people won
                        because the enemies got too exhausted they could no longer fight. And Mao
                        and everybody in China said consistently -- publicly, privately, in every
                        way -- this war cannot be ended by negotiations; anybody who negotiates is a
                        traitor to people's war; the only way to end this war is to win it and to
                        fight. That was the Chinese line.</p>
                    <p>We had the impression as we were flying across to Peking, as we then called
                        it, and as we discussed the meeting in advance that the Chinese were
                        becoming increasingly uncomfortable with this position, because the longer
                        the war went on, the more Soviet weapons poured into Vietnam, and the more
                        the Soviets relied -- the Vietnamese relied upon the Soviets for
                        weaponry.</p>
                    <p>So we felt that there was perhaps an opening here to ease the Chinese
                        resistance to negotiations. And so Kissinger in the meeting with Zhou Enlai
                        -- and I frankly don't know whether this is going to be in the FRUS
                        documents that you're releasing or not -- said the war can end in two ways.
                        One is by continuing the fight, and that will last a long, long time. The
                        other way is through negotiations, and that will be shorter.</p>
                    <p>It is clear that Zhou Enlai, whose eyes were always interesting to watch,
                        took this on and understood exactly what it meant. Now, what he said, of
                        course, was what we knew he would say, which was the Vietnamese make their
                        own decisions, we support them, they are fighting in a just cause, you are
                        not fighting in a just cause, you should leave. But nonetheless, we had the
                        distinct impression that Zhou Enlai knew exactly what we were talking about
                        and knew exactly what the implications would be for the Chinese position in
                        Indo-China, for the Chinese position in North Vietnam and for the Chinese
                        position in the world.</p>
                    <p>Now, obviously nothing changed overtly. But interestingly enough, when the
                        negotiations, the serious negotiations actually did begin later, the Chinese
                        eased their opposition. Now, this may have been because they said, well, the
                        Vietnamese want negotiations, we will support them. But we also felt that it
                        was because they understood that a shorter war, a war which the Soviets
                        would not be able to dominate by the weaponry that they could supply and
                        that the Chinese could not, would be in their interest.</p>
                    <p>Curiously enough, there's a couple things that might be amusing in this which
                        I want to mention. I'm not sure that they're amusing in a funny way, but
                        interesting. One thing that Zhou Enlai said to Kissinger was that he did not
                        know of the negotiations that we were conducting through Le Duc Tho. I have
                        never known whether he was conducting what some people called the classic
                        diplomatic obfuscation campaign or whether it was true, but I suspect it may
                        well have been true because the Vietnamese, knowing of the great Chinese
                        opposition to the negotiations, any negotiations, might well have felt that
                        the best thing to do was not to tell them about it. The other question that
                        it raises, of course, was whether, in fact, Chinese intelligence was not
                        terribly good, because these talks were going on in Paris, they had a
                        mission in Paris, and while, of course, we were able to keep them from the
                        press and from associated other people, nonetheless I should have thought
                        that the Chinese, if they had a really good intelligence service, would have
                        known about them. But they didn't.</p>
                    <p>We did meet with Le Duc Tho in Paris after coming out of Beijing. It was
                        arranged by Dick Walters, General Walters, known to most of you and will be
                        in the FRUS, I am quite sure, who used a very simple ploy. We all went to
                        the ambassador's residence for lunch and then the word was that Dr.
                        Kissinger was going to rest and the press were told, "Or you can leave." And
                        they said ha, ha, ha, ha, we're not that stupid, we're going to watch him
                        when he leaves. And so a team of press stayed at the front door of the
                        residence. But the residence had a back entrance which was a garage, so Dick
                        Walters arranged for a car to come into the garage. Henry slumped down on
                        the floor between you and me -- you may remember that -- because they
                        figured you and I were not recognizable to anybody but Henry certainly
                        was.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Speak for yourself. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SMYSER:</hi> I'm merely saying what they thought, not
                        necessarily what you thought. (Laughter.) But nonetheless, we were able to
                        get out, have a meeting with Le Duc Tho and then afterwards return to the
                        residence. And that evening, Henry had dinner with a young lady, an NBC
                        correspondent, as I recall, in a Paris restaurant and was accused by some
                        woman who shook her hand at him of not doing enough for peace. So this shows
                        about how things are.</p>
                    <p>I don't want to cover any more because I don't have much time, but I just
                        want to mention that one of the most interesting things to all this was the
                        Japanese reaction. And it was a reaction which I can best describe as real
                        genuine concern as to what this meant for the stability of Asia and also
                        really genuine concern that their principal ally, the United States, had
                        done this and not told them about it earlier. I remember in the ensuing
                        weeks I had several conversations with Japanese diplomats who came to my
                        office who wanted very, very much to talk about this subject. I'm sure you
                        had the same. And this was a genuine concern of our allies about things that
                        we had done which they thought we should have told them about. Obviously we
                        couldn't tell them for all the reasons that you know, but there we are.</p>
                    <p>Now, I wanted to mention one other thing. I have to leave early because I now
                        teach at Georgetown University and I have a class, a seminar, this
                        afternoon. So if I disappear, it is not in protest at what anybody is
                        saying, especially Winston Lord who of course is obstreperous as always --
                        (laughter) -- but simply because I do have to leave. But I did want to cover
                        this subject because it was an interesting and important aspect of what we
                        were trying to do. Thank you very much. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="scowcroft">
                    <head>Lt. General Brent Scowcroft</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Why don't we move a little bit
                        chronologically. General Scowcroft, could you give us your thoughts?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LT. GENERAL BRENT SCOWCROFT:</hi> Sure. I figured I would
                        sort of be last, but --</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> We knew you didn't like sitting on the left,
                        so -- (laughter)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Well, yeah, let me tell you a little bit
                        about my involvement. It started -- I arrived at the White House the day
                        before the advance trip for China left to prepare for President Nixon's
                        visit. And I was on that so I started out my introduction to the White House
                        was identical with my introduction to China. I was not an august colleague
                        of either Win Lord's or Dick Smyser, however. I was -- I had an
                        administrative job in the White House. I was the military assistant to the
                        President and in charge of logistics, Air Force One, Camp David, the motor
                        pool, the mess hall -- all the kinds of things that Defense used to support
                        the President. So that was the reason I was on the mission. I also provided
                        the aircraft for Dick Smyser to go to Paris quietly without anybody finding
                        out what they were doing. So that was my involvement in the early days.</p>
                    <p>But principally it came later on in the administration of President Bush and
                        especially related to Tiananmen Square. When Bush came into office,
                        relations with China were pretty good. In fact, they were quite good. As Win
                        Lord said, you know, we've had seven presidents reaffirm the general
                        direction of our relations with China, but they didn't all start out that
                        way. Reagan, for example, started out as a strong -- when he campaigned, a
                        strong proponent of Taiwan, so strong that he sent his vice presidential
                        candidate, who was then George Bush, over to Deng Xiaoping to explain that
                        this was just campaign rhetoric and so on and so forth. And actually, Bush
                        was in the meeting with Deng Xiaoping and an aide came in and gave Deng --
                        after Bush had just explained this didn't mean anything, he said, "He's done
                        it again." So this was an education process for several of our presidents to
                        the realities of the relationship and how fundamental it was, and that says
                        a lot.</p>
                    <p>So when Bush came into office in 1989, one of the first things we wanted to
                        do was to meet with the Chinese. Because just before inauguration day, it
                        had been announced that the Soviets -- Gorbachev was going to come to China
                        in March, I think it was, for a state visit. We wanted to get there ahead of
                        time, but how can you do that with a President, brand new, just inaugurated,
                        to jump on a plane and go to a trip to China. Well, the Japanese Emperor
                        obliged us by succumbing and we went to the funeral, and immediately after
                        the funeral we went on to China. And it was a great visit. Win, you should
                        have talked about that. Win was the ambassador at that time.</p>
                    <p>But one special thing, President Bush wanted the Chinese to know how close he
                        felt to them, so he brought a special dinner along, a Texas barbecue,
                        complete with the checkered tablecloths. The whole thing was flown in. Well,
                        I don't know about you, but the Chinese I sat with looked at it and poked at
                        it and pushed it around and didn't touch it. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>Anyway, shortly after that came Tiananmen Square. It was a serious crisis in
                        the relationship. We had to respond. It was an outrageous act. But President
                        Bush felt he had to respond but he did not want to sever this relationship
                        which had been gradually built up and gradually deepened. So we imposed
                        sanctions, but they were primarily sanctions against the military
                        relationship, military supplies and things like that, on the grounds that it
                        was the military who had moved in to Tiananmen Square and therefore they
                        were the -- they should bear the brunt of it.</p>
                    <p>But at the same time he was deeply worried that this relationship would be
                        destroyed, so he tried to call Deng Xiaoping on the telephone. Well, the
                        Chinese said, "Our leaders don't talk on the telephone." So what to do? So
                        finally, he asked me to go over to the embassy and I did, and there's a
                        little park in front of the embassy here, as some of you know, and there's a
                        big statue of the Lady of Freedom from Tiananmen Square, you know, up there
                        and all kinds of placards and so on and so forth. It was like walking
                        through a bomb field.</p>
                    <p>So I went in and explained to the ambassador that we didn't like what they
                        did, we had demonstrated we didn't like what they did, but nevertheless we
                        wanted to sustain our relationship. And if the Chinese leaders were
                        amenable, we would be prepared to send an emissary quietly to talk to them.
                        In less than 24 hours, a note came from Deng Xiaoping, yes, we'd be happy
                        to.</p>
                    <p>So Larry Eagleburger, who was Deputy Secretary of State, and I went over
                        there. We went on a C-141 with aerial refueling so we didn't have to land
                        anywhere between Washington and Beijing. The Chinese President told me later
                        that as we were approaching the entryway in through Shanghai that he got a
                        call from the border patrols that an unknown aircraft was approaching,
                        should they shoot it down. (Laughter.) And he said, no, let it through.</p>
                    <p>So we got there and had a fascinating set of discussions with both Deng
                        Xiaoping and Li Peng. And Deng Xiaoping said, "I'm not longer in the
                        government. I agreed to meet with you because you're an old friend, but I
                        want to tell you Tiananmen has absolutely nothing to do with you. It's an
                        internal matter. It doesn't affect you and you're interfering in our
                        business."</p>
                    <p>So I said, "Yes, you're right. It's an internal matter absolutely. But the
                        external effects of what you have done are of great concern to us and that's
                        why I'm here." So we had a long, long discussion for two days. It was not a
                        negotiating session, but what it was as a demonstration of the depth of the
                        relationship and that somehow we needed to get past this bad chapter.</p>
                    <p>Move ahead six months. We wanted to see if we could get something going with
                        the Chinese again so that -- so President Bush took the opportunity of the
                        Soviet summit at Malta to tell the Chinese he'd be happy to send somebody to
                        report to the Chinese about that summit. So the Chinese said yes, we'd like
                        that. And I went again this time, this time publicly, and then we did engage
                        in negotiations. It was still a difficult time.</p>
                    <p>When I got there, there was an American film crew in China. I can't remember
                        why they were there, but anyway the Chinese asked if they could film our
                        proceedings. And I said no, but it's all right -- you can film our first --
                        the opening session which is, you know, you sit down and have tea and
                        exchange pleasantries, and then you adjourn. So they said fine.</p>
                    <p>Well, they filmed that. And then as we were having our first dinner, as a
                        part of the first dinner, of course, the Chinese custom is that you have
                        toasts. Well, just as I was lifting a glass to respond to the Chinese toast,
                        in came the camera crew. And I thought: What do I do? Do I put my glass
                        down, refuse to toast, destroy my mission? Or do I go ahead and toast and
                        be, in return, toasted by the American press? Well, I chose the latter, and
                        boy, was I toasted.</p>
                    <p>Anyway, that session in negotiating principally with Qian Qichen, we came up
                        with a roadmap to renormalize our relations. They would do something, we
                        would respond, then we'd do something, they would respond, and so on. But
                        after the first couple of steps came the Romanian coup against Ceausescu and
                        I think the Chinese up to that point had been fairly relaxed about what was
                        going on in Eastern Europe because a lot of the other leaders were sort of
                        not pure communist. But Ceausescu, you know, a real down-to-earth communist,
                        he would survive. Well, when he didn't, I think they panicked. And the
                        roadmap stopped and then it was a very slow, gradual process to get back to
                        normal relations.</p>
                    <p>I think what it shows is that despite ups and downs -- and Philip Zelikow
                        didn't mention all of the downs, he made it sound sort of easy. There have
                        been some really, really rough spots in this relationship. But I think the
                        fact that it has endured shows that it is deeply important both to the
                        United States and China, and it won't survive any blows that either side can
                        strike at it but it's strong enough to endure most of them. So I'm proudly
                        optimistic for the future. Thank you. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="brzezinski">
                    <head>Dr. Zbigniew Brezinski</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> I understand, unfortunately, that Dr.
                        Brzezinski is going to have to leave us a bit early too, but maybe you could
                        go now.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">DR. ZBIGNIEW BRZEZINSKI:</hi> Thank you very much. I'm a
                        little baffled by the chronology. We started off by talking about the early
                        '70s and then we moved to the late '80s and now we're moving back to the
                        second half of the '70s.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> I just had to talk about something I knew.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">BRZEZINSKI:</hi> I suppose that is a device to keep
                        everybody alert and wondering as to what is happening. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>I very much agree with Brent that the American-Chinese relationship is not
                        only important, in all probability enduring, but it is also susceptible to
                        ups and downs, because it is an important but delicate relationship with a
                        lot of sensitivities and not always entirely identical national
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>Beyond that, I think it is also important to recognize that that relationship
                        has been evolving over now more than 30 years and it hasn't become what it
                        is today all at once as a consequence of the first Kissinger trip to China.
                        Winston, in summarizing the significance of that trip, recounted all of the
                        beneficial consequences that subsequently followed, but I think it is
                        important to recognize that the trip opened the doors to these beneficial
                        consequences but didn't cause all of them. There was a great deal left still
                        undone after that visit and the beginning of the political relationship that
                        it initiated.</p>
                    <p>To some extent, one might think here of the difference at least in the old
                        days between a romantic first kiss and going to bed. Now, I realize that
                        these days the two are conflated -- (laughter) -- but there was a time when
                        there was at least a decent interval between the two. (Laughter.) And I
                        think that going to bed actually occurred, in fact, in the second half of
                        the '70s. We had by then a political relationship with the Chinese, a very
                        important accomplishment, historically significant accomplishment. But
                        that's what it primarily was. And by the middle of the '70s there was a
                        sense, especially among the Chinese leaders but also to some extent here,
                        that it either had to move forward or it was facing the risk of in some
                        fashion receding.</p>
                    <p>And that brought up the question whether to move from a political
                        relationship that was fruitful and important to formal normalization which
                        would resolve some of the still highly unresolved issues that the political
                        relationship had put creatively aside. The Carter Administration in the
                        first year hesitated. It was inclined to pursue normalization but it decided
                        that with the Panama Canal treaties coming up, with the SALT negotiations
                        ongoing but difficult, that perhaps it would overload the circuits to try
                        it.</p>
                    <p>But after some hesitation, it nonetheless sort of halfheartedly decided to
                        explore the possibility of normalization, and that was the purpose of the
                        Secretary of State's visit to China in August of '77. But because it was
                        somewhat halfhearted and unclear, it did not produce the progress that had
                        been hoped. And that led then in 1978 to the President sending me to China,
                        not without some prior encouragement, in fact, of him by me, which took a
                        little time and required building some coalitions within the Administration,
                        particularly with the Vice President and the Secretary of Defense, because
                        the Secretary of State was not particularly enthusiastic about the idea of
                        my going to China.</p>
                    <p>But ultimately the President decided early in '78 that I should go to China
                        and that I should push the process of normalization forward, and then as he
                        became engaged in discussing the modalities of my trip he became quite
                        enthusiastic and really insistent that a complete breakthrough in
                        relationships be sought as the purpose of the mission and perhaps even more
                        than that.</p>
                    <p>And that led actually to my visit to China. It was unclear whom I would see,
                        whether it would be the Chinese Foreign Minister or whether I would be
                        received by Deng. But as it turned out, I spent a great deal of time with
                        Deng both formally and then later more informally in a private supper that
                        he gave for me. And we had begun to establish somewhat of a personal
                        relationship even. At one point he simply said to me that perhaps he's
                        already too old ever to contemplate the possibility of visiting the United
                        States, but still he hopes that maybe that will come to pass. And I told him
                        that if the relationship that we are now beginning to undertake to construct
                        actually bears fruit, I would hope he would come to the United States and
                        come and have dinner with me in my house.</p>
                    <p>We then initiated a secret negotiating process controlled largely out of the
                        White House, and that took the next few months. The Secretary of State
                        submitted a memorandum urging that it be finished by December '78. I mention
                        that quite deliberately because it is sometimes alleged that this
                        normalization was artificially accelerated for other reasons by me, but it
                        was a date actually agreed to by the President on the basis of the Secretary
                        of State's recommendation.</p>
                    <p>In the course of these negotiations, we were able to work out some
                        arrangement for Taiwan that would, in fact, ensure its continued existence.
                        We made it very clear to the Chinese that while we expected to reduce,
                        perhaps at some point even terminate, arms sales to Taiwan, we reserved the
                        right to continue selling arms to Taiwanese, an issue which even on the day
                        before formal announcement produced a last-minute attempt by the Chinese to
                        reinterpret that part of the agreement. And we also made it clear to the
                        Chinese that while Taiwan is an internal Chinese affair in keeping with the
                        protocols which were undertaken in Shanghai by Nixon and Kissinger, that we
                        would not be indifferent if force was used in the Taiwan Straits against
                        Taiwan because it would affect our interests in the Far East.</p>
                    <p>In effect, the agreement to normalize relationship reversed the existing
                        situation. Heretofore the United States had no diplomatic relations with
                        China in a normal fashion, but only a political presentation, and it was
                        recognizing Taiwan, in effect, as the government of the Republic of China.
                        We had somewhat limited commercial relations. They were beginning to open up
                        but were still lacking a formal context and the benefits of full
                        normalization. And most important of all, we did not have a strategic
                        relationship of any substance. And that emerged as a consequence of
                        normalization and the kind of reaction to the existing strategic context
                        both of the United States and of the Chinese. The Soviet Union was on a
                        roll, or so it seemed. It was becoming more assertive, and in different ways
                        the Chinese and we were concerned about it.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese also decided, of course, to use normalization of relations to
                        exploit their own specific interests in Southeast Asia. When Deng Xiaoping
                        and his wife came to have dinner at my house, and you referenced about the
                        Texas cookout that the President sent over to Deng, it reminded me of what
                        happened at that dinner. Namely, my children were serving caviar and my
                        little daughter, who was at the time barely ten, deposited a lot of the
                        caviar on Deng Xiaoping's trousers, right on his knee. And I remember he
                        kind of flicked it off very, very skillfully. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">PANELIST:</hi> Was it Russian caviar?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">BRZEZINSKI:</hi> It was Russian caviar and it was Russian
                        vodka, and I told Deng Xiaoping that we're celebrating the new strategic
                        relationship with Russian vodka and Russian caviar, which he welcomed. He
                        incidentally was very quick in conversations. At one point the conversation
                        kind of lapsed a little bit, became a little stale, formal. So to liven it
                        up, I said to him, "You know, the President of the United States has a lot
                        of political problems normalizing relations with you because there's a lot
                        of political opposition in the United States centering on the issue of
                        Taiwan. Do you have any political problems normalizing relations with us?" I
                        thought I was kind of tweaking him. And he looks me in the eye, and just
                        like that he says, "Well, of course. There was a great deal of political
                        opposition in the province of Taiwan." (Laughter.) He was quick. He was
                        quick. The next day when the President at a formal meeting brought up the
                        question of emigration from China, kind of parallel to the Soviet Union, he
                        kind of sat there, looked at him, then leaned forward and says, "Fine, next
                        year I'll allow 10 million to emigrate. Will you take them?" (Laughter.) And
                        we kind of decided to go on to the next item on the agenda.</p>
                    <p>But he requested the night before a private meeting with the President and I
                        told the President the next day that he wants a private meeting. And the
                        President asked me, "What do you think he wants?" And I said, "I suspect
                        it's going to be about Vietnam." So the President said I should be there,
                        and I was. And Deng Xiaoping then told the President that he's going to
                        shortly undertake a punitive expedition against Vietnam similar to the one
                        that China pursued in the early '60s against India. And I remember the
                        President was not too happy because he thought that normalization of
                        relations with China, in addition to a strategic relationship, was a
                        contribution to world peace and he wasn't enamored of the thought that for
                        Deng it was an opportunity to undertake a military campaign.</p>
                    <p>So he said to him, "Well, you know, this could produce very serious
                        reactions. The Soviet Union could react, and very, very adversely and there
                        could be serious problems." And Deng looked at him kind of in his very
                        steely fashion and says, "We have thought about it. What can the Soviets
                        do?" "Well, they can send arms to the Vietnamese." "That's no problem
                        because we're going to do it for just five or six weeks. We'll go in, we'll
                        go out, so those arms will have no effect."</p>
                    <p>"Secondly, if that isn't enough, they might stage intensified border
                        incidents between us and the Soviet Union." "We've thought about that. That
                        doesn't worry us. Since 1969 there have been 5,000 border incidents with the
                        Soviet Union, some of them lethal, so some more won't bother us."</p>
                    <p>"Thirdly, we have contemplated the possibility that they may actually use
                        their armored divisions -- they have 22 poised on the Sino-Soviet frontier,
                        a lot of them in Mongolia, so kind of pointed towards Beijing -- into China
                        in order to intimidate us. And in which case we will wage a people's war and
                        drown them."</p>
                    <p>"And last, they may use nuclear weapons against us. We don't have many
                        nuclear weapons," he says, "but we have enough, for example, to take our
                        Bratsk, which is the huge hydroelectric dam or maybe a city like Sverdlovsk
                        or maybe Moscow." And the President I felt was somewhat less enthused at
                        that moment about the relationship, but nonetheless it survived and it
                        continued to thrive.</p>
                    <p>Let me conclude by adding that it not only thrived on this sort of general
                        level but it produced immediately afterwards a very extensive intelligence
                        relationship between the United States and China which was extremely
                        beneficial, extremely beneficial, especially in view of the loss of the
                        intelligence facilities that took place at the time in Iran. And it was more
                        than a replacement for that. And this produced also an intelligence
                        cooperative relationship which previously had not existed.</p>
                    <p>And secondly and subsequently, it produced American-Chinese direct
                        collaboration in generating efforts to make the Soviet invasion of
                        Afghanistan very costly to the Soviets. We and the Chinese worked very
                        closely on that.</p>
                    <p>A final point. Very much like the early opening, this was a politically
                        sensitive undertaking, the normalization of relations with China, the
                        abandonment of the security treaty with Taiwan, the termination of
                        diplomatic relations with Taiwan. It was sensitive, much like the initial
                        Kissinger mission. And for that reason it could not be entrusted, and I hate
                        to say it in this building, to the State Department. And that was an
                        explicit presidential decision, very much as in the case of Nixon and the
                        first opening, it was run out of the White House, confined just to very few
                        people.</p>
                    <p>And I daresay it probably wouldn't have been successful if it had been
                        undertaken otherwise because the issue was so politically charged -- when we
                        were doing it, it was certainly charged. When Nixon and Kissinger were doing
                        it -- that we probably wouldn't have been successful in pursuing it had it
                        been done openly through normal diplomatic channels, and we certainly would
                        have been paralyzed by opposition and the conditionalities involved in
                        establishing the relationship might have been much more difficult for both
                        sides to accept. Thank you. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="freeman">
                    <head>Ambassador Charles Freeman</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Ambassador Freeman.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR CHARLES FREEMAN:</hi> General Scowcroft and Dr.
                        Brzezinski have said just about everything I wanted to say, but before you
                        get your hopes up and think I won't say anything, I'm afraid this leaves me
                        with no alternative but to address the topic of the conference, so I
                        will.</p>
                    <p>I would start by saying that I wondered why I was invited to this, if not for
                        comic relief than perhaps because I probably have the greatest continuity of
                        involvement with China and this relationship of any Chinese language officer
                        in the Foreign Service. I became interested in the opening to China in the
                        fall of 1964 when I was attempting to find reasons to leave Harvard Law
                        School and discovered strategic geometry. And it seemed obvious to me that
                        if there were three powers, two of which (a) and (b) were at odds, and (c)
                        was at odds with both, that (a) and (b) would either have to attempt a new
                        relationship with (c), and I decided I wanted to be there when that
                        happened. And by a stroke of great luck, I was, as a worker bee and as
                        interpreter mostly for Secretary Rogers. So I was involved for 15 years off
                        and on during the Nixon period, later opening the liaison office in Beijing,
                        as Director for Chinese Affairs here, as Chargé and DCM in Beijing, and
                        later in 1993, ten years after that, as Assistant Secretary of Defense
                        reopening military dialogue with the Chinese.</p>
                    <p>I'm going to speak about three basic points in light of this. First,
                        underneath the very large relationships and issues that are discussed in the
                        Foreign Relations volume and which have been discussed today, of course
                        there is a great deal of texture and detail. I counted 41 separate signals
                        to the Chinese bureaucratically in preparation for the opening that
                        Kissinger and Nixon brokered. When you work in the government, the last
                        thing on earth you want to have happen is somebody notice you, and so I
                        wrote an article about this and felt very good that no one ever noticed it.
                        But for anyone who's interested, all 41 moves are detailed in something
                        called Sino-American Normalization and Its Policy Implications, which was a
                        book that came out in the mid '70s.</p>
                    <p>This was an interesting process. When you try to turn the ship of state, a
                        lot of people have to run around and pull lines and reset things and it
                        doesn't happen easily. And I think in my case I was called back from home
                        leave early in April of 1971 for reasons which were not explained on the
                        telephone, but I ended up basically working full time for Dr. Kissinger
                        without his being aware of that because the boss in the office at that time,
                        Al Jenkins, claimed he was doing all the work on his own and I had to
                        pretend to my colleagues that I was doing special projects. And so at any
                        rate, it wasn't the case, I think, that Kissinger didn't know how to use the
                        State Department or didn't; he used it a great deal, but he used it outside
                        the chain of command. What I did never went up to the seventh floor, nor did
                        what Jenkins did go up to the seventh floor.</p>
                    <p>In fact, in preparation for the Nixon trip, to jump ahead a little bit, I
                        looked at the fitness report for that year. It says that I wrote 47 percent
                        of the material that was supplied to the President, not all of which was
                        recognized by the White House as originating at the State Department. There
                        was a habit of our colleagues in the White House of taking State
                        Department-produced material and retyping the front page so that it would
                        appear that it had been produced there.</p>
                    <p>As a result of this, something called Department of State briefing paper,
                        which is still in use, was invented by Nick Platt, then the head of the
                        Secretariat. In those days, you actually had to retype things, and this
                        managed to ensure that both the front page and the back page and everything
                        in between had to be retyped, which was too much work for our friends to
                        do.</p>
                    <p>So -- and I also, I should say, somebody at the last minute decided Mrs.
                        Nixon needed a briefing book, and I had 48 hours to write that. I wrote the
                        whole thing with a lot of help from Nagels Encyclopedia Guide, which I
                        commend to your attention.</p>
                    <p>But some of the things that happened are really quite interesting. We were
                        asked, for example, after the President made a statement about changing
                        controls on the use of the U.S. dollar by China to find out why the Treasury
                        hadn't implemented this. And I had the head of the Office of Foreign Assets
                        Control to lunch and I gave him the Presidential statement and explained it
                        to him. And he said, "This is very interesting." He said, "That may be the
                        President's policy, but it's not the Treasury's." (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>And so you shouldn't -- anyway, I'm just saying this is a very complex
                        process and I'm very pleased that some of this material at least apparently
                        is made available on an internet supplement to the volume, which undoubtedly
                        will be interesting.</p>
                    <p>Two further points. I went on this trip not as the producer of material but
                        as interpreter, but nobody ever told me that I was going to go in any
                        capacity. I found out -- this is a very secretive White House we're dealing
                        with. I found out when luggage tags were shoved through the mail slot on my
                        front door at home. Nobody told me what I was to do. I remember meeting this
                        skinny guy on a beach in Hawaii, Brent Scowcroft, I think a newly promoted
                        brigadier, and asking him if he had any idea what I was to do. And he said
                        no, no, no, as Pat Buchanan, who was the speechwriter. And I did, and I
                        learned from Pat Buchanan that he had put some of Chairman Mao's poetry,
                        with Dick Solomon's help, into the banquet toasts. And that was useful
                        information, but I didn't know what I -- didn't find out what I was to
                        do.</p>
                    <p>And in fact, when we arrived in Beijing I still didn't know what I was to do.
                        And the President didn't tell me, although we met. He went off to see
                        Chairman Mao. A banquet occurred. An hour before the banquet, I was called
                        over to the President's villa by Dwight Chapin and said -- told, "The
                        President wants you to interpret the banquet toast." And I said, "Fine. May
                        I have the text, please?" And he said, "Well, I don't think there is a text.
                        I think he's going to do it extemporaneously." And I said, "I think you're
                        quite wrong about that." (Laughter.) "But you know, really this isn't French
                        or Spanish and I really would like to look at the text if I could."</p>
                    <p>So he went back in to see the President, came out and said, "The President
                        says there is no text and he orders you to do it." (Laughter.) And I said --
                        well, mind you, I'm 28 years old. I said, "I think there's a mistake here. I
                        don't think you talked to the President." He said, "I did." He went back in,
                        came out and said, "The President orders you to interpret the speech." I
                        said, "Mr. Chapin, it might interest you to know that I wrote the original
                        draft for tonight's toast and I know that some of Chairman Mao's poetry is
                        in it, but I don't know which stanzas. And if you think I'm going to get up
                        in front of the world and ad lib Chinese poetry back from English, you're
                        out of your," and then I used a foul word, "mind." (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>Well, Mr. Chapin never explained why, but two days later the President did.
                        He apologized with tears in his eyes -- again, quite an experience for
                        someone who had expected the end of his career -- and explained that he
                        liked to appear -- he liked to memorize speeches and appear to be giving
                        them extemporaneously and that he understood I'd done a fine job and it
                        wasn't personal and so forth.</p>
                    <p>There are many other anecdotes I won't mention, and I'll just say one final
                        thing. I at least, partly because I come from a family with a long
                        involvement with China, a great grandfather who was the original designer of
                        the Three Gorges Dam for Sun Yat-sen, the founder of the Beijing University
                        Social Science Department and one of the co-founders of the Chinese steel
                        industry in the 19th century, whose ring I wear. As we drove around Beijing,
                        thought long and hard about what the impact of this visit was likely to be.
                        Never in my wildest dreams did I believe it would have the long-term impact
                        on China that it has had.</p>
                    <p>And I must say I was absolutely stunned -- Dr. Brzezinski has left -- but I
                        was absolutely stunned about six years ago in speaking with some people at
                        the Central Party School in Beijing who showed me documents from the
                        normalization period to discover that Deng Xiaoping's motivations for
                        normalization, although they were in part foreign policy related, were
                        mainly to introduce an American influence that would help a reform process
                        inside China that he sought to inaugurate.</p>
                    <p>The result, of course, has been that from that 1972 Nixon visit period when
                        China was a cultural desert, when it was a colorless and lifeless place,
                        we've seen the lights come on, the people dress up and the return of the
                        traditional philosophy of the Chinese philosopher Confucius, who said, (in
                        Chinese); that is, "Gluttony and luster, what it's all about." This is
                        something the Chinese have rediscovered with a policy and a program that are
                        based on pragmatism, eclectic borrowing from abroad, and now more and more
                        innovation.</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile, the Taiwan issue which focused -- which was the principal focus in
                        1972, seems to me to be moving toward resolution. This is an extraordinary
                        story and it's not over yet. Thank you. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="comments">
                    <head>Panelist Comments</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Thank you. Why don't we start by allowing
                        each of you to comment on what your colleagues have said. And let me please
                        encourage members of the audience, if you would like to pose a question to
                        the panel, please write it on the card and hand them in.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> I wanted to comment on something Zbig said, and
                        unfortunately he's had to leave. I caught him briefly. But I mentioned that
                        seven American presidents of both parties have carried this relationship
                        forward, and that is indeed true. And in fact, Zbig and Carter did play a
                        crucial role. I, of course, was only commenting on the '72 period.</p>
                    <p>The fact is that after this dramatic opening, Nixon indicated to the Chinese
                        he would normalize relations in his second term, and then Watergate, of
                        course, intervened and that proved impossible. And then Ford indicated he
                        would normalize relations in his next term, but he was constrained leading
                        up to that election because he was being challenged by Reagan on the right,
                        including on the Taiwan issue. And meanwhile, Deng Xiaoping was fighting a
                        succession struggle in China -- this was in the mid '70s -- with the Gang of
                        Four so he couldn't be flexible. So the Taiwan issue was strictly -- now, I
                        think Brent would agree with that. In fact, the Ford trip to Beijing,
                        through no fault of the President's, was not one of the more crowning
                        successes because both sides were constrained by their domestic
                        environment.</p>
                    <p>So it was left to the Carter Administration to take and bite the bullet on
                        normalization, both the strategic dimension which Zbig mentioned, the
                        Afghanistan and the cooperation vis-à-vis the Soviets in the intelligence
                        field, but normalization, which came under some attacks, but I and others
                        certainly supported it. And I think it was remarkable that the Carter
                        Administration managed to get in as part of the agreement the fact they
                        could continue to sell arms to Taiwan. So I just wanted to make clear that
                        important as the opening was, as I indicated in my remarks, the Carter
                        Administration and subsequent presidents, including Ford and people after
                        Carter, certainly carried this forward. Thank you.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> I'd like to make one general comment, and
                        that is it's important to remember what an emotional issue Taiwan has been
                        through all this, not just for the Chinese but for the United States. The
                        Taiwan issue came up in the late '40s really with the Chinese civil war and
                        Chiang Kai-shek and the Nationalists moving over to Taiwan. There was a
                        domestic repercussion, big debate about who lost China. That was carried
                        over into, for example, the McCarthy hearings about communist infiltration
                        of the State Department and so on. And that, plus the 20 years of hostility
                        and alienation, have left an emotional overcharge, and that has infected
                        over and over again our ability and our freedom of action on China. And
                        that's one of the reasons many of these things were done in secret.</p>
                    <p>And I remember after Tiananmen Square when Congress came back into session,
                        they passed a resolution, a law really, to allow the Chinese students who
                        were in the United States -- and there were thousands of them -- to stay
                        indefinitely. Well, we decided that would shut off all the students coming
                        because the Chinese would not permit that, so the President vetoed it. And
                        we did a head count. It was hopeless in the House. We did a head count in
                        the Senate. We counted five senators of the 35 you needed that were on our
                        side. I've never worked so hard in my life. He sustained the veto. But that
                        sort of gets overlooked in the kind of drag that there has been on this
                        relation. It is a very emotional issue in this country and residually still
                        so.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> I just wanted to make two footnotes on
                        subjects that actually Dick Smyser mentioned. One was the Japanese shock at
                        the Nixon trip. The fact is that long before the July 15, 1971 announcement
                        that Kissinger had been in Beijing, the United States had embraced the theme
                        -- some of the themes that Phil Zelikow was talking about earlier of
                        inclusion versus exclusion. And I distinctly remember a very intelligent and
                        now very famous Japanese diplomat, Sato Yukio, coming to me right after that
                        announcement and saying, "I could kick myself. You and everyone else have
                        been saying things that made it logical for this to happen." So the overall
                        policy framework had, in fact, not been anywhere near as secretive as people
                        imagined. The overall policy framework had shifted. There had been these
                        numerous signals. And if people don't take policy frameworks seriously and
                        then are surprised by things that happen as a result of them, I'm not sure
                        that that's anybody's fault but their own.</p>
                    <p>The second point is this, that when you read the volume you will find that,
                        as I think some of the introductory material suggests, there was quite an
                        effort during this entire period to keep our friends in Taiwan informed of
                        the general process and to offer reassurances about what we were not doing.
                        And I would say it's very interesting; there was a comparable effort on the
                        part of the Chinese with regard to the Vietnamese, and some years ago the
                        Vietnamese, apparently on their own, published the entire record of those
                        briefings and discussions between Beijing and Hanoi as this diplomacy we're
                        talking about unfolded. That has been translated into Chinese and I have
                        seen copies of that book in Beijing.</p>
                    <p>And my point here is that even as this material is made public and accessible
                        here, one must realize there is an enormous amount of material that has been
                        made available in China as well. And this is a story with several
                        narratives, all of which have to be read to understand what happened.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Let me comment further on the Japanese
                        dimension, which gets into the whole question of the secrecy of the trips.
                        Zbig maintained that what some of the stuff that his administration did as
                        well as the Nixon-Kissinger opener had to be secret. Other people have
                        challenged that. Let me just give the rationale. It might not be totally
                        persuasive for why this was secret, at least secret from the world.</p>
                    <p>We didn't know when we went to China in July that, in fact, it was going to
                        be able to move forward as it did. We thought we would, but it was a risky
                        gamble. It looks easy in retrospect, but it really was uncharted territory.
                        And therefore, to have a public announcement or a public trip would raise
                        expectations and it would be a tremendous diplomatic fallout if it, in fact,
                        didn't succeed, so we wanted to be sure in secret that it would work before
                        it was unveiled.</p>
                    <p>But more fundamentally, and Zbig alluded to this, if you indicate in advance
                        you're doing something as dramatic as a trip, first you have the
                        conservatives and the Taiwan lobby here, who have some genuine concerns and
                        we try to keep that into account as Chas. mentioned; nevertheless, there'd
                        be a tremendous backlash and political firestorm. After all, Kissinger's
                        bedrock support was often from this general area. And other countries,
                        including Japan and others, would be weighing in and locking us into
                        positions before we could even explore with the Chinese. So these are the
                        reasons it was kept secret. One can debate them, but I think on balance it
                        had to be done.</p>
                    <p>Now with respect to Japan, which is the most painful because we had held
                        Japan back for a decade or more saying you can't go ahead with China, and
                        then we leapfrog them and it was very embarrassing and we suffered greatly
                        in the short term. We did repair the relationship. Kissinger kept going back
                        there, and over time the Japanese moved quickly of course and the
                        relationship was repaired and the U.S.-Japan alliance, as I said, was sold
                        to the Chinese as a stabilizing factor, so this was all a plus.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, and this is retrospect -- I did not argue this at the time -- I
                        think after the secret trip and before the announcement a few days later,
                        Holdridge or I should have peeled off and been sent to Tokyo to at least
                        tell the Emperor in advance -- not the Emperor, the Prime Minister in
                        advance what was coming. He could at least then save face and said he knew
                        about it. He'd be in a tough position because would he tell his cabinet,
                        does it leak out in the Japanese press? Nevertheless, I think that might
                        have been done. You can even argue maybe send one of us low profile in
                        advance of the visit, but then again everyone was worried about the leaks
                        for the reasons we mentioned. So we paid a price temporary with Japan. That
                        is the rationale for it.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="qa">
                    <head>Question and Answer</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Okay, let me start. One -- actually, several
                        of the panelists referred to, I guess, what Dr. Brzezinski described as
                        something, it was too sensitive to be entrusted to the State Department. We
                        are in the State Department now. But General Scowcroft, I guess from your
                        perspective, did this change? I would assume it would once Dr. Kissinger
                        took over both positions simultaneously as National Security Advisor and
                        Secretary?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Well, it changed. I don't know if it
                        changed with the Department as a whole because Dr. Kissinger was Dr.
                        Kissinger and, you know, he had his group inside the State Department the
                        way he had in the NSC. But you know, I don't -- on this issue, there was no
                        fundamental difference between the NSC system and the State Department, so I
                        don't see that. I don't know. Win, maybe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Let me comment on the issue of the State
                        Department in the opening and Chas. Freeman has made his own comments on
                        this. Again, in retrospect, I think it would have been better if -- it had
                        to be closely held for reasons I've already mentioned, but we certainly
                        could have trusted, say, Marshall Green and one or two of his colleagues to
                        work with us, let Rogers know. I think it could have been kept secret and we
                        would have benefited.</p>
                    <p>Having said that, the State Department did contribute to the preparations,
                        even for the secret trip even though they didn't know about the trip. We
                        commissioned -- Holdridge and I commissioned many papers. I'm sure some are
                        written by Chas. I hadn't realized he had done absolutely everything, which
                        is quite amazing. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> Only half.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Yeah, only half. Okay, well, that's quite
                        amazing, too.</p>
                    <p>But in any event, we got some very useful stuff, including Taiwan issue, past
                        historical stuff, and we would commission that. Holdridge knew a lot about
                        China. We had CIA reports and we had outside experts ranging from a
                        professor from Michigan to André Malraux. So there was considerable
                        preparation, including by the State Department once removed getting ready
                        for the trip. Then once the secret trip had been taken, there was full
                        collaboration on the Nixon trip and of course opening up the liaison
                        offices. So it was a temporary thing.</p>
                    <p>Now, one other sore spot -- again, no one is proud of including Henry
                        Kissinger himself in his memoirs -- is cutting the State Department out of
                        the communiqué drafting in Shanghai. Now, the October part we did a lot of
                        it, but then we have to finish it off in China. I happen to think it was a
                        brilliant communiqué the way it came out, but it was a very awkward moment
                        in Hangzhou, the last stop in the President's trip, I was with Kissinger and
                        the President comes in and says, "We've got a real problem. Secretary Rogers
                        and Marshall Green think the communiqué is lousy." Now, it wasn't quite that
                        strong, but partly out of some concerns, partly out of understandable pique
                        at having been cut out and having their expertise, they wanted to reopen the
                        negotiations. So Kissinger was less than enthusiastic about this.</p>
                    <p>All he had to do was go to the Chinese, to Zhou Enlai, and say, "Look, I know
                        Mao has approved this communiqué personally. I know the entire politburo has
                        approved this communiqué personally. We're now down in Hangzhou but we'd
                        sort of like to reopen the negotiations." This was awkward. The Chinese let
                        us save face. We got some changes, the most important of which I think
                        Marshall Green put forward, which was a good suggestion. Some of the others
                        we just couldn't fundamentally change at that late stage.</p>
                    <p>We had some phrasing in there reaffirming all our alliances, like Japan, but
                        of course leaving out Taiwan. Marshall pointed out that this exception would
                        obviously be known and underlined and so I think he suggested, or Kissinger
                        agreed, or in any event we worked it out. We dropped all references to
                        alliances so that it wouldn't single out Taiwan.</p>
                    <p>And then Henry in his press conference in Shanghai took the remarkable step,
                        which he foreshadowed to the Chinese, of reaffirming our defense alliance
                        with Taiwan on Chinese soil, which is a good trick.</p>
                    <p>So that's just a long way, because I gather we're trying to look at the
                        history and the chronology here of saying the State Department did play an
                        important role and some of the being cut out was less than seemly, but in
                        any event it came out extremely well in terms of substance and long-term
                        relations.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> I think that is a very accurate description
                        of the course of events that Win has given. I would say as a general rule
                        when policy decisions, foreign policy decisions, have a very highly high
                        impact on domestic politics, there is a natural instinct in the White House
                        to manage those directly, and I think that is correct. And that certainly
                        was the case with the opening to China.</p>
                    <p>The second point I'd make, however, is that sometimes institutional rivalries
                        are a problem and I would cite here the transition between the Carter
                        Administration and the Reagan Administration when it suddenly dawned on
                        people that the only official who was going to be left after this transition
                        who knew the inner history of the U.S.-China relationship was me, Country
                        Director for China. But I had not been briefed on and knew only fragments of
                        what had been going on directly between the National Security Advisor, Mr.
                        Dr. Brzezinski, and the Chinese. And some of the programs and areas of
                        cooperation they had agreed to were quite important and quite complex.</p>
                    <p>And so I was brought over to the White House to read all the files and bring
                        myself up to speed, which was a good thing; otherwise, the government would
                        have once again administered a frontal lobotomy to itself with the
                        predictable results.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> It's a well told story that in 1954 when Zhou
                        Enlai met John Foster Dulles in Geneva and Dulles refused to shake his hand
                        that Zhou held that grudge for the next decade and a half. Could you guys
                        comment a bit about the personal dynamics between Mao and Zhou and Nixon and
                        Kissinger when they each first met?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Let me take a crack at that first. Precisely
                        because of this history of the handshake, Nixon was determined when he got
                        off the plane in February '72 to stride toward Zhou Enlai and put out his
                        hand, and it was very carefully choreographed and of course the Chinese
                        picked that up immediately.</p>
                    <p>Briefly on Mao and Zhou, and this could go on forever and I don't want to hog
                        this podium here. When we walked in with Mao, you were immediately struck by
                        his physical presence. I don't mean that he was Arnold Schwarzenegger, but I
                        do mean he was exuding authority. Now, how much of that as you figure in
                        advance this is a great historical figure and you sort of assume that, I
                        don't think it can be quantified. But I think we all felt that you'd get
                        this sense even if you didn't know who he was when you walked into the
                        room.</p>
                    <p>The interesting thing was that Zhou Enlai in his presence -- here's Zhou
                        Enlai, the most charismatic foreign diplomat I've ever seen, Kissinger says
                        the most impressive he's ever met along with de Gaulle, who dominates by his
                        intelligence, by his humor, his sense of history, his tactical <hi
                            rend="italic">sagesse</hi>, et cetera, at every meeting he's in, in the
                        presence of Mao was totally subservient, close to obsequious in his body
                        language. Extraordinary. Now, you could argue that's why he survived and he
                        was always number three and not number two and he wasn't active in his
                        youth, but we were struck by the contrast of Zhou in the meeting with the
                        Chairman as opposed to being on his own. The contrast between Mao and Zhou
                        was extraordinary. First of all, the conversations -- and I was in every one
                        between Nixon and Mao and Zhou and Kissinger and Zhou and Mao, I do think
                        will go down as some of the most extraordinary diplomatic exchanges in
                        American diplomatic history.</p>
                    <p>But they were totally different. Mao spoke in brushstrokes and, as I said, we
                        were initially sort of disappointed because he seemed very sort of casual
                        and he just would sort of go to allusions.</p>
                    <p>For example, in a later meeting he said -- as Brzezinski I think mentioned,
                        he wanted to send us ten million women to the United States and we couldn't
                        figure out what that was all about. I asked my wife who was born in Shanghai
                        and he says he's having trouble with Madame Mao. And that's of course
                        exactly he was saying -- (laughter) -- but this is the kind of thing you've
                        got to sort of figure out with Mao. And so in a seemingly casual way in that
                        one hour he hit enough points, particularly as I said on the Soviets in
                        Taiwan and a few other things like I haven't changed China -- as Nixon said
                        -- I've only changed a few things around Beijing, indicating the problems he
                        had.</p>
                    <p>So that we realized in the course of the following week in talking to Zhou
                        that he had gotten the framework he needed. But he was rough. He could use
                        scatological language and wasn't at all eloquent -- more like a union dock
                        leader but impressive in that sense. Whereas Zhou Enlai -- and now I'll stop
                        -- was extraordinarily elegant Mandarin and extremely polished and extremely
                        skillful and clever.</p>
                    <p>Finally, I'll make the point that we had no illusions however -- however
                        impressive these gentlemen were that they were not ruthless. Of course they
                        were ruthless and of course it was a very grim society that they were
                        presiding over. So we had no illusions about who we were dealing with but
                        they were impressive in their own way.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> Two quick comments. First, the interesting
                        question is not so much -- to me is not so much Mao and Zhou but Nixon, who
                        had no small talk, but was probably -- when you read the transcripts you
                        will see the quality of the man's mind in foreign affairs which is superb.
                        But he could not handle a dinner conversation, as a result of which I got a
                        lot of conversation in with Zhou Enlai at the dinner table on my own, so
                        that's the first point.</p>
                    <p>The second point I'd make is that you need to look, as you read these
                        documents, look at the structure of this meeting which is not unprecedented
                        but which is entirely appropriate. Actually FDR pioneered this during World
                        War II. That you reserve for your discussions at the summit those things on
                        which you may reach agreement. And all the disagreements, to the extent you
                        can, you shove off on the foreign ministers in a separate meeting and let
                        them yell and scream at each other and register all the points that you have
                        to go to tell your allies and friends you registered, but you don't
                        introduce this negative tone into the discussions at the top. And as I said
                        I was -- I ended up interpreting for Secretary Rogers and they were very
                        contentious discussions. But I think all of us there understood why we were
                        having them while other discussions went on elsewhere, at least I did.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Just very quickly, in '72 I did not -- was
                        not in the meeting with Mao. Zhou Enlai was obviously extremely impressive.
                        I went in with President Ford, though, in 1974. Mao had had several strokes
                        and he looked, for all intents and purposes, like a huge sack of rice
                        sitting in a chair like this. He would growl something. He had an
                        interpreter, two nurses and a doctor and they would all put their heads
                        together and converse and then decide what Mao had said and tell us all. But
                        in that meeting he made an elliptical comment about Deng Xiaoping, which in
                        retrospect said, you're purged, buddy. You may not know it but you're
                        purged, which was quite astonishing. But even then when he was half a
                        vegetable he exuded this kind of majesty which certainly didn't come from
                        his look, from anything. He was a very remarkable individual.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> One quick comment again about the Ford meeting
                        with Mao and, in fact, the last couple of meetings with Mao that Kissinger
                        had as well. He was extremely physically weak and could only grunt a few
                        words. We got a little suspicious though. He would grunt maybe three or four
                        words and then we'd get a five-minute translation from the interpreter. So
                        we figured he was saying, number one is my Taiwan my policy; number two is
                        my Soviet policy and please take it from there.</p>
                    <p>But I do want to underline it took great physical courage on his part to get
                        through these meetings but he clearly was fading at the end and, of course,
                        had a very tense relationship with Zhou Enlai as well as Deng at the
                        end.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> In the approach both to the Chinese
                        initially and then as we moved on towards normalization, were there, I
                        guess, contingency plans, plans made for exactly how to break this to the
                        Taiwanese or was it just winged on the fly when the news came out or was
                        this carefully thought out in advance?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Okay. Well, that obviously was the most painful
                        dimension of this whole opening was what it would do to Taiwan but as I've
                        said earlier they have rebounded magnificently from this diplomatic shock.
                        No, a great deal of thought was given to this.</p>
                    <p>The general strategy followed first by Kissinger and then by Nixon was in the
                        meetings with Mao and Zhou were to make some general statements of policy
                        and assurances going forward like no independence. We would not support
                        independence. We wouldn't support Japan moving in -- one China, one Taiwan
                        kind of thing -- but to say nothing that committed us to an actual act.
                        People like to think that a lot of concessions were made by Nixon and
                        Kissinger on the Taiwan issue of the Chinese; that's true, but it's equally
                        true that the Chinese made a lot of concessions.</p>
                    <p>When we first arrived in July '71, Zhou Enlai said the President can't come
                        unless he's established diplomatic relations with Beijing and broken them
                        and the defense treaty with Taiwan before he comes. Well, we got -- I don't
                        he was serious about that, but he certainly pushed us on it. For years they
                        had said in Warsaw talks and elsewhere that they wouldn't do anything with
                        us unless we resolve the issue of Taiwan, or at least Taiwan had to be the
                        only item on the agenda. And we finally resolved that through the Pakistani
                        channel as I said where we enlarged it or in the short communiqué where we
                        included not just normalization but issues of mutual concern.</p>
                    <p>So Nixon and Kissinger did have Taiwan's concerns in mind. There was no way
                        to do this without hurting Taiwan. But the strategy was figuring that that
                        the Chinese because of their desire for balancing the polar bear and the
                        general isolation would be willing to postpone the hard decisions on Taiwan
                        and, indeed, Zhou Enlai said we recognize the courage of your President
                        coming here. We won't embarrass him for now on this issue, although it
                        remains a matter of strong principle. And throughout, as I think Chas
                        mentioned, we did keep briefing the Taiwan authorities and reassuring them
                        on the basic elements of diplomatic relations, defense treaty and arms sales
                        and rounding off the edges on the general long-term assurances.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Just a quick anecdote to show that not
                        everything went smoothly on this whole thing. When there was -- debate went
                        on in the UN about transferring a seat from Taiwan to the communist,
                        President Bush was our ambassador to the UN and he was vociferously
                        defending the right of Taiwan to maintain a seat at the very time that he
                        was having the rug pulled out from under him in Washington.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> It's interesting that -- Dr. Brzezinski
                        really should be here to address this question because I think the most
                        notorious slipup was the informing of Jiang Jingguo when normalization was
                        announced. And as you know, very unusually, the communiqué issued here on
                        the 15th of December and in Beijing on the 16th of December, 1978, was dated
                        January 1, 1979. It was effective only two weeks later and it was put out in
                        large measure because of concern about possible leaks. But the means by
                        which Taipei was notified were not elegant, to put it mildly.</p>
                    <p>And I take this as an example of an issue that somewhat undercuts Dr.
                        Brzezinski's assertion that secrecy had to be followed here. In my
                        experience, the NSC can be, at its best, very good at coordinating policy;
                        it is usually miserable at implementing it. And I could give you multiple
                        examples from the course of my career, and I'm sure every other Foreign
                        Service officer could find others, where we had to behave like the little
                        guy in the Bullwinkle cartoons after the elephant, you know, sweeping up
                        what -- (laughter) -- only polite people would call debris. So there is a --
                        when our government works well, I think it works very well. It did not work
                        well in that instance and I think it's a management caution for the
                        future.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> I'm not going to respond. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> One further comment on Zhou and Mao and their
                        style because I think it was quite indicative of Zhou Enlai's skill. I
                        wanted to add on the secret trip we saw the Forbidden City all by ourselves.
                        They closed it off and we went and had a Peking duck lunch in Zhongnanhai --
                        no, at the Great Hall of the People -- anyway, it doesn't matter -- with
                        Zhou Enlai. In the course of the lunch, he talked about the Cultural
                        Revolution. Now this started in 1966 and technically wasn't over 1976,
                        although it was still going on, although by far the most rabid dimensions
                        was subsiding by '71.</p>
                    <p>He had been locked -- Zhou had been locked in his own office. He had seen
                        many of his colleagues persecuted. He had saved some people and some
                        artifacts and he was a very pragmatic person who made the trains run a
                        little bit on time in Mao's chaotic China, so obviously the Cultural
                        Revolution wasn't Nirvana for him.</p>
                    <p>On the other hand, he had a chairman -- and he always wanted to survive with
                        this chairman -- who was going to read the transcript and hear about the
                        meeting and a discussion of the Cultural Revolution at lunch. So how did
                        Zhou square this circle? It was something along the following lines. I don't
                        have it verbatim but it's in the volume, I'm sure:</p>
                    <p>You know, Dr. Kissinger, the Cultural Revolution has been very full of
                        turmoil here. And I have to say that I didn't fully understand the purpose
                        of this. It seemed to me that there are a lot of excesses and people were
                        hurt and it really had some unpleasant aspects. But that just shows you how
                        short-sighted I am compared to the chairman -- (laughter) -- because the
                        chairman understood that the bureaucracy in China was ossifying our
                        revolution, that we're going to become another Soviet Union, we had to shake
                        things up. And therefore he saw much further than I did the need to go
                        through this terrible turmoil and all the terrible things that happened and
                        he was a very wise man to do this.</p>
                    <p>So of course, he was telling us he thought the Cultural Revolution was a
                        horrible mistake, but if Mao read the transcript he'd still be safe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> And how do you put the personality of Deng
                        Xiaoping in the mix compared with Mao and Zhou?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Well, as I say, I can't compare them too
                        well because I just had one meeting with Zhou Enlai and one semi-meeting
                        with Mao. But I think Deng Xiaoping was to me very uncharacteristically
                        person for the Chinese. You know, usually when you meet with the Chinese you
                        meet in a U-shaped -- the chairs are in a U-shaped room and you and your
                        interlocutor are sitting side by side facing out. And typical Chinese --
                        they talk to the wall in front of you. Well, Deng instead would sit on the
                        edge of his chair and lean right over in your face and make his points. He
                        was very lively and so very animated. He chain smoked. I mean, literally
                        chain smoked; light one off the butt of another and he had a spittoon by
                        him. Always had a spittoon and every once in awhile he'd make a comment and
                        he turn around and puuuck. (Laughter.) So he was a remarkable
                        individual.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Let me add a few comments on that. I was at a
                        great many meeting with him. He was sort of a transition figure from Mao to
                        Deng's successes, in a sense that Deng was the last of the long marchers,
                        the charismatic revolutionary leaders and/or military leaders and so he
                        still he had those credentials unlike Jiang Zemin and others who've come
                        since then who have ascended through managing the economy or through
                        bureaucracy or through technical skills. They don't have these credentials
                        by virtual of chronology. So he was a figure that had the history and the
                        resonance and the prestige to a certain extent of Mao and Zhou, but he also
                        had some of the technocratic skills that his successors had. And of course
                        his greatest contribution was opening up China starting in 1979. A man of
                        remarkable resilience who was up and down about three or four times in the
                        course of his political career and so he had the personality that Brent has
                        mentioned and he always was stressing the importance of U.S.-China relations
                        and warning about both the Japanese and the Russians. And if there were
                        difficult times -- and we'd have them on our trips to China -- usually we'd
                        see Deng last and the atmosphere would greatly improve. He would make sure
                        these other bits of underbrush were cleared away by others.</p>
                    <p>So he will go down in history with a mixed record in my opinion. Great credit
                        for the opening -- we see the results even as we sit here today, great
                        credit for promoting U.S.-Chinese relations but always a dark stain on his
                        legacy of Tiananmen Square, which after all he ordered the army in. And it's
                        against the backdrop of political repression, generally on Deng. He was
                        Mao's front man for the '56 anti-rightist campaign. He purged Hu Yaobang and
                        Zhao Ziyang, who were relatively moderate, and he ordered the tanks into
                        Tiananmen Square so he's a got a mixed legacy.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> I have a couple of things to say. First,
                        Deng Xiaoping, blunt and direct as he was and engaging as he was, had an
                        extraordinary sense of what he was trying to accomplish. And I can recall --
                        I'll give you one anecdote with maybe a little bonus.</p>
                    <p>In August of 1981, I was chargé in Beijing. I took in several visitors to see
                        Deng Xiaoping; one of whom was Charlie Wick who was the head of USIA at the
                        time. The other was Chief Justice Burger of the Supreme Court. Deng Xiaoping
                        in the course of the conversation said flatly, "When the history of our
                        country is written, Mao Zedong will be seen as my precursor. The real
                        revolution began three years ago." And he had a sense of destiny and his
                        role in it and I think history will be kinder to him as the architect of
                        modern China than Win suggests.</p>
                    <p>The second anecdote is Charlie Wick for some reason was trying to get radio
                        transmitters installed in Shenyang to broadcast all over Central Asia and
                        the Soviet Union and, in order to persuade Deng Xiaoping of this, proceeded
                        to try to convince him of the evils of Soviet communism. And Deng Xiaoping
                        interrupted him -- and this is the blunt part -- and said, "Young man," --
                        Charlie was only in his sixties, I think -- he said, "Young man, at age 23,
                        I was Secretary General of the Chinese Communist Party and I was purged
                        because of my opposition to the Soviet communism and that happened to me two
                        other times. And there is no need for you to tell me about the evils of
                        Soviet communism. Now what do you really want?" And then we had a
                        discussion. But the man had a way of cutting through what a lot of people
                        don't and coming straight to the point and letting you know exactly where
                        you stand.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> If I could just add one point. I do agree
                        with Win that he's a mixed record figure, but I think my sense is he's the
                        true revolutionary in China, not Mao. Mao was a sort of continuation of the
                        imperial thing. Deng changed things. And when he decided that the stability
                        of the country, the stability of the regime depended on economic progress,
                        on giving the average Chinese the sense that his life was getting better,
                        his standard of living was going up; that was the real revolution in China.
                        And when he said, you know, to get rich is glorious, they have followed
                        through on that and that is why China is the powerhouse it is now. Now
                        that's creating its own problems now because the Communist Party out in the
                        field and so on still believe his dictum -- to get rich is glorious, so
                        they're cooperating with the local government people to seize land and sell
                        it to developers and so on because they're being judged on how much is your
                        province producing in terms of increasing GNP. So he's creating enormous
                        problems now, but I think he more than any other individual is responsible
                        for the China today.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Just a more general question. What were --
                        I guess your expectations before you made these trips, before the first
                        trip, before the normalization trip and how did the results measure up with
                        your expectations before hand? From your perspectives were these, you know,
                        total successes or did it not quite go as you had expected or did you have
                        any expectations?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Well, if we can start chronologically with the
                        first secret trip or Nixon trip, it certainly exceeded everyone's
                        expectations, and they were quite large, of the positive reaction not only
                        around the world but in the United States. As I said earlier, Nixon and
                        Kissinger were still fretting on the way back on the plane how this was
                        going to be received in the U.S. And so in that respect, although I thought
                        -- they figured it would be very positively generally in the world, they
                        were worried about the domestic reaction and that was very positive. There
                        were some people worried about it, but on a whole, as I said, it put Vietnam
                        in a context and it was a dramatic -- to show that we were not crippled by
                        that war, et cetera.</p>
                    <p>Japan's reaction I think was predictable and I think could have been
                        moderated somewhat, but sort of like Taiwan that was inevitable. I think the
                        positive impact which we didn't predict by any means fully was the impact on
                        the Soviets. We were trying to open up in China precisely to improve
                        relations with the Soviets, not to hurt them. But I don't think anyone
                        thought that within a matter of -- literally of months, in some cases weeks,
                        we just moved ahead across the board with the Soviets on Berlin, on arms
                        control, on economic agreements and on a summit meeting.</p>
                    <p>Finally, on Vietnam, the other key issue and expectation, I think the
                        President always put more weight, particularly with the Russians helping us
                        on Vietnam and to a certain extent, Chinese and Kissinger who felt they
                        probably wouldn't. So I think the results in Vietnam were about what we
                        would have expected namely, that they wouldn't cut off aid to their lips and
                        teeth ally. We didn't realize fully just how bad relations were and they
                        were in a competition with Moscow.</p>
                    <p>But we did feel -- and I think they did weigh in and it helped modestly in
                        Hanoi along the following lines. Look, the Americans have made an offer to
                        get out and we've made this offer of a ceasefire and withdrawal unilaterally
                        and prisoners of war being returned in May '71. And we kept emphasizing to
                        the Chinese and I think they relayed to Hanoi that this was a significant
                        achievement for them.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese felt, I think -- and we would tell them this, Kissinger
                        explicitly and Nixon -- that if we go further and overthrow Thieu and put in
                        a coalition government, which was the Vietnamese demand until late '72 and
                        then they finally moved because they saw McGovern wasn't going to get in and
                        Nixon was going to be there again, this would humiliate the U.S., we'd be
                        less able to balance the Soviet Union in China's own interest.</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, as Smyser pointed out, it was in China's interest to get this
                        war over with, competition with the Russians and it was ideologically
                        awkward for us to be fighting the supposed ally near their borders. So for
                        all these reasons, we hope that China would help. It was a modest help, but
                        not insignificant. And therefore, the expectations I think were mixed. In
                        some cases, we did better than we thought. Other cases, not as well. But
                        over the long run, of course, the full promise and the distant horizon of
                        this relationship has been more than fulfilled in a very positive sense.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> Just one comment. Counselor Zelikow in his
                        talk quoted the State Department drafted response to NSM 14. That was
                        actually drafted by the late Paul Kreisberg. And as you will recall, the
                        point was to speculate in August of 1969 contrary to the conventional wisdom
                        at the time that the United States might actually benefit by the end of
                        Chinese isolation and the inclusion of China in the regional and
                        international system. I think it's fair to say that the greatest success and
                        the greatest surprise of American policy going back to those early days is
                        the amazing extent to which that happened.</p>
                    <p>China which in 1971 and '2 was full of billboards announcing that the people
                        want liberation and revolution and what not and which was involved with the
                        Puerto Rican independence movement and all kinds of other troublemaking all
                        over the place. And with the Khmer Rouge as well as with the Vietnamese
                        Communist Party and which was an enemy of the status quo explicitly
                        demanding its overthrow has been peacefully integrated into the global
                        system is now a member of every major international organization and
                        somewhat ironically, if I may make a comment in 2006, it is more of a
                        defender of the global status quo than the United States and therefore less
                        of a source of international stability.</p>
                    <p>So this peaceful integration of China or the transformation of China from
                        outlaw to supporter of the status quo given the weight of China in world
                        affairs and particularly its weight as it has grown in recent years, is an
                        amazing, absolutely amazing achievement that no one would have predicted
                        however much -- whatever we smoked back in 1972.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> A little more general, how would you
                        compare -- several of the panelists mentioned Mao's tendency to speak in
                        broad strokes with kind of poetic illusions and vast freedom. You referred
                        to the 41 signals being sent between Beijing and Washington. How do you --
                        how would you compare dealing with the Chinese as opposed to dealing with
                        the Russians or West Europeans or so on?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Well, during this period as I mentioned with
                        the Chinese, we had very dramatic developments with the Russians as well,
                        the difference in the two relationships is with Russia we had a lot of
                        concrete issues to negotiate: arms control, economics, principals in
                        international relations and so there was an actual full agenda. With the
                        Chinese it was more, as Kissinger said -- I mean Brzezinski said, first
                        kiss. I won't carry that any further. He's exhausted that subject.</p>
                    <p>But the fact is it was more conceptual and we had to sort of reassure each
                        other what our mutual interests were and sketch the longer term trend. So by
                        definition, you didn't have concrete agreements. That's one reason we kept
                        briefing the Chinese on Soviet relations with us -- one, to reassure them
                        that we weren't doing anything behind their back, but also to make the
                        Chinese nervous that we had a lot of concrete agreements with the Soviets.
                        We didn't have them with the Chinese, so it was designed to spur the Chinese
                        to have good relations, even as it worked the other way with the
                        Russians.</p>
                    <p>Now in terms of style, this may be somewhat exaggerated and certainly is no
                        longer true today necessarily. But in the early '70s, there's no question
                        that Kissinger and Nixon found the Chinese style much more pleasant and
                        attractive and easy -- not easy, but at least reliable to deal with than the
                        Russians. With the Russians the feeling was you were dealing with rug
                        merchants. And they would come in and they would inflate greatly their
                        opening position from what they really needed and bargained like in the
                        bazaar until you got down to your bottom line, so you never quite knew when
                        you got to the bottom line of the other side -- could be unpleasant.</p>
                    <p>There were instances when we'd reach an agreement, for example, in arms
                        control in May 1971 and it was published the Russians would do their own
                        translation and sort of stick it to us a little bit in ways that were not
                        very pleasant. But the Chinese -- and again, this may be has been
                        romanticized in retrospect and it's certainly no longer true. But at the
                        time, the general approach was to lay out what they really needed at the
                        beginning, their bottom line.</p>
                    <p>And in effect, say we have these principles, we've got to respect these
                        principles for them to be flexible in details and tactics within that
                        framework. Can't have a two-China policy, can't have two embassies in
                        Washington. Fine, you have an embassy and a liaison office, which is an
                        embassy in everything but name. And so Kissinger and Nixon felt that with
                        the Chinese, it was a more pleasant process than with the Soviets that you
                        could figure out what they really needed and get quickly to a possible
                        compromise in contrast to the Russians.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> You know, I would just add that I think
                        with the Chinese, there was no common background. We were coming out two
                        decades of total isolation. We had no communications with them. So we didn't
                        know what they were like, they didn't know what we were like, so a lot of it
                        -- I don't disagree with anything that Win has said, but it was this kind of
                        feeling our way and getting acquainted with each other what -- how did each
                        one feel about this problem or the other?</p>
                    <p>With the Soviets on the other hand, it was a fundamentally hostile approach.
                        We didn't like each other, we made it clear we didn't like each other. We
                        were there because we thought there were practical things we could do to
                        improve and reduce the dangerous intentions in the relationship. But there
                        was no fundamental spirit of give and take. There was no trust, anything.
                        This was the hardest of hard in negotiations. And of course, for the
                        Europeans it was different from either one of those. We had common
                        backgrounds, we've worked with each other over and over and over again, so
                        it was a much more congenial kind of approach.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> Two quick points. With China, we had an
                        arranged marriage. That marriage, that relationship was not driven by
                        affection at the outset. There was no affection. It was a very cold-blooded
                        decision on both sides. But as we began to interact, we discovered affection
                        and maybe more than that because as Tiananmen showed, we emotionally had too
                        much invested in China. You have to have illusions to be disillusioned.</p>
                    <p>The second point I'd make is that the Chinese have a very distinctive
                        negotiating style. In fact, I was reminded of this the other day. I met
                        someone in the intelligence community here who told me that a memo I'd
                        written during this period on Chinese negotiating style was declassified.
                        And apparently it was sent -- it was one of the things that was retyped,
                        rather than on Department of State briefing paper.</p>
                    <p>And the basic points that I made were precisely those that Win and Brent have
                        made, that the Chinese approach principles quite differently from concrete
                        arrangements. Principles are strategic goals which are immutable. Concrete
                        arrangements are ways to accomplish common purposes consistent with those
                        strategic goals. It is a very distinctive style and I think described later
                        by Dick Solomon in a book done through Rand and it has really nothing in
                        common with European or Russian styles and Americans tend to find it rather
                        appealing.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Well, speaking of the Russians, how much do
                        you feel the Chinese feared the Soviets? Were they in effect using us to
                        move the Soviets the way we were using the Chinese to move the Soviets.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Well, the quick answer is yes and no. Yes, the
                        Soviets were a factor. And they wanted, as I said earlier, the poor
                        barbarian and to help balance them off against the Soviets and to restrain
                        the Soviets around the world. But theirs was more defensive vis-à-vis Russia
                        because they're so much weaker. In our case, we were using the Chinese to
                        try to make progress concretely with the Russians. So those are the --
                        that's the major difference. Because clearly that was in the Chinese mind
                        and a Soviet factor in the Anti-Hegemony clause and the Shanghai communiqué
                        was the single most motivating force, but there are many other reasons on
                        both sides that I mentioned earlier.&gt;/p&gt;</p>
                    <p>While I've got the mike, on the negotiating styles, one of the strengths of
                        Nixon and Kissinger and they had their flaws like everyone else, but their
                        ability particularly Kissinger had more detailed negotiations to adjust to
                        their interlocutor's style, culture and history, even if they weren't
                        experts. Henry was essentially a European expert. He didn't know that much
                        about Asia. But he quickly saw the Chinese style that we've described. He
                        knew how to deal with the Russian style and then if he's with the Arabs, it
                        would be more romantic and you've got to save face with the Israelis
                        understandably given their history and their insecurities were like Talmudic
                        scholars and going over every last detail to make sure they got what they
                        needed.</p>
                    <p>I remember once in the shuttle we were with Golda Maier and the others and
                        they gave us ten compromises to get out of Sadat. We went to Cairo, got nine
                        out of ten, came back and the Israelis complained about the tenth the entire
                        time. So -- and then the Vietnamese, of course, just try to wear you down
                        and they didn't negotiate at all in retrospect until they saw that they had
                        to deal with this madman Nixon for another four years and not McGovern and
                        they suddenly got more flexible.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> I think the Chinese and particularly Deng
                        Xiaoping became increasingly uncomfortable with our use of them to put
                        pressure on the Soviet Union. And as the 1980s began to increase Chinese
                        leverage in its own right, they began to play the same game using us more
                        and more against the Russians. Fair enough.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Time's just about up. Would you at least like
                        to take a minute or two just to sum up? Final observations?</p>
                    <p>General Scowcroft.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SCOWCROFT:</hi> Well, I'll make just one comment I haven't
                        made before and that is about the whole Chinese negotiating style. The
                        Chinese came out of a period of almost total isolation. They were autarchic
                        by nature, they were autarchic by design. They thought they were
                        self-sufficient, they didn't need any outside communications and so on. So
                        we started the relationship on purely bilateral kinds of affairs and issues.
                        And that has gradually changed. But I think as Philip Zelikow said,
                        referring to Bob Zoellick and the responsible stakeholder, what is happening
                        now is the Chinese are beginning to engage us on issues that are not purely
                        bilateral, that are general, worldwide or regional issues.</p>
                    <p>This has been a gradual development over this entire period. And I think that
                        while you can look at the Chinese as being reluctant negotiators, I think
                        they are gradually moving out and gradually becoming a stakeholder in the
                        world as they become more dependent for both imports and exports and other
                        things on what goes on in the world. They're a long way from there, but I
                        think that's the evolution that's taking place in Chinese diplomacy.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">FREEMAN:</hi> I think when you read this record and when
                        the record of subsequent negotiations, particularly those bearing on the
                        Taiwan issue are released, I mean, the normalization negotiations, I mean,
                        the August 1982 communiqué negotiations, you will draw the conclusion that
                        the United States has broken almost every commitment we made to the Chinese
                        over the course of the succeeding period. The fact that there has been great
                        progress on the Taiwan issue and that, as I said in the outset, I believe it
                        is moving toward resolution. That was a great deal to Chinese statecraft and
                        patience and left to our fidelity, to our friends or our word. So there are
                        interesting things to be discovered in these documents and I'm sure you'll
                        enjoy them.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Ambassador Lord, you were the first one into
                        China. You get the last word.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">LORD:</hi> Okay. I was going to make some other comments,
                        but that was a real bombshell at the end. Maybe we can pursue it. I don't
                        know whether the chair is going to be here tomorrow. I don't want to leave
                        it at that. I think that's unfair to seven American presidents. I think it's
                        wrong. I think we have stretched some commitments, particularly arms sales
                        to Taiwan. No doubt about that. We did somersaults to continue to justify
                        the quality and quantity of arms sales. But to sit here and say that America
                        has not left -- kept its word, is not only inaccurate. I think it's very
                        damaging for an audience like that to hear that, unsubstantiated. So we
                        ought to continue that. And of course, we stretch it. So have the
                        Chinese.</p>
                    <p>But I continue to believe that seven presidents of both parties have pursued
                        remarkable diplomacy with all the inevitable ups and downs, this is always
                        going to be a sweet and sour relationship. The fact is we've moved ahead
                        with China and Taiwan has flourished and we've done it by sticking to basic
                        principles occasionally stretching it. The Chinese in turn have done the
                        same. And I think we should leave this in a much more positive note than
                        suggest the United States has not kept its word.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">SUSSER:</hi> Thank you gentlemen. It's been a fascinating
                        two hours. Thank you. We are adjourned today. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="hill">
                <head>Keynote Speaker: Christopher R. Hill, Assistant Secretary of State for East
                    Asian and Pacific Affairs</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">ASSISTANT SECRETARY HILL:</hi> Thank you very much. It's a
                    real pleasure to be here. I must say it's a little intimidating to be here, too,
                    because as my bio suggested I'm not a China scholar although I did serve in
                    Albania which has a sort of curious Chinese connection. I'll always remember in
                    Albania we were giving them some cotton and weren't sure whether it would work
                    in their textile mill. And I said, well, where did the textile mill come from?
                    They said oh, it came from China. So we had a couple of experts go and check it
                    out. And it said something like Moscow, in Cyrillic, on it, 1890. And what we
                    realized was it was a gift of the Soviet people to the Chinese people who
                    promptly or maybe not so promptly turned it around and made it a gift to the
                    Albanian people. So I have a little familiarity from China in those days.</p>
                <p>But I must say taking up my current position, as you see from my bio, I moved
                    from being Ambassador to Korea to being Assistant Secretary to North Korea. We
                    occasionally have some dealings with China. Every day I walk into my office and
                    I walk past the picture of John Carter Vincent, who at some point I guess took
                    up cigarette smoking because he's there with a cigarette in his mouth. I've been
                    tempted to pick up cigarette smoking as well in this position. I also walk past
                    the photo of W.W. Butterworth. And these are two figures who had my position and
                    who have had to live through I think a very, very tough time in policy terms, a
                    lot of recrimination, just took a lot of courage. And so I frankly find those
                    people quite an inspiration.</p>
                <p>It has been more than three decades since President Nixon and Secretary of State
                    and National Security Advisor Kissinger made their historic breakthrough with
                    China. It's, I think, always memorable at the Beijing banquet that honored him
                    in 1972 President Nixon responding to Chou En-lai's toast spoke frankly, he said
                    "Let us recognize at the outset these points. We have at time in the past been
                    enemies. We have great differences today. What brings us together is that we
                    have common interests which transcend those differences. Neither of us will
                    compromise our principles. But while we cannot close the gulf between us, we can
                    try to bridge it so that we may be able to talk across it." And indeed, I think
                    those remarks uttered some 30 years ago at a toast are very much applicable
                    today, very prescient remarks.</p>
                <p>I think at a critical juncture when China's own leadership was reassessing its
                    priorities, emerging from the isolation of the Cultural Revolution to engage on
                    an uncertain course of opening to the west, U.S. policymakers decided that our
                    approach to China had to be different from the way we dealt with the Soviet
                    Union. That approach would take deeper roots once China launched its impressive
                    domestic reform program in 1978 and the U.S. and the PRC established diplomatic
                    relations.</p>
                <p>Indeed I would say the policies pursued by both administrations, by
                    administrations of both parties, by now some seven Presidents, has been to
                    encourage China's economic reforms, to expand the trade and our contacts with
                    China, and to especially use our influence to integrate and bind China into a
                    rules based international system.</p>
                <p>And I would say that policy, that policy that has been for seven Presidents has
                    been extremely successful. China is an active player in the United Nations, a
                    Perm 5 member, a member which we are in constant communication, constant
                    negotiations across international issues across the globe. China's part of the
                    WTO, virtually every other economic organization participates in international
                    endeavors ranging from efforts to stop the spread of infectious diseases to
                    initiatives on the development of clean energy, which is one such effort we have
                    going in China just this month. And increasingly stepping up to take an active
                    role in dealing with regional security issues and a prime example being China's
                    efforts at hosting the six-party talks and dealing with North Korea's very
                    dangerous nuclear ambition, something I'll get to a little later.</p>
                <p>And certainly, I think this is very good for China and I think it really reflects
                    to some extent to China's economic rise. It's GDP has grown some ten-fold since
                    1978, per capita income has doubled every eight and a half years. By comparison
                    it took Great Britain 58 years to double its per capita income in the early 19th
                    Century. It took the U.S. 47 years. It took Japan 34 years after
                    industrialization.</p>
                <p>China recently surpassed Italy and the United Kingdom to become the world's
                    fourth largest economy. It trails only the U.S., Japan and Germany. But -- and
                    I'll go back to the famous -- I call it a quote, but I hate to do that in front
                    of historians because it's probably more apocryphal than anything else. But when
                    President Nixon congratulated Mao Tse-tung on the enormous changes in China, Mao
                    is reported to have said, "In fact, Mr. President, I've only been able to change
                    a few places around Beijing."</p>
                <p>And indeed, I think when people do go outside of Shanghai and outside of Beijing,
                    you still see that China remains in many respects a very poor country, a per
                    capita income that ranks 133 in the world at $1200. Over 160 million people have
                    moved fitfully from China's rural areas to cities looking for employment, really
                    the largest internal migration in world history. And this floating population
                    now accounts for almost 20 percent of Beijing's residents, almost 20 percent of
                    Shanghai's residents. Indeed it's because of this migration in less than a
                    decade Shanghai's population has increased by a number equal to the population
                    of China.</p>
                <p>And of course, as we are very aware, and I would say the Chinese Government is
                    more aware than anybody, average urban incomes are some four times what they are
                    in the rural areas. So by no means is China, as way say, out of the woods in
                    terms of what it has to do economically, but I think it is also fair to say that
                    one should look at some of the enormous progress in that rural area. In fact,
                    despite the disparities, the number of China's rural poor has been cut in half
                    during the 1990s, according to the World Bank, and that a population larger than
                    the entire population of the United States has been pulled out of abject
                    poverty. And I would say that this development in China has been very good for
                    the United States. China is now our fourth largest export market. It -- the
                    trade deficit is a huge issue to be sure, but also I think U.S. exports to
                    China, it's worth pointing out they've doubled since China joined the WTO in
                    2001 and that pace continues this year.</p>
                <p>I had the pleasure of accompanying or meeting President Hu Jintao in Seattle.
                    What the Governor of Washington said, this is the real Washington, and you will
                    soon go to the other Washington. And I think she had a very good point, because
                    it was truly stunning to see the volume and depth of our relationship with
                    China.</p>
                <p>China is going to be in the market in the next 20 years for some 2800 jets. And
                    when Hu Jintao came to the Boeing factory and was greeted by workers there in
                    overalls and just cheering him like he was their best customer. And there's a
                    reason why they treated him like he was their best customer, he -- it was a real
                    sense among the workers of how important he was. And what I really liked about
                    the meeting -- and I've never had a chance to ask him this but I'd love to ask
                    him, when he looked out on those sea of faces, many people wearing work overalls
                    and baseball hats, I think he realized something very important which is
                    Americans also need jobs now and again. America also needs to export goods now
                    and again. And so I think when he went there he saw really I think a very good
                    face of what our country is about, and it's not just about people in suits and
                    the other Washington, that is in Washington, D.C., but people who are really
                    trying to make a living as workers. And I thought it was a very important visit
                    in that regard.</p>
                <p>He also went to the Microsoft campus, as the factory there is called, and saw I
                    think what was important in a number of respects, first of all, the cutting edge
                    technology that goes on in Microsoft. But secondly, when you look at the number
                    of Chinese engineers or people of Chinese extraction, Chinese-Americans, I think
                    he saw not only the connection of our economies but very much the connection of
                    our people.</p>
                <p>In short, I think that trip to Seattle which lasted some 24 hours which -- and
                    where he met a lot of people including a lot of Falun Gong protestors I might
                    add, I think he saw and I think we saw in him the fact that our countries are
                    very much linked, very much linked if not entirely by a common past then
                    certainly by a common future.</p>
                <p>And as one goes around in Washington, D.C. today, you will hear the occasional
                    person talk about China as the new Soviet Union, but that is extremely rare,
                    extremely rare indeed. I think you see very clearly from Americans of all
                    political persuasions that this is our key relationship. This is the
                    relationship that we have to, above all other relationships in the world,
                    nurture and make it work. We need to make it work in a way that's true to our
                    value, true to our interest but also make it work in a way that makes sure that
                    U.S. and China can work together because the stakes are simply enormous. They're
                    not only stakes in East Asia, they're all over the world and we have to work --
                    we have to find ways to work with China.</p>
                <p>I think our engagement with China, which now takes place across many fora both
                    bilaterally and multilaterally, speaks to the importance that we attach to this
                    fundamental relationship. Bilaterally we have -- in the State Department we've
                    had a senior dialog that was first started by then Deputy Secretary Bob Zoellick
                    last year. And in fact, we planned -- of course we'll have a new Deputy
                    Secretary who will continue that dialog, but we didn't want to have too many
                    months go by. And so when I was in China just a couple of weeks ago, I
                    approached the senior foreign policy leadership to see if we could get the
                    dialog going as early as this month and have our Under Secretary for Political
                    Affairs handle it, and the Chinese were very, very happy to pursue that dialog.
                    And I think it was really a reflection of the fact that they appreciate the fact
                    that we sit down systematically go through our political relations and not just
                    issues that are urgent, which is often when you have diplomacy, but also issues
                    that are important. That is, these are dialogs where we try to have the
                    important crowd out the urgent now and again.</p>
                <p>So we're looking forward to having the senior dialog continued in the next month
                    by Under Secretary Burns. Of course, you are all aware of Secretary Paulson's
                    strategic economic dialog. This is a dialog where in addition to the specific
                    dialogs where we get down to, you know, discussing imports of chicken parts,
                    this is a dialog that's not going to be discussing imports of chicken parts,
                    it's going to be a dialog that will be on top of the entire economic dialog if
                    you will flying at 20,000 feet to try to oversee some of these economic dialogs
                    and make sure that we can make this really, really work.</p>
                <p>In addition to this strategic economic dialogue, we have a number of other
                    economic dialogs. The JCCT, the State Department NDRC dialogue. Our Under
                    Secretary for Global Affairs, Paula Dobriansky, is also pursuing a global issues
                    forum. We have a Department of Energy energy dialog as well. And these are just
                    a few of the examples of how we interact with China today. We have very
                    successful engagement on law enforcement cooperation. We have constant exchanges
                    of teams to discuss areas such as human trafficking, cyber crime, combating
                    corruption. The other day Elaine Chao from the Labor Department had her
                    counterpart over from China and they discussed issues like labor code and
                    especially pensions, an issue that if you've been reading the Chinese press, now
                    is quite an issue in Shanghai.</p>
                <p>So we have a very -- it's just -- I've never seen anything quite as comprehensive
                    as the relationship we have with China, and it is comprehensive because it is so
                    fundamentally important. Still, we have to find ways not only to talk to China
                    about things that we agree -- already agree on or things that we already
                    disagree on, we also have to find ways to work with them together. And here I
                    think is the -- is where the six-party process I think plays a key role in the
                    relationship with China. I cannot tell you today that the six-party process is
                    going to succeed in getting North Korea to disarm itself of these nuclear
                    weapons. I think we have -- it has been a difficult process. We are dealing with
                    difficult people. But what I can tell you is that there is a certain early
                    harvest in the six-party process and that is the fact that we are able to work
                    very closely with China, come up with common initiatives, make approaches to
                    North Korea that are coordinated, have work multilaterally in very specific
                    areas such as with the South Koreans and yes, with the Japanese because a lot
                    has been said in recent months and recent years about the difficulty of
                    Sino-Japanese relations. But yet, in the six-party process they actually work,
                    they function and because we all share the interests of getting the North
                    Koreans to give up these weapons.</p>
                <p>A key moment, I think, came in early July when against all advice, against all
                    admonitions all over the world North Korea decided to fire off several missiles.
                    There was really a missile for everybody in that barrage. There were some six or
                    seven missiles. There were short-range missiles whose only purpose in practicing
                    would have been to hit South Korea. There were short-range longer-range missiles
                    whose purpose would be threaten Japan, and there was Taepodong-2 missile whose
                    purpose would have to be looked at as an intercontinental missile ultimately
                    with the purpose of reaching the United States. In short, in that missile
                    barrage, the North Koreans essentially validated the concept of the six-party
                    talks. In that missile barrage, the North Koreans were essentially saying this
                    is not a U.S.-North Korean problem. We in North Korea are going to make it a
                    problem between us, the North Koreans and everyone else. They validated the
                    process of making this multilateral.</p>
                <p>And so as soon as these missile launches happened, which was for us in the
                    afternoon of July 4th, the first example of a sense of irony I've ever seen from
                    North Korea, we got in -- went into action diplomatically, and I went off -- I
                    left that next day on the fifth. And normally when I'd make a trip to Asia to
                    discuss North Korea I'd start with our allies, Japan and South Korea. In this
                    case I went right to China. And I sat down with the Chinese and we went through
                    what could be done, what needed to be done. And I could see in China there was a
                    certain -- I should say a sea change in how they dealt with the North Koreans. I
                    was not asked to be more patient. Often the dynamic between me and the Chinese
                    is, as you can predict, the Chinese asking me to show more patience and I asking
                    the Chinese to show less patience. But in fact, I think we got on very quickly
                    to the task of what can we do to convince the North Koreans that they can't do
                    this.</p>
                <p>And indeed as we began to discuss the need to respond, the need to respond
                    forcefully and with a sense of unity, the Chinese asked if they could be given
                    an opportunity to get up to Pyongyang and get from the North Koreans a
                    commitment to get back to the talks to re-impose a moratorium. And so we worked
                    that out. We worked that out in a way that our diplomacy going on in New York
                    with the passage -- with the work we're doing especially with the Japanese who
                    are on the Security Council to get the -- to have a strong resolution. We gave
                    the Chinese some time. We worked with the Chinese on their efforts to get up to
                    Pyongyang. They sent a very senior delegation to Pyongyang. And when they came
                    back, in fact I returned to China and we talked some more and we worked out,
                    especially our diplomats in New York, worked out a UN Security Council
                    Resolution 1695.</p>
                <p>There are a couple of very important elements to that. The first element, of
                    course, is this was a great credit to Japanese diplomacy because they were the
                    ones who drafted it and began to press forward in the UN. But I think it was
                    also a great credit to our ability to work with China because at the end of the
                    day when 1695 was passed, it was actually the end of the week, it was unanimous
                    and China was on board, on board on a unanimous resolution dealing with a
                    neighboring country and significantly I think the word condemned, that is, the
                    people who supported -- the countries that supported this which included Japan
                    and China, we all used the same word, we condemn these missile launches.</p>
                <p>We also called upon all member-states to exercise vigilance in ensuring that
                    North Korea does not get the funds and does not get the technology to continue
                    these types of programs. I saw in the Chinese, with respect to this North Korea
                    missile launch, a real kindred spirit, and I think it was very important. And so
                    someday in the annals of U.S.-China relations, we'll have to give Kim Jong-il a
                    little credit because he brought us much closer together that week.</p>
                <p>We have also continued to work with China in other areas of the world. We're
                    working in Iran. We're working very, very feverishly with China to try to come
                    up with a resolution on Iran that would encourage Iran to do the right thing on
                    these weapons of mass destruction. This is a very difficult problem. It's a
                    problem that's also rooted in Iran's situation and its own neighborhood, but
                    it's also routed in the U.S. and China and the other Perm 5 members' desire to
                    see -- to prevent nuclear arms proliferation. And this is an area were I think
                    we're working very closely with the Chinese.</p>
                <p>I do not mean to suggest that our relations with China are at this point a walk
                    in the park. We have a lot of issues, a lot of difficult issues where we deal
                    with China. We work with China on human rights issues, on religious freedom
                    questions. These are not easy issues. Some of these issues don't come naturally
                    to China, and we need to work with them and try to work with China on
                    international standards. We're not looking to impose a U.S. view on all of these
                    issues, we're looking to really gain an international consensus on how to
                    approach issues like human rights and religious freedom consistent with China's
                    agreement with the UN charter and consistent with China's desire to live up to
                    these universal values.</p>
                <p>We also have to work very hard every day and every hour of every day on getting a
                    level playing field for U.S. businesses. Anyone who's been to China knows that
                    there has been improvement on intellectual property rights in the -- in a de
                    jure sense and in a legislative sense, but on the street the picture can
                    sometimes be different. Although I must say that if you try to buy a counterfeit
                    version of anything to do with the Beijing Olympics, you'll be very hard
                    pressed. In fact, the intellectual property rights of the Beijing Olympics are
                    being very well respected. And let's see if we can use that as an inspiration
                    for everything else including golf clubs.</p>
                <p>So that is a work in progress, but I think we have a pretty strong and active
                    dialog with the Chinese on that. We're also working, and I know this is a --
                    this continues to be an enormous issue, to look for more transparency in
                    military budgets, in military doctrine and, in fact, in military intentions.</p>
                <p>Now if you look at the U.S. budget, as the Chinese have done, you will notice the
                    U.S. budget somewhat exceeds the Chinese budget, a fact that has been brought to
                    light by Chinese analysts. We're not questioning that for a minute, but you can
                    also find in the U.S. budget exactly where the money is going. You can find the
                    supply of explanatory notes at times exceeding the demand for those same
                    explanations. In short, everyone in Washington has an opinion about our military
                    budget, and it's out for everybody to see.</p>
                <p>China has not quite achieved, let me put it, the same degree of transparency. And
                    what we're really looking for from the Chinese is not necessarily to reduce
                    their budget or something like that, we're looking for transparency. What are
                    they doing? Where is the money going? Why is it going there? What is it -- what
                    are the contingencies they're working on? We need clarity on this and we need a
                    good dialog. We are beginning to have a dialog with the Chinese on this. I was
                    just with Admiral Fallon who has gone to China on several occasions, most
                    recently just a few weeks ago. We've had some -- we had some joint exercises
                    with the Chinese recently in San Diego. We are beginning a process to work on
                    ways that we can agree -- we can see what each other is doing because we still
                    do have a mountain of mistrust in this relationship, especially in this military
                    relationship, and we need to work on that.</p>
                <p>We're also working in I'd like to mention a couple of other regional areas. I
                    know in Southeast Asia, an area that I also cover, that there are people who say
                    that the U.S. is somehow staging a strategic withdrawal while China is a staging
                    a strategic entry into that area. I really don't buy that frankly. I don't buy
                    the idea that we're leaving, and I don't buy the idea that the Chinese want us
                    to leave. I think there's -- more China in Southeast Asia does not mean less
                    U.S. After all, I think China for years and years, decades and decades, the
                    world has looked for a second engine of growth, and I think many countries are
                    finding that second engine of growth and it's called China. It's called the
                    China economy, and we welcome that. More China does not mean less U.S. there.
                    And so we can work that out.</p>
                <p>We're also working in the Pacific island states. You know, people look at the
                    Pacific Island states, they look at the Pacific and they try to find the islands
                    there. Very small countries. I would that say sometimes big problems can come in
                    small places, and we need to make sure that governance issues in the Pacific
                    Island states and capacity issues, tiny places like the Solomon Islands, you
                    know, that those countries develop and don't become centers of problems and,
                    therefore, we need to make sure that countries that are big donors, and China is
                    a big donor in those states, finds ways to make sure that the assistance that
                    China is giving is going to causes that will help those countries develop
                    governance and capacity. And in that regard, we're going to have still another
                    dialog with the Chinese. We're going to sit down and talk about some of our
                    mutual assistance or assistance efforts in some of these countries.</p>
                <p>So I think ultimately I feel that there is a real reason for optimism in this
                    relationship. I feel that the people who worked so hard on this relationship in
                    the late '40, early '50s, the people who really I think in some cases went to
                    their graves with a sense that this was going to be a very, very difficult
                    process that may not turn out well can actually, if they're still listening,
                    realize that a lot of their work in those very troubled years has led to some
                    very special developments. We are by no means there. We are by no means there,
                    but I hope that future generations can look back on this period and draw from it
                    a certain inspiration as we move forward.</p>
                <p>So, again, I speak as a sort of a person who can maybe give some raw material to
                    your -- to what you are doing. I am not a historian. I probably spend more time
                    looking at the U.S. Civil War than I have at China's various civil wars. But I
                    do believe that to understand our history with China is to understand our future
                    with China. I'm very pleased at the publication of this. I will read every word
                    of it later in the day I guess. But to be sure it is I think an excellent time
                    to be reflecting on where we are with China because there's no relationship in
                    the world that's more important to us than the relationship with China.</p>
                <p>Thank you very much. (Applause.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
