<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</title>
                <title type="short">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State</author>
                        <title>Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</title>
                        <date when="2011-03-07">March 7, 2011</date>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="overview">
                <head>“Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976”</head>
                <p rend="centerstrong">The Office of the Historian, U.S. Department of State, and
                    <lb/> The George Mason University School of Public Policy<lb/> Present the
                    Inaugural Conference of the<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> Special Conference
                    Series</p>
                <p rend="centerstrong">“Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976”<lb/> March 7, 2011</p>
                <p>As part of an array of events designed to commemorate the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history">sesquicentennial of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> (FRUS)
                        series</ref>, the State Department’s Office of the Historian is inaugurating
                    the FRUS Special Conference Series to highlight recently-published FRUS
                    volumes.</p>
                <p>On March 7th, the Office of the Historian and the George Mason University School
                    of Public Policy will host a half-day conference focused on the FRUS volume
                    dealing with <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</hi> . The
                    conference will take place at the George Mason University School of Public
                    Policy in Arlington, Virginia. The text of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic
                        Policy, 1973-1976</hi> is available <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v31">online</ref>, allowing
                    conference attendees to read it beforehand.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</hi> examines U.S. policy
                    during a time of great global economic change, focusing on issues such as the
                    end of the fixed exchange rate system envisioned at the 1944 Bretton Woods
                    conference and the transition to flexible exchange rates; the creation of the
                    G-7 economic summit; the passage of the Trade Act of 1974; the launch of the
                    Tokyo Round of GATT negotiations; and North/South relations and commodity policy
                    in a post-1973 oil embargo world. The significance of the volume and the lessons
                    to be gleaned from this period by historians, economists, and policy analysts
                    promise an engaging event.</p>
                <p>The conference will feature a presentation by the volume’s editor, Dr. Kathleen
                    Rasmussen; an academic panel of historians, foreign policy analysts, and
                    economists; and a keynote address by Under Secretary of State for Economic,
                    Energy, and Agricultural Affairs Robert Hormats (who is also the author of
                    several key documents in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy,
                        1973-1976</hi> volume). Participants on the academic panel include: Will
                    Gray, Department of History, Purdue University; Susan Aaronson, Elliot School of
                    International Affairs, George Washington University; Dan Hamilton, School of
                    Advanced International Studies, Johns Hopkins University; and Kent Hughes,
                    Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>LOCATION</head>
                    <p>George Mason University School of Public Policy (Founders Hall), 3351 Fairfax
                        Drive, Arlington, Virginia (near the Virginia Square / GMU metro stop; <ref
                            target="http://policy.gmu.edu/Home/AboutUs/Directions/tabid/63/Default.aspx"
                            >maps and directions</ref>). Presentations will be in the ground floor
                        auditorium. Reception and coffee, etc., will be in the ground floor
                        multipurpose room.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>SCHEDULE</head>
                    <p>March 7, 2011, 2:30-7:00 p.m.</p>
                    <table rend="schedule">
                        <row>
                            <cell>2:30-2:40</cell>
                            <cell>Welcome and opening comments by George Mason University Provost
                                and historian Peter Stearns and the Office of the Historian</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2:40-3:10</cell>
                            <cell>Presentation by editor Kathleen Rasmussen, Office of the Historian
                                on the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</hi>
                                volume; and Q&amp;A. <lb/> Moderator: Edward Rhodes, Dean of the
                                School of Public Policy, George Mason University. <lb/>
                                <ref target="#opening-remarks-and-editors-talk">(Audio and
                                    transcript)</ref>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3:10-3:30</cell>
                            <cell>Break</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3:30-5:15</cell>
                            <cell>Academic Panel and Q&amp;A on the significance of the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy, 1973-1976</hi> volume to
                                scholars’ historical understanding of this topic and time period;
                                and the relevance of the issues revealed in the volume to
                                present-day foreign policy makers and analysts. <ref target="#panel"
                                    >(Audio and transcript)</ref>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Will Gray, Department of History, Purdue University</item>
                                    <item>Susan Aaronson, Elliot School of International Affairs,
                                        George Washington University</item>
                                    <item>Dan Hamilton, School of Advanced International Studies,
                                        Johns Hopkins University</item>
                                    <item>Kent Hughes, Woodrow Wilson International Center for
                                        Scholars</item>
                                    <item>Moderator: Edward Rhodes, Dean of the School of Public
                                        Policy, George Mason University</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5:15-5:30</cell>
                            <cell>Break</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5:30-7:00</cell>
                            <cell>Keynote address by Robert Hormats, Under Secretary of State for
                                Economic, Energy, and Agricultural Affairs. As Senior Staff Member
                                for International Economic Affairs at the National Security Council
                                from 1973-1976, Hormats was a key participant in the events
                                documented in the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy,
                                    1973-1976</hi> volume. <ref target="#hormats">(Audio and
                                    transcript)</ref>
                                <lb/>
                                <lb/>Reception follows.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="audio-transcripts">
                <head>Audio and Transcripts</head>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="opening-remarks-and-editors-talk">
                    <head>Opening Remarks and Editor’s Talk on <hi rend="italic">Foreign Economic
                            Policy, 1973-1976</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>George Mason University School of Public Policy, Arlington, Virginia <lb/>
                        March 7, 2011</p>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item><list>
                                <head>MODERATOR</head>
                                <item>Edward Rhodes, Dean, School of Public Policy, George Mason
                                    University</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item>Amb. Edward Brynn, The Historian (Acting), Office of the
                                    Historian, U.S. Department of State</item>
                                <item>Dr. Kathleen Rasmussen, Division Chief, Asia &amp; General,
                                    Office of the Historian</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/conferences/2011-foreign-economic-policy/FEP_Opening_and_Editor_Talk.mp3"
                            >Download Audio</ref> (22.7 MB MP3)</p>
                    <p rend="italic">Note: This transcript and linked audio recording contain
                        comments made during a roundtable discussion of the “Foreign Economic
                        Policy, 1973-1976” volume of the <title>Foreign Relations of the United
                            States</title> (FRUS) series. The comments of Robert Hormats and
                        Kathleen Rasmussen reflect their individual points of view and do not
                        necessarily reflect the views of the Department of State or the United
                        States Government.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Silence has descended on the room. I
                        guess that means on academic time, it’s time for us to begin this
                        conference. I’m Ed Rhodes, Dean of the George Mason School of Public Policy.
                        And it’s my honor and pleasure to be the first today to welcome you to
                        GeorgeMasonUniversity, to the School of Public Policy, and to this new
                        facility.</p>
                    <p>We’re hoping that this facility for each and every one of you will come to be
                        a second home, that it will come to be a place that you know well, that we
                        are conveniently located to lots of things that are going on in Washington.
                        And part of the joy of being a school of public policy is that we are a
                        wonderful place to serve as an intersection between everything that’s going
                        on in Washington and the various offices and outside folks, folks from the
                        academic community, folks from consulting communities, a place where we can
                        meet and have conferences just like this one, where we can exchange
                        ideas.</p>
                    <p>As many of you have heard me say on previous occasions, deans are to
                        successful conferences as dams are to rivers, so before I yield and let this
                        river go to the places it’s supposed to go, I just did have a couple of
                        quick points I wanted to make, just to share with you why I am so
                        particularly pleased to be welcoming all of you here today. Frankly, this
                        conference really is what a school of public policy is all about.</p>
                    <p>As I’ve indicated, what we have and what we’re able to do here is have a
                        place where scholars from all the corners of academia, from history through
                        civil engineering through whatever, all of the academics whose insights
                        impact in some way on public policy can come together with practitioners.
                        It’s in conferences like this one where I think we can identify critical
                        issues from our past, from our present, and from our future and bring to
                        bear some combined insights and to try to develop better explanations and
                        better solutions, because, frankly, if there are any clues to the future,
                        surely we’re going to have to find them in the past. And so a chance like
                        today where we can take a look at the past and understand it better is a
                        wonderful opportunity to think about the problems and challenges that we’re
                        facing even now.</p>
                    <p>I’m also happy because our discussion today is possible, and it’s possible
                        because of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series and because of a new <hi
                            rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume, a new volume in the State Department’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi>. What,
                        this is about volume number 360, 350, 370? Anyway – keep bidding, okay – all
                        the way back to President Lincoln.</p>
                    <p>This is – as those of you who use the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> series
                        know, the volumes, like the volume today, contain the actual policymaking
                        documents from the period, not some sanitized summary of them, not some
                        expurgated or prettified history. What we’ve got is the – are the actual
                        documents revealing what decisions were made, by whom, in consultation with
                        whom, based on what arguments and on what information. And what this means
                        is it’s possible for Americans and for the entire world to see what our
                        government has done, what it has not done, and why it did it or did not do
                        it.</p>
                    <p>Frankly, if this volume is like most of the ones that I’ve looked at, there
                        are going to be some documents in this one that make us angry, some that
                        make us blush, and some that make us shake our heads or pound our heads with
                        disbelief that we could have done something so stupid. But every volume in
                        this series is in an important way a celebration and a contribution to
                        democracy, because what these volumes do is they allow us to know. They
                        allow us to know exactly what it is we need to hold our government
                        accountable for, what it was that was done.</p>
                    <p>The old axiom that the victors write the history books is defeated,
                        disproved, whatever it is you do to an axiom to make it go wrong, with these
                        volumes, because what these volumes mean is that the power to run the
                        government, the power to run the state, is not the power to rewrite the
                        past. And we are able, therefore, to hold our leaders accountable, after a
                        lapse of 30 years, but nonetheless to hold them accountable for what’s been
                        done.</p>
                    <p>One last reason why I’m particularly happy that we’re all here – and it’s an
                        entirely personal one – I’m delighted to have a chance to welcome so many
                        people I know over to the School of Public Policy, so many faces I recognize
                        from the Historian’s Office and from the Advisory Committee on Historical
                        Diplomatic Documentation. Working together, the Historian’s Office and the
                        HAC [Advisory Committee on Historical Diplomatic Documentation or Historical
                        Advisory Committee, for short] are responsible for producing a thorough,
                        accurate, and reliable record. And that is a critically important thing and
                        something that makes all of these discussions possible.</p>
                    <p>Okay, I’m holding up progress far too long. You’re already checking your
                        watches to see if we’re late. My next pleasure is the opportunity to
                        introduce Ambassador Edward Brynn, who has served as Acting Director of the
                        Office of the Historian in the State Department since August 2009.
                        Ambassador Brynn, who comes from Pittsburgh and was raised in Vermont,
                        graduated from the Georgetown School of Foreign Service and got his master’s
                        and PhD in British history from Stanford University and another round of
                        degrees, a master’s in literature and PhD degree in Irish politics from
                        Trinity College in Dublin. Ambassador Brynn has published two books and many
                        scholarly articles on Ireland and the British Empire.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Brynn was an Air Force officer from 1968 to ’72 and served as
                        assistant and associate professor of history at the Air Force Academy out in
                        Colorado Springs, and joined the Foreign Service in 1972 with overseas
                        appointments in Sri Lanka, Mali, Mauretania, the Gambia, Comoros Islands,
                        Cameroon, Burkina Faso, and Ghana. Is there any place in West Africa you
                        didn’t go to?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR BRYNN:</hi> I’ve ruined them all.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES: </hi>Ambassador Brynn served as diplomat in
                        residence at the Air Force Academy, a staff member of the Senate Select
                        Committee on Intelligence in Foreign Policy. At the same time, he was an
                        advisor to Senator Leahy, principal deputy assistant secretary in the Bureau
                        of African Affairs, international affairs advisor and deputy commandant at
                        the NationalWarCollege. He’s received the Walter J. Stoessel Award for
                        distinguished diplomatic service. Ambassador Brynn also served as associate
                        provost at University of North Carolina at Charlotte and as a teaching
                        professor there as well. From 2002 to 2005 he was the chair of World Affairs
                        Council of Charlotte and he’s a member of the board of trustees of the Vera
                        Institute of Criminal Justice Reform in New York.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Brynn, I could go on and on and on, but in the interest of moving
                        us on, thank you so much for co-hosting. (Applause.) I should – the last
                        thing I should say is this conference is courtesy of the U.S. Department of
                        State in collaboration with GeorgeMasonUniversity. Thank you,
                        Ambassador.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR BRYNN:</hi> Thank you. Thank you, Ed. In the
                        interest of full disclosure, I guess all of you are aware that Ed was a
                        member of the HAC in a – six years ago, six or seven years ago? Yeah, so
                        it’s great to have him as our host here. I want to thank George Mason for
                        hosting us in this elegant accommodation this afternoon. I was astonished to
                        find out from Ed the GMU School of Public Policy is a big-time operation.
                        How many grad students do you have?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> We’ve got a thousand.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR BRYNN:</hi> A thousand. Wow. And very, very
                        impressive and, as you say, wonderfully located to take advantage of all the
                        opportunities in the Washington area.</p>
                    <p>I’d like to welcome everybody who came today, not only a good contingent from
                        the Office of the Historian, but others as well who’ve been vested in the
                            <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> adventures a long time. I know for some
                        strange reason that Todd [Bennett] has come up all the way from North
                        Carolina. He got a new passport, so he was able to get into Virginia.
                        (Laughter.) I’m really pleased to see that. I want to thank some of the HO
                        staff who really helped to put this together. Michael McCoyer, who is here
                        today, and Lindsay – I think she’s here – Lindsay Krasnoff, Joe Wicentowski
                        – I didn’t see Joe. Is Joe here?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PARTICIPANT:</hi> He’s out this week.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR BRYNN:</hi> Hmm?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PARTICIPANT:</hi> He’s out this week.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">AMBASSADOR BRYNN:</hi> He’s out. Okay. And of course, Kathy
                        Rasmussen, who will be our speaker today, and Forest Barnum, who is our
                        secret weapon. He came in from British Columbia on a rocket and has already
                        demanded that we speak only Latin over in HO. So we’re back into the swing
                        of things.</p>
                    <p>As you know, today’s conference is part of an array of events to commemorate
                        the sesquicentennial of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                            United States</hi> series, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">FRUS</hi> is 150 years old this year. Ed has already said
                        that on the 200th anniversary, we could have another thing here. I promise
                        to be around. <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> has become the world over the gold
                        standard for documentary publications in the history of foreign policy. HO
                        staff made two presentations at the American Historical Association Annual
                        Meeting in Boston, and we are scheduled to make additional presentations at
                        this year’s annual meetings of the Society for History in the Federal
                        Government and the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations. And
                        we’re also planning talks and discussions for general audiences and
                        non-academic specialist audiences, and you can consult our website,
                        www.history.state.gov for the latest information.</p>
                    <p>As part of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> sesqui and of HO’s ongoing
                        commitment to raise awareness of the series, today’s conference is the
                        inaugural event of the <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> special conference series
                        which is designed to highlight recently published <hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi> volumes. We look forward with great anticipation to what
                        today’s speakers will share with us, what they think this volume tells us,
                        the one we’re going to feature today about the topic and the time period,
                        and how it relates to issues today. I want to add here, of course, that Bill
                        McAllister has been an architect in residence for shaping this series which
                        is going to be a highlight of our outreach for the entire year, and it’s
                        wonderful having the HAC members here. We did prove something today – how
                        many HAC members could fit into the back of a Beemer – (laughter) – on our
                        way over. If I told you, I’d probably be arrested for unsafe driving
                        conditions.</p>
                    <p>But anyway, we made it all over here, and they each paid their hundred
                        dollars, which is really great. I want to thank you again, Ed, for having us
                        all here, and I think this is going to be a wonderful presentation this
                        afternoon. Thank you much.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Thank you very much. (Applause.) Let me
                        just add my thanks to Ambassador Brynn’s thanks to all of the folks at the
                        Historian’s Office who did the hard work on it, and also to some of the
                        staff here at the School of Public Policy. Susan McLure, who many of you met
                        on the way in, did a lot of the arrangements here, along with Barb Hill, and
                        Andy Brown has helped us with some of the publicity for the event.</p>
                    <p>A quick note about our schedule for the afternoon. We’ve convinced Kathy
                        Rasmussen, who is the compiler, to lead off, and she’s going to talk about
                        the volume. Around about 3:10 or 3:15 – we’re flexible – we’ll break for
                        coffee, which will be right outside. And then when we resume, we’ve got an
                        academic panel and Q&amp;A scheduled to look at the significance of the
                        foreign economic policy of the period and of this volume. Will Gray from the
                        department of history at Purdue University, Dan Hamilton from the School of
                        Advanced International Studies at Johns Hopkins, Kent Hughes at the Woodrow
                        Wilson International Center, and if she’s able, we’re hoping we’ll still be
                        joined by Susan Aaronson from the Elliot School. Susan’s not feeling well.
                        So whether she’ll be able to join us is still uncertain.</p>
                    <p>After that, there will be yet more coffee, something that’s never in short
                        supply here at a university. And then Under Secretary Hormats will give the
                        keynote address, and then we will celebrate with a bit of a reception next
                        door. So we’re hoping that everyone will be able to stay for the entire time
                        because I’ve been warned that I will have to drink whatever wine you don’t
                        drink. (Laughter.) So in the interest of not getting me arrested, we’re
                        counting on you all to stay and enjoy the full day.</p>
                    <p>As I indicated, we get to lead off with Dr. Kathleen Rasmussen, who is going
                        to talk to us about the volume. Kathy graduated from the University of
                        Toronto with a PhD in history. Before that, I guess, she spent some time
                        here in Washington over across the river at Johns Hopkins SAIS. These are
                        relationships with SAIS that we will change with time. (Laughter.)
                        Apologies, but there’s room for both of us. There’s room for George Mason
                        here as well, so. And of course, before that, Kathy started off her academic
                        work at the University of Toronto, where she studied international relations
                        before she went over to the dark side of history.</p>
                    <p>Kathy has worked as a historian at the Office of the Historian in the State
                        Department since 2002. She’s completed three volumes in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> series. Two of
                        her volumes examine U.S. foreign economic policy during the 1970s, and the
                        third documents U.S. relations with Western Europe, also during the 1970s.
                        Since July, 2009, Kathy has served as the chief of the Asia and General
                        Division of the Office of the Historian. Obviously, the State Department
                        isn’t keeping you busy enough, because you find time also to serve as a
                        professorial lecturer in history at another unnamable university here in the
                        Washington area, the GeorgeWashingtonUniversity, where she teaches
                        diplomatic history.</p>
                    <p>Kathy, thank you so very much for leading us off. (Applause.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Well, I’m certainly not going to be the
                        only one who doesn’t get to offer thanks around here. Before I start, I want
                        to thank Ed Rhodes and his associates here at George Mason for cosponsoring
                        and organizing this conference and hosting it at this lovely new facility. I
                        also want to thank Bill McAllister and Lindsay Krasnoff, who got this thing
                        going in the first place and saw it through to a successful ending. And I
                        also want to extend my thanks to Michael McCoyer, who did all sorts of hard
                        work on getting this thing up and running, especially in securing our
                        speakers for today.</p>
                    <p>And speaking of speakers, let me also thank my – the people who’ve agreed to
                        come here today and speak to us about my little FRUS volume: Susan Aaronson;
                        Will Gray, who actually flew here all the way from Purdue to be with us
                        today; Dan Hamilton and Kent Hughes. I also thank in advance Under Secretary
                        Hormats, who, of course, will be joining us later this afternoon.</p>
                    <p>Finally, needless to say, I thank you all for coming because usually when one
                        thinks about the best way to spend an afternoon, hours of discussion on
                        foreign economic policy is usually not at the top of everybody’s list. So I
                        really do thank you for putting your trust in us that we will be able to
                        engage your attentions for a few hours today. I’ll do what I can to keep it
                        interesting. In this, I think, I’m actually quite helped by my volume on
                        foreign economic policy 1973 to 1976. Perhaps in spite of myself, it
                        actually is a really, really cool and interesting volume because it’s a
                        really cool and interesting time that the volume covers. It’s a volume that
                        explores U.S. monetary, trade, and North-South relations at – in sort of an
                        in-between time, a time of sort of great – a time of great crises, a time of
                        great change, where it was clear that a sort of an old order was passing,
                        but it wasn’t quite apparent yet what the new order was going to be that
                        would take its place. So it’s really – it’s really, again, sort of an
                        in-between time, which I think really sort of makes for a really interesting
                        – at least for me, I found it a really, really fascinating period to
                        study.</p>
                    <p>Just to sort of give you a sense of sort of what the – Richard Nixon and his
                        advisors faced when they came into office for their second term in January
                        of 1973, I just want to sort of sketch out just generally speaking what was
                        going on in the international economy. By January 1973, it was pretty clear
                        that American economic hegemony, which had been sort of rock-solid –
                        rock-solid since – for decades, but certainly since the end of the Second
                        World War, it was clear that hegemony was ebbing. It was clear that the
                        United States was increasingly being challenged as the top dog in the
                        international economy. The nations of Western Europe and Japan had not only
                        recovered from the effects of World War Two, but in fact had experienced the
                        sort of resurgence that actually led a number of them – West Germany and
                        Japan in particular – to increasingly challenge the United States as an
                        economic rival in markets not only around the world but also markets here at
                        home, frighteningly enough for American policymakers.</p>
                    <p>Western Europe was also poised to become even more of a factor in the
                        international scene because, of course, in 1973 the European Economic
                        Community, the EEC, expanded from the original six members to nine members.
                        It started off, of course, with France, Belgium – Belgium, France, Germany,
                        Italy, Luxembourg, and the Netherlands. In 1973, they added three more
                        members: the powerhouse of Denmark, Ireland, and of course most important of
                        all, the United Kingdom, making for a potentially ever more powerful force
                        in the international scene.</p>
                    <p>The system of fixed exchange rates that had been envisioned at the 1944
                        Bretton Woods Conference, this was a system of fixed exchange rates that was
                        really centered on the U.S. dollar. This was a system that was clearly in
                        crisis. One of the first major shocks that hit, actually during the first
                        administration – in the first Nixon Administration, rather, in August of
                        1971, when Nixon unilaterally suspended the gold convertibility of the
                        dollar, thus sort of taking away one of the fundamental props of this fixed
                        exchange rate system. Efforts had been made since August ’71 to cobble the
                        system back together. In December of 1971, there was an agreement at the
                        Smithsonian Institution that Nixon called the greatest monetary agreement in
                        the history of the world, and I’m not exaggerating when I say that, which
                        tried to sort of put the system back together again, establishing a new set
                        of fixed parities that would again allow for a system of fixed exchange
                        rates, which policymakers at the time really believed was key – was key to
                        prosperity as well as just general stability.</p>
                    <p>Within months of establishing this new system, by mid-1972 it was already
                        breaking down again. And by the time that Nixon takes office for the second
                        time in January of ’73, it’s not entirely clear just how stable that system
                        is.</p>
                    <p>The most recent round of GATT negotiations – General Agreement on Tariffs and
                        Trade – the most recent round of GATT negotiations, from 1964 to 1967, the
                        Kennedy Round, had ended – on one hand, it ended in sort of a triumphant way
                        because the Kennedy round negotiators had tried to go beyond just sort of
                        reducing tariffs in order to – trying to do away with some of the non-tariff
                        barriers that impeded trade in the international system. They went, however,
                        quickly from hope to disillusion when the U.S. Congress picked apart the
                        deal and refused to pass various parts of the deal that had been erected
                        during the Kennedy Round, leading to a lot of political recrimination in the
                        Western alliance.</p>
                    <p>The frictions that arose as a result of sort of the crumbling Bretton Woods
                        monetary system and also the – again, the recriminations that were left over
                        from the Kennedy Round of the GATT, these actually led to tensions among the
                        main economic industrialized nations that carried over into the political
                        realm. They’re important enough themselves for the global economy, but
                        they’re also important for the political realm because, of course, America’s
                        primary economic rivals were also America’s primary political allies. And if
                        we learned nothing else in the 1930s, it’s that sometime – is that if you
                        have economic rivalry among countries, this bleeds off into the political
                        area. And so this also sort of threatened the underpinnings of the Western
                        alliance in 1973.</p>
                    <p>During their time in office, first Nixon and then Gerald Ford faced even more
                        global challenges. Interestingly enough, these actually came not from within
                        the Western alliance but actually from the South. In 1973, the autumn of
                        1973, the Arab members of OPEC imposed an oil embargo. And also, OPEC as a
                        whole agreed to cut production of – agreed to oil production cuts as well as
                        price rises in oil. And also, in 1974 the less developed countries called
                        for something called the New International Economic Order. This was an
                        effort by the poorer countries of the world to try to get the richer
                        countries to remake the international global economy in such a way as to
                        redistribute, as to – to effect a better redistribution of the world’s
                        resources and incomes. And if that weren’t challenging enough, Congress
                        began to reassert itself in foreign policymaking, even before Watergate.
                        Even before Watergate arises, Congress is increasingly sort of putting
                        itself back into the policymaking process.</p>
                    <p>Now, my volume examines exactly how Nixon Administration and Ford
                        Administration officials dealt with, again, this sort of time of change and
                        crisis – dealt with this time of change and crisis. The structure of the
                        volume – half of the volume is devoted to international monetary policy as
                        well as the creation of the G-7 summit. This really reflects the fact that
                        the sort of the biggest innovations, the biggest developments during this
                        period, really sort of come out of this disarray in international exchange
                        markets.</p>
                    <p>And just how – you know how, like, singer-songwriters actually kind of like
                        getting into really bad relationships – (laughter) – because it means
                        they’ve got really, really good material to work with? You know how
                        sometimes crisis can be a great time of creativity? This is basically what
                        happened in the 1973 to 1976 period. Because international financial markets
                        were in such total disarray and no one knew what was going to happen next,
                        it actually in the end turns out to be not just a time of crisis but also a
                        time of creativity. You have institutional reform as well as institutional
                        innovation that really sort of changes the way in which the international
                        economy runs.</p>
                    <p>After two massive runs on the dollar within weeks of each other in February
                        and March of 1973, the United States and Western Europe came to a more or
                        less sort of silent agreement that it was time for fixed exchange rates to
                        go. It was time for exchange rates to be the value of national currencies to
                        be determined on the market, and the era of flexible exchange rates began.
                        This was actually a really big intellectual jump, actually, for policymakers
                        because before that, it was thought that fixed exchange rates – that you
                        couldn’t trade unless you had fixed exchange rates because how would you
                        know? How would you be able to make contracts that extended into the future
                        unless you could always be certain what the value of your currency would be
                        in terms of other countries’ currencies? So to go over – to switch to
                        flexible was a huge intellectual leap for these policymakers.</p>
                    <p>The G-7 – the G-7 is also created, and it’s actually created as a result of a
                        French initiative. It’s created as a result of a French initiative in 1975
                        and 1976, with a membership that really reflects this new global
                        distribution of economic power, essentially. The United States’, again,
                        hegemony is ebbing. And it’s not just the United States that is really sort
                        of dominating the international economy. The fact there are – it has six
                        partners, six partners now with which it feels the need to sort of discuss
                        global economic developments, is not only an important sort of institutional
                        reform but, again, reflects this new reality. Note, incidentally, that of
                        course, just to sort of contrast it with the 1940s, note that three of the
                        seven members of the G-7 – the United States, the United Kingdom, Canada,
                        Germany, France, Italy, Japan – notice that three of those – Germany, Italy,
                        and Japan – actually were our enemies in World War Two and so actually had
                        not been a part of the effort to remake the economy after World War Two.</p>
                    <p>The volume’s second half is divided equally between trade policy and
                        North-South relations. The trade compilation covers the passage of a
                        landmark piece of legislation, the Trade Act of 1974, which introduces a
                        number of innovations into American commercial policy. It renewed the
                        President’s authority to negotiate reductions in tariffs. This authority was
                        necessary to engage in a new round of GATT negotiations. It implements what
                        we know today as fast-track authority, whereby Congress can vote yea or nay
                        on trade deals that include reductions in non-tariff barriers. It reworked
                        the fair trade laws of the United States, such that U.S. producers who felt
                        they were being damaged by foreign trade could have easier recourse to the
                        government to help protect their interests. It instituted a series of tariff
                        preferences for LDCs in order to encourage development through trade.</p>
                    <p>It did all of these things, and yet no one remembers the Trade Act of 1974
                        for doing all of these things because the Trade Act of 1974 also has the
                        Jackson-Vanik amendment, and everybody remembers the Trade Act of 1974
                        because it has the Jackson-Vanik amendment, which is that amendment to a
                        title of the act which conditions the granting of normal trade status, Most
                        Favored Nation status, to the emigration policies of non-market economies.
                        “I’m looking at you, Soviet Union,” is really what the Trade Act of ’74 is
                        saying, although it never actually says it outright.</p>
                    <p>The trade compilation also looks at the beginning of the Tokyo Round of GATT
                        negotiations. These began in 1973. The United States really believed that it
                        was important to have this round in order to make – not only to build on the
                        Kennedy Round but also, in a way, to actually to sort of make amends for
                        what had happened during the Kennedy Round, and this time to start attacking
                        non-tariff barriers in a way that – where they – where the United States
                        would do it right. Unfortunately, the progress of that round was stymied by
                        the fact that the United States had no negotiating authority for the first
                        15, 16, 17 months of that round, simply because the trade act wouldn’t pass
                        because of Jackson-Vanik.</p>
                    <p>The final quarter of the volume is on North-South policy, which tackles sort
                        of the traditional issues that are dealt with in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>
                        volumes, the development of U.S. tradepolicy but also, in my opinion, the
                        more interesting documents explore how Henry Kissinger, who really took the
                        lead in this – Henry Kissinger responded to the challenge that was posed to
                        the North by – the industrialized North by the less-developed South, that
                        said we want a new international economic order; what are you guys going to
                        do about it?</p>
                    <p>When you’re putting together a <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume, you’re
                        encouraged to think of the series as a whole. You’re encouraged to think of
                        it, as Henry Kissinger would have said, as an organic whole. Each volume
                        tells a different aspect of the story. And whereas I believe that <hi
                            rend="italic">Foreign Economic Policy</hi><hi rend="italic">’73-’76</hi>
                        really does stand on its own as an independent volume, it is also really
                        profitably read with a number of other volumes in the series. We have some
                        volumes on energy policy for the 1970s that provide a very important
                        complement to it, volumes on the Soviet Union, particularly when it comes to
                        the Jackson-Vanik amendment, global issues, Western Europe – these – the
                        volume on Japan – these volumes also sort of provide different aspects of
                        the story that’s told in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The volume contains documents from all the usual agencies that you’d expect
                        to find in <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi>. We’ve got the National Security
                        Council; we’ve got the Department of State; we’ve got the White House. But
                        of course, we also have some voices that one doesn’t usually hear from in
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, including, of course, the
                        Treasury, the ever robust voice of the Federal Reserve Board and Arthur
                        Burns’s extreme wonkiness as chairman of the Fed. We have the Special Trade
                        Representative, we have the Council on Economic Advisors, Council on
                        International Economic Policy, and the Economic Policy Board.</p>
                    <p>And interestingly enough, of course, because this is a volume that deals with
                        the ’73 to ’76 period, we actually really have honest-to-God voices because
                        we have the Nixon tapes. And I think some of the most interesting documents
                        actually in the volume are the transcripts of the Nixon tapes, when you see
                        Nixon and Kissinger and Paul Volcker and George Shultz really sort of
                        hammering out what approach we should take to, in this case, the exchange
                        crisis of the spring of 1973.</p>
                    <p>And it’s those conversations that, I think, in addition to sort of the theme
                        of crisis and chaos but also creativity that I think sort of runs through
                        the volume – those tapes really highlight another theme, which I think is
                        really integral to the volume, which is the intersection of political – of
                        politics and economics, essentially. It’s not just econ policy wonks who are
                        making policy by any means. Politics, domestic politics, foreign politics,
                        very much factor into the policy choices that are made during this period.
                        So for example, in March of 1973, there’s a run on the U.S. dollar. That’s
                        again – that’s the second exchange crisis to hit the United States in a
                        matter of weeks. And Nixon’s concern is less with what this means for the
                        future of the monetary system and more on how this will reflect on the
                        United States as a leader in the international community. If we devalue the
                        dollar again, does that make us look weak? If we don’t take the lead in
                        trying to find a solution to this problem, will that make the Europeans
                        doubt our leadership? What if we want – what if we use our actions – Nixon
                        thought, what if we use our actions in the monetary realm in order to get
                        the Europeans to play ball with us on other issues, such as MBFR or NATO
                        reductions?</p>
                    <p>Kissinger, also, of course, is obsessed with politics when it comes to this
                        exchange crisis. And unlike Nixon, who really wants to use the crisis to
                        solidify relations with the Europeans, Kissinger wants to use the crisis to
                        beat them over the head and teach them a lesson and, if possible, split them
                        apart entirely so that we can dominate them. In very, very open – (laughter)
                        – very open and very assertive terms, Henry believes that this is really the
                        crisis when we should tell – show the Europeans that they can’t push America
                        around, that we may want them to be integrated, blah, blah, blah, but we
                        don’t want them to be integrated into a force that opposes us.</p>
                    <p>The Jackson-Vanik amendment is obviously – the Jackson-Vanik amendment is
                        clearly a product of politics. Congressional members sought to actually turn
                        – of course, Nixon’s and Kissinger’s policy of linkage on its head, using
                        Nixon’s promise of Most Favored Nation for the – status for the Soviet Union
                        in order to affect human rights policies within the Soviet Union. And also,
                        the way in which Nixon and Kissinger address the challenge posed by Congress
                        in the form of the Jackson-Vanik amendment also, of course, is highly
                        political.</p>
                    <p>Because the Jackson-Vanik amendment is embedded in this big, huge piece of
                        trade legislation, what it comes down to in the end is Nixon and Kissinger
                        have to make a choice: Do you want to get this piece of trade legislation
                        passed? And if you want to, the best thing to do is just like take MFN for
                        the Soviet Union out of it altogether. Or do you want to leave it in and
                        have – sort of hold the entire American commercial policy program hostage to
                        this one title of Most Favored Nation for the Soviet Union? Nixon and
                        Kissinger choose to leave MFN in, which means that the trade bill takes a
                        long, long time to pass. And Charles Cooper, who’s a member of the NSC staff
                        – I thought he put – I thought he had a really perceptive observation in
                        October of 1973, in which he said that the way in which Nixon and Kissinger
                        were approaching the issue of MFN and the trade bill was that they were –
                        quote –“putting the relationship with Moscow ahead of the relationship with
                        our allies and friends,” which is really actually one of the subtexts I
                        think of the way in which they deal with Jackson-Vanik.</p>
                    <p>Let me just briefly also say when it comes to North-South policy, the
                        rhetorical response to LDC demands for a new international economic order
                        was a source of controversy in the Ford Administration, not the policy that
                        we would pursue but how we talked about that policy on the world stage. That
                        was a source of big controversy. And in this wonderful series of meetings in
                        May of 1975, the Secretary of the Treasury, William Simon, dukes it out with
                        Henry Kissinger in front of Gerald Ford, in which Kissinger wants to make a
                        series of speeches in the international arena in which he pays at least some
                        rhetorical mind to the fact that the South believes that the system is
                        arrayed against them. But William Simon says no, that’s socialism, and we’re
                        Americans, and we believe in free market principles; we can’t even bend on
                        terms of rhetoric. And Henry wants to bend in terms of rhetoric, because he
                        says if we bend in terms of rhetoric, then we can split the less developed
                        countries and we can nail them on individual issues, and I don’t want to do
                        international economic order either, but I want to at least make it seem
                        like I want international order because it’s going to look better for our
                        image to do so.</p>
                    <p>I think the issues covered in this volume continue to be relevant to the
                        present day. Clearly, politics has not left us, nor has image left us when
                        it comes to international economic policy. And I will just sort tell you an
                        – I’ll just tell you briefly an anecdote which really reflects sadly on me
                        as a human being more than on anything else. I remember I awoke one morning
                        in September of 2009 to the fact that the G-8, which had replaced the G-7 in
                        1997 with the addition of Russia, had officially declared itself obsolete,
                        that it was replacing itself with the G-20 and that henceforth the G-8
                        wasn’t enough, that once again sort of the global balance of power had
                        shifted so that it wasn’t just enough to have the eight in the room; you
                        actually need to have 20 countries in the room. And I remember feeling some
                        nostalgia for the passing of the creation of the G-7 that I documented in my
                        volume.</p>
                    <p>I’m serious; I’m, like, waking up to NPR, listening to this, and thinking
                        “that’s just too bad, that time has come and gone.” And on an even more
                        personal level, what strikes me as particularly noting as – of the coming of
                        the G-20, which, of course, has replaced the G-8, is that, man, this is
                        going to make my life difficult in 30 years when I do the <hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi> volume on foreign economic policy – (laughter) – because now
                        I’ve got to deal with, like, 20 countries as opposed to 7.</p>
                    <p>And on that note, I will say thank you very much for your attention.
                        (Applause.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Would you be willing to take a few
                        questions if there are –</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Oh, if there are questions.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Are there – before we break for coffee,
                        are some questions – there’ll be more time for questions later as well. But
                        if you want a chance to grill Kathy right now –</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Or you can grill me over coffee.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Silence. Well –</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Kathy, can you tell us a little more about
                        the NIEO? Was there like an emerging debate within the government about it,
                        or was it just we think this is a dumb idea from the beginning and just a
                        matter of how to spin it? Was there any – how did the policy for the U.S.
                        emerge when it came to the New International Economic Order?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> I think there is, even beyond rhetoric.
                        I mean, it’s really this discussion that I examined, that I mentioned, from
                        May of 1975 really focuses on the rhetoric. But I do think that there is – I
                        think the administration is split. William Simon is known – the Treasury
                        Secretary who followed George Shultz – he really is known as being a very
                        hard line sort of free market principles sort of guy. I think that in other
                        realms of the department, and particularly the Department of State, there
                        was more of a willingness to go some way to meet the demands of the less
                        developed nations, but not in any – I mean, we are talking about degrees as
                        opposed to sort of a fundamental shift of U.S. foreign economic policy
                        because, of course, quite frankly, we’re quite happy with how the system is
                        ordered. It’s worked well for us for quite some time, and we don’t really
                        want to see fundamentally any changes to it.</p>
                    <p>So there are debates, but it’s really a matter of just – it’s not a – it’s
                        not, hey, this is a great idea; let’s do it. It’s far more sort of a matter
                        of degrees about how far are we willing to stray towards a slightly more
                        managed global economy. So, from outright opposition to okay, we can
                        consider it. So there is some debate.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Since Henry Kissinger used to like to say
                        that he wasn’t really interested in economic policies, who from your volume
                        do you think has Henry’s ear? Was it Bob Hormats or somebody else on his
                        staff, or was he actually interested in it and didn’t (inaudible)?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> I think that he certainly – I mean, Bob
                        Hormats has his ear. Charles Cooper, who’s an NSC staff member, has his ear.
                        Tom Enders, when he moves over to State, has his ear. So he does – he is
                        careful – Hal Sonnenfeldt, actually, interestingly enough, also has his ear.
                        He is careful to have advisors who can explain to him what’s going on,
                        because – I mean, in many documents in the volume, Kissinger freely admits
                        that he absolutely no idea what’s going on terms of the economics. I think
                        he’s bluffing, to a certain extent. There’s this wonderful staff meeting in
                        which Kissinger throws up his hands and says, “I have no idea what’s going
                        on,” and he knows full well what’s going on, actually. He’s able to tell Tom
                        Enders exactly what’s happening.</p>
                    <p>Whether or not Henry Kissinger likes economics, after he becomes Secretary of
                        State in September of 1973, economics is thrust upon him and he is forced to
                        deal with the issues not only in terms of sort of, again, their importance
                        to the global economy, but he continues to do what he had done for –
                        throughout his time as National Security Advisor, which is to look at them
                        within sort of the geopolitics of the economic issues, which is why he gets
                        into trouble with people like Bill Simon, who just really believe that he’s
                        being too political and not economic focused enough. But he’s not quite the
                        naïf that he claims to be.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Kathy, this is the time when you have Bob
                        McNamara at the World Bank.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Mm-hmm.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> And exactly the period where he’s making a
                        big speech in ’73 on poverty in Nairobi. He obviously is a Democrat,
                        obviously appointed by Johnson. What do you find the policymakers in the
                        government saying about the bank and about McNamara?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> It’s not – McNamara actually figures in
                        a number of the documents, particularly in the early period, when we are
                        trying to get some appropriations through Congress in order to fund some of
                        the bank programs. And he fades from view as time goes on, as I think that
                        sort of energies on the development issues are shifted away from traditional
                        sort of – the 28th annual replenishment of the IDA. I mean, as we sort of
                        shift away from those sort of questions into sort of – not just sort of
                        thinking about how do we keep what we’ve got going, but shift it over to how
                        can we sort of make something new, because clearly what we’ve got going
                        isn’t really working all that well.</p>
                    <p>So McNamara actually – although he does figure – he does actually figure
                        prominently in a few telephone conversations, actually in the beginning, I
                        feel like he fades away. I feel like, also, he fades away is because, as
                        Nixon and – as the Nixon and Ford Administration goes on, Congress is
                        increasingly stingier when it comes to appropriations for the international
                        development – international lending – financial institutions, I beg your
                        pardon, the IFIs. And so, again, sort of the shift of the focus – the White
                        House’s focus also shifts as well, away from, again, these more traditional
                        things on to new ideas like: Do we want to have a common fund? Do we want to
                        have buffer stocks? I mean, do we want to, instead of giving less developed
                        countries money, or engaging in sort of discrete development products, do we
                        want to completely rework how primary commodities are bought and sold?
                        Because that’s what they’re talking about. They’re really talking about sort
                        of restructuring the international economy to give certain advantages to the
                        LDCs. And again, there really is – I do see a sort of shift of focus.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> [Somewhat related to that, in Margaret de
                        Vries’ history of the IMF] there’s this latent vitriol between Pierre-Paul
                        Schweitzer and Nixon, but there’s nothing at all about him at this point
                        [but there’s nothing at all about him in this volume].</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Yeah, I think there may be – if memory
                        serves, there might be, like, a footnote on it. (Laughter.) It’s true,
                        because I think the French are really cross, of course, that we don’t
                        support their candidate to – the renewal of his tenure as head of the IMF.
                        It’s – when you do one of these volumes, ultimately, of course, you have to
                        make choices. And in terms of sort of the internal workings of the IMF and
                        the structure of the organization, I tended to sort of focus more on sort of
                        actually the reform of the organization as opposed to the sort of stuff that
                        Margaret Garritsen de Vries would cover in her official history of the
                        IMF.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Kathy, talk about the tapes. How useful were
                        they to you? How awful were they to use, or –</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> The terrifying thing about the tapes is
                        that when you listen – so these Nixon tapes, these are wonderful in a
                        crisis. That’s – they – I found them most particularly helpful in the
                        exchange crises of February and March of 1973. The one thing, though, where
                        you have to be really careful when you work with the Nixon tapes is that we
                        had a number of folks in our office who did the first transcripts of the
                        tapes. But then, of course, the compiler will listen to the tapes and look
                        at the transcripts over and over again. The danger of working with the Nixon
                        tapes is that when you listen to them enough times, they worm their way into
                        your head. (Laughter.) So now when I read those transcripts, I can hear the
                        economists speaking slowly and in a monotone. And it’s just horrible.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p>So in a way, they’re horrible. But in another way, what I love about them is
                        that they’re unguarded. They show – as actually, as David’s question sort of
                        alluded to – they show the strengths and the flaws of policymakers. Nixon
                        clearly – sometimes he gets what’s going on and other times he’s making
                        random analogies about poker games that have nothing to do with what’s going
                        on, and he’s just trying to seem – like, he’s just trying to hold on for
                        dear life. So they really are – I mean, they – it’s – they really are a
                        priceless – priceless documents. And again, though, I think for me, I think
                        that they’re best used in a crisis, when the tensions are focused and
                        Nixon’s not just rambling about who he likes and who he doesn’t like.</p>
                    <p>Kent?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Kathy, thanks for a wonderful overview.
                        How do we sign up for your diplomatic class? (Inaudible.) (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Yeah, I feel sorry for them. They get
                        entirely too much of this, actually. (Laughter.) They get – they know way
                        more about the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act than any person should know.
                        (Laughter.) It’s really quite terrifying.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Well, in your – you cover the shift
                        between Nixon and Ford.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Yeah.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Are there three policy areas that really
                        were decided differently, do you think, because of that shift?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Oh, I think so. I think the fact that
                        Jackson-Vanik – I think the fact that the trade bill passed is entirely due
                        to Gerald Ford, because Nixon clearly has other things on his mind from
                        April in ’73 until August of – well, January ’73 until August 1974. And, I
                        mean, clearly, getting an acceptable amendment that somehow bridged the gap
                        between what Congress wanted and what the Soviet Union would accept in terms
                        of our fulfilling the promises that we made to them at the Moscow summit,
                        clearly that was going to take a decision at the political level. And Nixon
                        just either was unwilling or, more to the point, probably incapable of sort
                        of focusing his attentions on it.</p>
                    <p>But Gerald Ford comes in, and with his legislative experience, he just gets
                        right on that thing. So actually, I believe that Ford really deserves the
                        credit for actually getting the trade act finally passed through
                        Congress.</p>
                    <p>I wonder, too, with the creation of the G-7 summit – again, this is – the G-7
                        is very much a French initiative to which we respond. And there’s actually
                        some resistance in the Treasury Department to a positive response to the
                        initiative. We’re afraid that the French are going to back us into a corner
                        and force us to accept gold as the center of the monetary – international
                        monetary system, and also France’s general awesomeness. And so the Treasury
                        Department’s like, “Mr. President, you can’t get into a room with those
                        French; they’ll just pin you down, and this is just not going to – it’s not
                        going to work.” But Ford doesn’t listen to them.</p>
                    <p>And I wonder – I do wonder if Nixon would have been – I wonder if Nixon would
                        have been able to allow some – another country to take the lead. But Ford
                        doesn’t have a problem with it, for better and for worse. So I think that
                        Ford also is – even though his performance at the G-7 summit is not what one
                        would want – it’s clear he’s reading the text of the prepared remarks and
                        he’s not engaging like the other leaders – I do believe that Ford also
                        deserves a lot of credit for being open to an act of leadership on behalf of
                        another country.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Let me cut off the discussion for right
                        now so that we can get a cup of coffee, and then we can come back and grill
                        the panel, let the panel have some comments, and then grill them. Thank you,
                        Kathy. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="panel">
                    <head>Panel Discussion</head>
                    <p>George Mason University School of Public Policy, Arlington, Virginia <lb/>
                        March 7, 2011</p>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item><list>
                                <head>MODERATOR</head>
                                <item>Ed Rhodes, Dean, George Mason School of Public Policy</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item>Prof. Will Gray, Department of History, Purdue University </item>
                                <item>Dr. Dan Hamilton, School of Advanced International Studies,
                                    Johns Hopkins University </item>
                                <item>Dr. Kent Hughes, Woodrow Wilson International Center for
                                    Scholars</item>
                                <item>Dr. Kathleen Rasmussen, Division Chief, Asia &amp; General,
                                    Office of the Historian</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p><ref
                            target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/conferences/2011-foreign-economic-policy/FEP_Panel_Discussion.mp3"
                            >Download Audio</ref> (45.6 MB MP3)</p>
                    <p rend="italic">Note: This transcript and linked audio recording contain
                        comments made during a roundtable discussion of the “Foreign Economic
                        Policy, 1973-1976” volume of the <title>Foreign Relations of the United
                            States</title> (FRUS) series. The comments of Robert Hormats and
                        Kathleen Rasmussen reflect their individual points of view and do not
                        necessarily reflect the views of the Department of State or the United
                        States Government.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Well, let’s resume. I know folks are
                        still drifting back in with coffee, and more folks will drift in as we
                        proceed. But picking up where Kathy has left us with a background on the
                        volume and its contents, we have now a terrific panel. Sadly, Susan Aaronson
                        couldn’t be with us, but a terrific panel picking up on different themes
                        that were developed in the volume. </p>
                    <p>Let me do some introductions, and then the plan is to let each of the three
                        panelists make some remarks, and then we’ll open up to general discussion
                        questions on the floor. Closest to me, Professor William Gray from Purdue
                        University Department of History. Professor Gray, Ph.D. from Yale
                        University, another from the dark side. (Laughter.) </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> Very dark, very dark. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Prof. Gray is – has a book with the
                        University of North Carolina Press on <hi rend="italic">Germany’s Cold War:
                            The Global Campaign to Isolate East Germany</hi> . A recent -- I’m
                        picking and choosing, in fact. To list all of their accomplishments, we’d be
                        here all day. But a recent book chapter in a volume by – edited by Tom
                        Schwartz and Matthias Schulz, a chapter entitled, “Toward a Community of
                        Stability: The Deutsche Mark between European and Atlantic Priorities 1968
                        -’73.” And a recent article in <hi rend="italic">Diplomatic History</hi> ,
                        “Floating the System: Germany, the United States, and the Breakdown of
                        Bretton Woods, 1969-1973.” </p>
                    <p>Next to – let’s jump to the far end, to Dan Hamilton. Dr. Hamilton is at
                        Johns Hopkins SAIS Foreign Policy Institute, where he is research professor
                        and also director of the Center for Transatlantic Relations, and also
                        executive director of the American Consortium on EU Studies. Dr. Hamilton
                        got his Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins. He is former deputy assistant secretary of
                        state for European Affairs, former U.S. special coordinator for Southeast
                        European stabilization, and former associate director of the Policy Planning
                        staff for no less than two secretaries of state. Among his long list of
                        books, a few recent books – one titled, <hi rend="italic">Shoulder to
                            Shoulder: Forging a Strategic U.S.-EU Partnership,</hi> another on the
                        transatlantic economy<hi rend="italic">,</hi> and another on the <hi
                            rend="italic">Alliance Reborn: An Atlantic Compact for the 21st
                            Century.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Kent Hughes, stuck in the middle here between these two Europeanists. Dr.
                        Hughes received his Ph.D. in economics from Washington University in St.
                        Louis. Dr. Hughes is currently the – at the Woodrow Wilson International
                        Center for Scholars, where he is director of The Program on America and the
                        Global Economy, and also director of the Wilson Center on the Hill. He was
                        in the past associate deputy secretary of Commerce, also president of the
                        Council on Competitiveness, and chief economist to the late Senate Majority
                        Leader Robert Byrd. Among his publications, a book with Johns Hopkins
                        University Press, <hi rend="italic">Building the Next American Century: The
                            Past and Future of Economic Competitiveness,</hi> and among his
                        articles, one here – <hi rend="italic">“</hi> Innovation in the United
                        States: The Interplay of History, Institutions, and American Culture.”</p>
                    <p>I think we’ll take folks in alphabetical order. Does that seem all right,
                        beginning with you, Dr. Gray?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> Well, I believe we had already considered
                        that perhaps the historian would represent the past, moving along to the
                        policies.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Well, I will let the panelists determine
                        the sequence of events here. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HAMILTON:</hi> He came the furthest. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> All right. Well, thanks all for your
                        attention. I have to say this is a unique pleasure in a couple of respects
                        -- first of all, because as a historian, I do not always get to interact
                        with policy-interested scholars. And, secondly, as a historian of Germany, I
                        do not always reach out to historians of American foreign relations,
                        although I have found the SHAFR organization to be quite welcoming over the
                        years, nevertheless. </p>
                    <p>Thanks in particular to Kathy and Michael for inviting me to come for what
                        was actually just a nice excuse to hang out in the capital. </p>
                    <p>Any event, I’m going to separate my commentary into two sections, one
                        concerning the story arc that’s found in this volume and one concerning the
                        use of sources. In both, I want to emphasize that the editor’s selections
                        are likely to have a significant impact on future historical research about
                        the Nixon and Ford Administrations. And I will probably refer to this often
                        as “Kathy’s volume.” That’s how I’ve come to think of it. </p>
                    <p>But of course, although I think that you have probably spent more time with
                        these pages than many people will likely in the future in its entirety,
                        what’s fascinating is that each of us comes to this with fresh eyes. And I
                        think I may actually politely disagree with you on some of the results of
                        your own volume, as it were. </p>
                    <p>But the volume opens in a phase of complete disorder for the world economy –
                        confidence in the U.S. dollar is waning, speculators are mounting sustained
                        attacks on the lira, the dollar, the pound, and the Nixon Administration is
                        shown here as facing a dilemma. Nixon and Kissinger repeatedly expressed
                        their interest in showing American leadership on economic issues. After all,
                        monetary problems had moved to the forefront of diplomatic attention in the
                        early 1970s. </p>
                    <p>And I think that, in some ways, it’s appropriate that this is one of the
                        earlier volumes from this period, ’73-‘76, to appear, because in terms of –
                        if you were to look for a spine of U.S. foreign relations, increasingly it’s
                        shifting, I believe, toward economic issues. I think that a number of other
                        volumes that come out, whether it’s Western Europe or United Nations, Energy
                        Policy, if there is such a volume, all these things will end up referring
                        back to in many ways the sort of fundamental material which is found here.
                        Henry Kissinger himself expressed this in a quote that’s tucked in the back.
                        And for those who are tempted to let go of the commodity policy section,
                        I’ll point out that some of the juiciest quotes are in the very back of the
                        book. Now, this is out of context, but Kissinger remarks, at one point, and
                        I think it’s quite interesting – I don’t actually know what he means – “The
                        trick in the world now is to use economics to build a world political
                        structure;” mysterious, no?</p>
                    <p> </p>
                    <p>In any event, my point for now is that they understand that economic problems
                        are at the forefront of diplomatic attention. But they conclude that it’s
                        not worthwhile to expend the resources necessary to keep propping up the
                        U.S. dollar. They’re well aware that Congress is increasingly hostile toward
                        shoveling money toward the IMF, the World Bank, and other international
                        institutions. The trouble is that absent American efforts to support fixed
                        exchange rates, the Europeans have decided to arrange a joint float of their
                        currencies, a move that will draw them closer together and apparently
                        reinforce their growing distance from America. This is all the more
                        worrisome in light of the fact that Britain has not joined the EC, making it
                        a Europe of nine, and thank you to Kathy for spelling out all nine already.
                        It appears that Europe, the United States, and Japan are emerging as three
                        separate, if interrelated, centers of global capitalism, a tendency
                        acknowledged in David Rockefeller’s creation of the Trilateral Commission in
                        1972 and ’73. Trilateral thinking turns up in this FRUS volume as well, as
                        seen in a lengthy planning paper from December 1973, produced by the State
                        Department’s director of planning and coordination. </p>
                    <p>Surprisingly, perhaps, the paper in question sees a trend toward greater
                        entropy and less interdependence among the three big regions. The prediction
                        was that the relative decline of American economic might would bring greater
                        self-sufficiency for Europe and Japan. Perhaps not self-sufficiency, given
                        the obvious resource weaknesses that – lack of oil – that Japan and Western
                        Europe had, but nevertheless a belief that the industrial world would become
                        less integrated. I found that to be a fascinating and totally wrong
                        prediction. </p>
                    <p> </p>
                    <p>So to state the problem faced by Nixon and Ford in a different way, how could
                        the United States remain active in shaping international economic and
                        monetary environments at a time of weak American prestige and hyper-vigilant
                        congressional scrutiny?</p>
                    <p>I want to discuss two U.S. approaches featured here in the volume. The first
                        involves a blunt American effort to shoehorn its way into allied decision
                        making exemplified by the Year of Europe controversy that raged in 1973 and
                        ’74. Historians have been examining this episode for some time now,
                        including in that volume that we just heard about edited by Tom Schwartz. I
                        think two or three different speakers at that conference spoke about the
                        Year of Europe initiative. Historians have been examining this for some time
                        now dating it from the moment of Henry Kissinger’s controversial speech on
                        April 23, 1973, in which he more or less said, “America is a global power;
                        Europe is a regional power. European countries, therefore, need to line up
                        in some ways and coordinate with the United States.”</p>
                    <p>The Europeans reacted testily to the proposition that it was America’s
                        business to proclaim a Year of Europe. And this, in turn, touched off
                        indignant reactions in Washington. The whole affair was only really resolved
                        in the summer of 1974 with the adoption of parallel declarations by NATO and
                        then a separate U.S.-EC document. Now Kathy’s volume allows us to connect
                        this diplomatic kerfuffle, which is often mostly related to alliance
                        security to problems of political economy in a new way. It turns out the
                        Year of Europe idea long predated Kissinger’s April, 1973 speech. It appears
                        as early as January of ’73 in a Treasury memo advocating trade negotiations
                        with the newly expanded Europe of nine. Whether the Europeans knew it or
                        not, the Nixon Administration was coming to see European integration as
                        something of a problem. </p>
                    <p>More importantly, we learned that the behavior of European leaders during the
                        currency crises of February and March, 1973, above all, the German-led
                        initiative to institute a joint float of European currencies, touched off a
                        real concern at the White House. Kissinger insists on March 3rd, ’73 that,
                        “We must make clear to the Europeans that they cannot take a common position
                        without consultation with us on a matter that vitally affects our interest
                        and buy us off in the currency of abstract currency integration,” end quote.
                        So the germ of Kissinger’s infamous Year of Europe initiative is seen here
                        as a direct response to international monetary issues, the breakdown of
                        Bretton Woods. As far as I know, that’s not a connection that historians
                        have made thus far. I certainly hadn’t myself.</p>
                    <p>Less surprising, perhaps, is the thoroughly partisan world view displayed by
                        Nixon. Kathy made some reference to this. Nixon’s commentaries about
                        European politics show him to be moderately well-informed, but emphatically
                        anxious to stave off his excess of the Left in France and Germany, the Left
                        being defined as socialist, social democrats, basically anyone, I suppose,
                        to the right of the Christian Democrats. If European integration was a
                        problem, the in Nixon’s perspective, this reflected, in part, a fear of what
                        a socialist Europe might look like. And here I’m going to quote once again.
                        These documents really contain so much of this, and it’s a shame not to kind
                        of get into the juice here. “Today, however, when we talk of European
                        unity,” says Nixon, “And when we look far ahead, we have to recognize the
                        stark fact that a united Europe will be led primarily by left-leaning or
                        socialist heads of government.” And so this is an independent reason –
                        independent of whatever objective differences of economic interests might be
                        evident between Europe and the United States. It’s simply for political
                        reasons a united Europe was <hi rend="italic">unerwunschte</hi> , not
                        desired in some ways by the Nixon folk. </p>
                    <p>Now, by itself, Kissinger’s Year of Europe initiative could hardly be
                        considered a success. Yet the general American strategy of inserting itself
                        into, and at times disrupting European decision making appears to have
                        gained better traction in connection with the oil shocks of ’73 and ’74. The
                        present <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> volume doesn’t deal directly with energy
                        policy. I assume that coverage is planned separately. But based on the
                        behavior I’ve seen here, I strongly suspect that Kissinger’s initiative for
                        the creation of an international energy agency, the basis for the still
                        topical strategic petroleum reserve, was undertaking the expectation that
                        this would drive a wedge between the key European powers, Germany and
                        France, as indeed it did. We do see here a remarkable deference toward
                        France, a conscious effort to coddle President Pompidou and Pompidou’s
                        successor, Giscard. Perhaps because Helmut Schmidt, the German finance
                        minister, and later chancellor, was repeatedly characterized accurately as a
                        close American ally, more attention was devoted to stroking French egos. The
                        French problem was tied in directly to the question of gold in the
                        international monetary system which received surprisingly extensive coverage
                        here. </p>
                    <p>And here to speak as a fellow historical researcher for just a moment, I have
                        to admit that having looked at Arthur Burns’ papers also in the Gerald Ford
                        Library, I was astonished to learn how much interesting material was in
                        folder B-52 on gold because I did not have the stamina to make my way
                        through that material, and you did. (Laughter.) </p>
                    <p>So Kathy sets up a tense rivalry in her work, and I call this section a story
                        arc for a reason. There is a story that I think editors pick up on and
                        convey through their choice of documentation. Kathy conveys a tense rivalry
                        between Treasury and the Fed on the gold problem leading to an almost
                        comical series of parallel memos submitted to President Ford by Arthur Burns
                        and Bill Simon. In the end, the Bank of France received America’s tacit
                        consent to sell off a certain portion of gold at market price allowing
                        handsome gains that Germany could not realize because it had done the U.S. a
                        favor all along by keeping dollars in place of gold. And so often in the
                        past, France was in a sense rewarded for its obstreperous behavior.
                        (Laughter.) Though I should point out that Paris did not achieve its larger
                        goal – the return of a gold-backed fixed rate international monetary system. </p>
                    <p>Now, the second, and in some ways, opposite American strategy having sketched
                        already this desire to, in a sense, split apart Europe and make sure that
                        Europe could not gang up on the United States in some way – the second, and
                        in some ways, opposite American strategy that I see conveyed here involved
                        efforts coordinate economic policy on a relatively equal basis among the
                        three major economic groupings, a program that gave rise during this period
                        to the economic summits we now see, although they didn’t at the time, as the
                        birth of the G-7. </p>
                    <p>Does this really count as U.S. leadership if the U.S. wasn’t completely
                        running the show? Historians, including myself, have tended to stress the
                        agency of France and Germany in staging the Rambouillet Summit, the first of
                        these, a summit of six, another reason why we can’t really call it the first
                        G-7 Summit, but close enough. Kathy’s volume shows us that the Ford
                        administration went in with limited expectations. For example, Helmut
                        Sonnenfeldt remarked offhandedly in October 1975, that the Germans were
                        unrealistic to expect interest rate coordination between the Federal Reserve
                        and the Bundesbank. Robert Hormats wrote Kissinger three weeks before the
                        summit depicting the occasion as a kind of global public relations exercise.
                        It would, as he put it, try to project publicly that Western leaders are
                        able to manage current problems. These were modest goals. </p>
                    <p>In many respects, Ford’s economic team went in with a negative agenda
                        intending to stave off French pressure to return to fixed exchange rates,
                        ignore German pressure to engage in deficit-driven reflation, and stress the
                        advantages of letting all the countries in question pursue whatever
                        independent policies appeared necessary to bring inflation under control
                        while stimulating economic growth. Looking at these low key predictions in
                        advance of the Rambouillet Summit, the eventual success of the G-7 model
                        appears all the more striking. At its best over the next decade, the G-7
                        group would engage in interest rate coordination and implement far-reaching
                        agreements about which countries should reflate or inflate for the sake of
                        achieving balanced and stable growth across the industrial West. </p>
                    <p>Naturally, this raises significant questions for historians of the period.
                        Why did the G-7 work? How could a mere three days of conversation outside
                        Paris followed by a similar meeting in Puerto Rico the following summer lay
                        the foundations for a resurgence of Western confidence? Why did the 1970s
                        ultimately pave the way toward greater economic interdependence giving rise
                        to what we’ve come to call globalization rather than fostering the breakup
                        of the world economy into distinct industrial regions as predicted by the
                        State Department in 1973? Now, obviously, I don’t need to suggest that these
                        diplomatic summits are totally the explanation, that one would find the
                        explanation simply in the realm of international summit diplomacy in the
                        first place. And I also imagine that trying to address these questions would
                        require far more time than we have over the next two hours and perhaps even
                        more than the immense quantity of material already assembled in this
                        volume.</p>
                    <p>Among other things, reference to the documentary record of the other major
                        powers would be essential, and I quite agree that the <hi rend="italic"
                            >FRUS</hi> volume is sort of the gold standard, but I have to say, one
                        of the happy results is that the Germans now are producing a very, very
                        strong document publication with an emphasis on year by year publication. So
                        I believe my library will soon have 1980 on its shelves which is a wonderful
                        asset. And of course, the French are trailing, but they are into the late
                        1960s by now in their own French document series. </p>
                    <p>In any event, <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> is – <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> is
                            <hi rend="italic">FRUS</hi> , and we’re very fortunate to have it. And
                        in studying American foreign relations, I have lost my place. (Laughter.)
                        Yes, I see clues in the documents at hand for addressing some of these
                        larger questions that I have just raised from this American material. Robert
                        Hormats did not just stress the public relations facets of the Rambouillet
                        Summit. He noted also that this summit’s objective should be a serious
                        inquiry into common problems. </p>
                    <p>The Ford administration went to Paris prepared to listen. Unlike, say, the
                        Carter administration at the London Summit of 1977, Ford’s team came without
                        a set of prescriptions. They sized up their fellow leaders and anticipated
                        in considerable detail what each would have to say, but they allowed the
                        conversation to proceed unfettered, allowing a sense of trust and common
                        purpose to unfold among those assembled. This, in turn, facilitated the
                        convening of a second meeting in Puerto Rico that was far more sensitive and
                        probably far more important, involving a frank conversation about the
                        deteriorating economies of Britain and Italy. </p>
                    <p>Now, aside from the G-7, which I’ve emphasized here as an example of American
                        leadership through essentially a willingness to defer to global
                        conversation, or at least a conversation among other powers, almost on an
                        equal basis, there’s a second example of relatively cooperative American
                        policy that I want to emphasize: the North-South dialogue. And here I want
                        to dovetail with what Kathy said before, but I might give it a slightly
                        different spin. In my view, a relatively hardnosed view coming from the
                        Nixon years gives way to a stance that puts the U.S. in a position of
                        engaging with the economic concerns of other countries. </p>
                    <p>And here I want to quote from Gerald Ford. And I think one of the differences
                        of interpretation that would probably be worth talking about is the extent
                        to which Ford’s own perspective, his own style, might have had a formative
                        influence on Kissinger rather than vice versa. And I think that’s worth
                        considering if one has invested any time in Robert Dallek’s study of
                        Kissinger and Nixon in which one sees Kissinger very much responding to the
                        leadership style of the president in question. Doesn’t that suggest that in
                        some ways Kissinger might also be learning to talk like Ford? </p>
                    <p>Here we have Ford at the front end of a meeting in May 1975 on this commodity
                        issue, on this north-south question, saying the following: “You may have to
                        give a little on words in order to achieve something necessary to solve
                        problems. I don't believe you can get practical solutions by being too
                        sticky on phraseology.” Now, that’s pretty much what Kissinger has been
                        saying, but the fact that Ford himself is willing to come out and articulate
                        this has significant implications.</p>
                    <p>I also believe that Henry Kissinger is responding not just to Ford’s style
                        but also to the absence of allied support. And once again, the fact that the
                        United States would actually hold back because they knew they didn’t have
                        anyone covering their back is quite significant. Here it’s important that,
                        for example, Kissinger realizes that the Germans are afraid. The Germans are
                        afraid to earn the enmity of the global South by taking too pronounced a
                        line against the new international economic order. So for that reason, too,
                        Kissinger appears to be adopting a more mellow line, and the fruits of that
                        mellow line are seen in a very nice document drafted by Brent Scowcroft in
                        December 1975. Essentially, Scowcroft argues to the President that
                        Kissinger’s expressions of sympathy for the poorest LDCs – the poorest – the
                        least developed countries, who had been hit hard by the impact of the oil
                        shocks, was driving a wedge between the OPEC countries and those poorest
                        LDCs. Thus, in place of the pugilant (ph) defensiveness of the Nixon years,
                        we see a more soft-spoken and ultimately wiser course. </p>
                    <p>Now, I want to not take too much more time from the rest of the panel, but
                        I’ll briefly comment, again, as speaking as a historian, we have a lot of
                        fun talking about sources, commenting on sources. I will do that very
                        quickly. One of the more useful editorial choices made by Kathy involves a
                        relative de-emphasis on reprinting diplomatic cables. There are practical
                        and substantive reasons why this choice makes sense. First of all – and if
                        anyone in the audience is not aware of this, I encourage you strongly to
                        take note of this. This is the most amazing, searchable, easily accessible
                        database you can imagine. The lion’s share of U.S. diplomatic cables from
                        1973 to ’76 are available online at the National Archives in a full-text,
                        searchable database. So there’s not much need to reprint them in large
                        numbers here, and I suspect that must have also informed your decisions on
                        some level. Okay. I made – (laughter). </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Yes and no.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> Yeah, I would be, actually, curious for
                        your thoughts of that. I mean, of course, there are certain categories of
                        cables that don’t appear to appear in that online database, particularly the
                        stuff that I think is NODIS for example. In any event, I still think that’s
                        a reason not – the structure of the volume really struck me as being very
                        different from volumes that covered, say, the 1960s, and I did notice your
                        cables. Also, as Kathy already pointed out, there are just some actors here
                        who don’t appear in – who wouldn’t be appearing in cable traffic back and
                        forth – the Treasury, the White House, the Federal Reserve. And I might
                        point out that this kind of carefully culled material tells us so much more
                        and provides such a more robust picture than, say, a randomly leaked source
                        of material – (laughter) – which simply doesn’t give insights into policy
                        making in the same way. All right.</p>
                    <p>Now, a second editorial choice involves the foregrounding of conversation
                        transcripts. These occupy a substantial portion of the book, pages and
                        pages, thanks to their great length. Aside from the White House tapes, there
                        are some other phone calls that are reproduced here. Now, these transcripts
                        are made with painstaking care. They offer a marked contrast to the usual
                        summary memoranda of conversations prepared by NSC staffers such as Brent
                        Scowcroft. And those of us who habituate presidential libraries will be
                        accustomed to NSC memos conveying the gist of the meeting. But those are not
                        verbatim comments, and I’ve often suspected that Scowcroft in particular
                        sometimes introduced a kind of gruff machismo to some of his renderings of
                        Nixon and Kissinger’s comments. </p>
                    <p>Well, the transcripts remove some of the uncertainty about the personal
                        dynamics prevailing at the White House. Readers can see the flow of a
                        conversation in remarkable detail, observing which aides were able to
                        complete their points and which were being constantly interrupted. And
                        actually, one hesitates to question the utility of such an extraordinary
                        amount of labor, as those transcripts must have involved. On some level, I’m
                        not certain that historians will universally prefer the kind of fine-grained
                        conversational renderings on offer here. They break the conversation down
                        almost to the molecular level. Zooming back outward from this degree of
                        intimacy with the pauses, stutters, and broken syntax of the White House
                        staff might be necessary, in some ways, to get a larger sense of
                        administration policy. </p>
                    <p><lb/> But in any event, I would laud the craftsmanship apparent in this
                        volume unhesitatingly. Foreign relations historians who spend time on these
                        pages will come away with a far sharper understanding of the limits of
                        American diplomacy in an age of waning economic prowess. Thanks very much.
                        (Applause.) </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> You’re next in the alphabet, Dan. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HAMILTON:</hi> Okay. Well, thank you for inviting me
                        here today, and it’s a pleasure to be here. I should say to my George Mason
                        colleagues the American Consortium in EU studies includes George Mason,
                        along with the other Washington universities, so I actually represent George
                        Mason all around the Washington metropolitan area with great pleasure. So
                        I’m happy to be here at one of our universities. </p>
                    <p>So I have a few points, as I say. I think a few of my points, not only sort
                        of looking at the history of it, but also I was asked to sort of look at it
                        with a view to sort of how things have developed since then and sort of
                        current issues. And also, since I was also in the State Department in
                        various capacities, maybe an eye to some elements that struck me in terms of
                        how decisions are made or not made and whose influence actually counts. </p>
                    <p>So one point, I think, which has been mentioned a number of times here, which
                        is interesting, is to look at this period as sort of the beginning of a
                        serious discussion about the emergence of a multi-polar world. It starts
                        really in the – just before this volume starts with breaking the dollar
                        conversion to gold, the August 1971 Nixon speech, and it reflects sort of a
                        view in the Nixon Administration, particularly Nixon and Kissinger together,
                        that this is sort of the way the world is moving. And the United States had
                        to reposition itself along a whole number of fronts to deal with this type
                        of world. </p>
                    <p>I think it’s always important to put context in here. We read the document
                        but, of course, the context is broader in which the United States found
                        itself, not only those issues but trying to wind down the war in Vietnam,
                        the Cold War still going on, the opening to China, détente with the Soviet
                        Union, linkage policies with the Soviet Union, the oil crisis. I mean, it’s
                        a broader context, obviously, in which some of this is happening besides
                        just what the documents – they sort of narrow down into a topic, but I
                        think, obviously, one has to keep the context in mind.</p>
                    <p>And you see then when the discussion of the multi-polar world starts to
                        happen that it’s not reflected in the documents. But if you look at the
                        foreign – the history of foreign relations of the United States or look at
                        State Department documents, White House documents at the time, Nixon and
                        Kissinger both released a series of documents in which they charted,
                        basically, a multi-polar world. They have, in fact, documents directly
                        addressing that. Kissinger and Nixon wanted to set forth a conceptual
                        framework for the world that was emerging at the time. And if you look,
                        there are annual documents in which the President sets forth – these are
                        White House documents – the emergence of this multi-polar world in which
                        they talk about the U.S., Japan, Europe, China, and the Soviet Union as the
                        five poles. And there’s a whole much broader debate about this, but it was
                        an effort by the Administration, particularly Kissinger, given his
                        background, to give some conceptual coherence to sort of the underpinnings
                        of U.S. foreign policy and why it was engaged in these things, the rationale
                        for the opening to China, all of this type of thing. You had to engage on
                        those poles, and the U.S. would be the hub of those various interactions. </p>
                    <p>But when you look at these documents, it becomes clear that the reality,
                        given the Cold War and tensions with China, is that it’s only three of five
                        poles that really are the ones that they’re engaging with. And even there,
                        it’s interesting to see the debates. We have a quote here from Nixon who
                        says the big five, and this is his quote. “Japan, England, France, Germany,
                        U.S.” – (laughter) – that’s it. That’s his quote. And how there’s this big
                        debate about the U.S. trying to get Canada involved in this, against the
                        French, and nobody really wanting the Italians involved, particularly
                        Schmidt, and so much for European unity. And if you project forward today to
                        debates about Germany in the permanent seat in the UN Security Council,
                        who’s the biggest opponent? Italy. (Laughter.) You see some resonance
                        here.</p>
                    <p>And I think – I do disagree, I think, on the notion that the origins of what
                        became the G-7 was a French idea. I think if you look actually deeper, one
                        has to look at the particular dynamics between Germany and France at the
                        time, that often what were actually German ideas were conveyed through the
                        French. You had a divided front line semi-sovereign country that had lost a
                        big world war and was not willing or able or in any position to sort of get
                        out in front on almost any issue. And given its importance to reconcile with
                        the French and the core of Franco-German reconciliation sort of being the
                        motive for this European integration, many German ideas were floating
                        actually through the French vehicle, if you will. And that corresponded on
                        the French side to a sense of their own grandeur and their own position in
                        the world, so it was a mutual way of doing things. But I think one has to
                        look at that dynamic and understand. </p>
                    <p>And if you look on this specific issue, you saw that Schmidt, as the finance
                        minister, was the one who had pushed particularly the notion that the
                        finance ministers had to have informal ways to communicate that got beyond
                        protocol and to really deal with the kinds of issues they were dealing with.
                        And Giscard, as his counterpart, sort of said yes, that’s – you are
                        absolutely right. And I think the related issue here is the notion that the
                        Europeans, asking themselves, how do we influence the hegemon? How do we
                        influence the big United States, the unilateral power? Well, we get in the
                        room with them. And if we could dispense with protocol and actually just get
                        in the room and talk, we will have commensurate influence with the United
                        States. </p>
                    <p>So this was a strategy not only of getting things done but actually having
                        influence over the direction of the U.S. policy in many different areas, but
                        it was led because Giscard and Schmidt together were the finance ministers
                        at the time. There was all these crises. And then, of course, there happens
                        to add that within just, I think, a week of each other they were both
                        elected to be heads of their government, their respective governments. And
                        they both carried that same notion of informal meetings that they had as
                        finance ministers now as heads of state or heads of government. And that
                        has, I think, kept projecting this notion forward. So you have the
                        Rambouillet, you have Puerto Rico, and so on. When Jimmy Carter was elected,
                        they had a meeting right afterward in this very small format.</p>
                    <p>And I do believe a lot of it was this notion if you get – you can get into a
                        room with the Americans and whisper in their ear, you’re going to have some
                        more impact than these, sort of, stolid kind of settings with protocol and
                        all that. And you see in one quote – it’s interesting – a Giscard quote in
                        the book that says – he says this. He says – when they’re talking about IMF
                        Committee of 20, which is interesting thinking about the G-20 today, his
                        quote is, “Twenty is perfectly useless except to permit a meeting of the
                        five.” (Laughter.) </p>
                    <p>And I think if you not only think of that period and what I was saying, but
                        actually project forward even to today, there is, I think – when one thinks
                        about foreign policy and how agencies of government operate, the notion that
                        you can use bigger meetings to have smaller meetings that actually get
                        something done is very still much a part of U.S. foreign policy, clearly.
                        And that sort of multilateral – formal multilateral structures, in the view
                        of many, I would think, are only useful because you can have the informal
                        meetings on the margins, or you can form other kinds of groupings, contact
                        groups for other kinds of things. They’re actually the ones that are going
                        to get something done. </p>
                    <p>And I think you see that even today, certainly with the role of the G-20, the
                        debates in the Clinton Administration about moving from the G-7 to the G-8,
                        in which you had – politically wanted to include Russia, but they had no
                        business being at a G-7 finance ministers meeting, so you created this
                        strange thing where the finance ministers of the seven met, and then you
                        invite the Russians after you were basically done. And if you look even
                        today, right now with the French presidency at the G-20, some of these same
                        issues are in place. The G-20 is fine as a chapeau, but who’s really making
                        decisions within the room? </p>
                    <p>So you see the beginnings of this and sort of the reasons for doing these
                        kinds of dynamics and this notion of informal groupings, international
                        non-organizations, starting to play perhaps more of a role than
                        international organizations in terms of how foreign policy is conducted. And
                        I – you could look at a range of areas beyond economic policy where that’s
                        true today.</p>
                    <p>A second area that really struck me is this continuing ambivalence over
                        almost – in the Nixon administration very clearly a view of how you had to
                        divide the Europeans and this question whether European integration is
                        really an American interest. And it was very striking in some of the quotes
                        that were in the book. As I said, this is a broader issue than just this
                        period. I think it extends from the beginnings of the European integration
                        movement, in fact, to today and how U.S. policy makers and, frankly, how
                        U.S. diplomats think about that issue. You have Paul Volcker at the time,
                        the under secretary in the Treasury, saying, “We have to guard against this
                        so-called European solution, one view in Europe, mainly the French view,
                        antagonistic. And the European solution is a euphemism for saying, quote,
                        ‘Let’s leave the United States out of the world and go our independent
                        course.’” And Nixon says, “Yeah.” (Laughter.) And Arthur Burns then saying,
                        “And this is the way Europe is moving.” </p>
                    <p>It’s interesting. Nixon, right at that same sort of series of documents, he
                        says, “Europe may be united 10, 15, or 20 years from now.” We think of the
                        timeline – (laughter) – maybe we’re not quite there yet. (Laughter.) And
                        Kissinger’s point, which he was very consistent on, both actually in private
                        and in public, that no European integration without full consultation with
                        the United States. And he was very clear about that, I think, and he still
                        his, actually. He still holds that view, I believe, that the Europeans could
                        not do that without the – sort of the Americans were a part of this project
                        and that you could not gang up on the U.S. He says at one point – this is a
                        quote from Kissinger, “I’m no longer so sure that European integration is
                        all that much in our interest.” And Nixon says, “Oh, I’m not so sure of it
                        at all.” And it – and that – Nixon goes on to say maybe we should start to
                        build our own bloc – U.S., Japan, Latin America, Africa, and Asia.
                        (Laughter.) And the interesting – he says – this is sort of the quote I’m
                        sure would get the media attention if – I think I’ve seen it, in fact,
                        already referred to. He says – this is Nixon, “We must not get this into the
                        bureaucracy,” meaning the State Department, frankly, “or we will create a
                        Europe that is a Frankenstein monster which could be highly detrimental to
                        our interests in the years ahead.” </p>
                    <p>And I think if you – those are quite striking quotes, very at odds with
                        public statements U.S. policy makers that made about European integration.
                        But I think it does reflect, again, a broader pattern that one sees, that
                        ever since sort of the beginnings of that movement after World War II and in
                        the 50s, there was always a sort of U.S. ambivalence about the European
                        project, much of it because of European ambivalence about what they were
                        doing themselves. The Europe of Charles de Gaulle is different than one of
                        Margaret Thatcher and different than one of Jean Monnet. So which Europe is
                        the European project, I think, has always been hard for Europeans to convey
                        to Americans. And so understandably, there’s some ambivalence on the U.S.
                        side of what this means. </p>
                    <p><lb/> But you do have – you do see a regular pattern that generic, sort of
                        rhetorical support in broad terms for European integration bringing
                        Europeans together, starts to break down when it comes down to any specific
                        issue, whether it’s agriculture or the role of the United Kingdom with the
                        European community in the ‘60s. If you move into the period, you have the
                        question of EMU, the European Monetary Union, the question of the snake and
                        the fixed terrains and what’s that for the dollar.</p>
                    <p>You go into the ’90s, you have the question of – or the ‘80s, you have the
                        question of the single market – Jacques Delors and what are they trying to
                        do here. There was a whole cottage industry in the United States about
                        Fortress Europe, about the single market, even though the single market is
                        actually opening up markets.</p>
                    <p>But you see this kind of reaction in policy and outside as well. The question
                        – what’s the euro mean for the dollar? – the Clinton Administration had to
                        grapple with that. In the end, came down and said, “It’s Europe’s decision.”
                        They didn’t try to disaggregate the Europeans on that issue. Whereas, and
                        you see the Bush administration, Bush II actually using those terms of
                        disaggregation and trying to split apart the Europeans. So I believe that’s
                        still an ambivalent policy, frankly, today. It’s the rhetorical support, but
                        in real hard, day-to-day operational issues, quite a bit of questioning
                        about what the nature of European integration is likely to mean in the
                        future.</p>
                    <p>A third area that I think got a lot of attention in the book is the role of
                        the dollar, obviously, and this relation to gold and the special drawing
                        rights, this whole debate that was going on. And here again, this is part of
                        a longer debate that actually in some ways still continues, and this is
                        particularly a Franco-American debate with Charles de Gaulle, frankly and
                        Jacques Rueff, his main monetary guy at the time, complaining about what
                        they called the exorbitant privilege of the dollar as the world’s reserve
                        currency, which allowed the United States to just print dollars and
                        everybody would take them. And as John Connolly, sort of, said to them at
                        the time, “Yeah, it’s our currency, but it’s your problem.” (Laughter.) And
                        I think the French have never forgotten that little quote.</p>
                    <p>I think it’s certain not only did it give the U.S. this exorbitant privilege
                        in their view, but also on balances inflationary, which was a horror to
                        Germans, in particular, because it allowed the U.S. to just print things as
                        it needed to deal with its growth policies. Because it was so tied to the
                        policy of this one single country undermining confidence in the type of
                        monetary system that was around, at the time the French and the Italians
                        both had these balance of payments problems and had all this gold sitting
                        around and suddenly it didn’t know how they could tap that, which led to
                        sort of the debase with U.S.</p>
                    <p>Whereas on the U.S. side, you see a very intense effort to maintain the role
                        of the dollar as the world’s reserve currency because that did give the U.S.
                        this particular privilege. And that a reluctance to ever be tied down, the
                        U.S. policy would ever be constrained, by any sorts of committee
                        arrangements or tying it to sort of fixed prices or things that would not
                        give you – the U.S., freedom of movement, and that this idea of dividing,
                        again, the Europeans was a way to maintain U.S. privilege, if you will. And
                        you still see some of that today. I think many of those debates still
                        resonate in some ways.</p>
                    <p>Today, in a different world, now we’re talking about the role of the dollar
                        versus the euro – as the only two real currencies that are around – but
                        there’s talk now of the Chinese currency becoming part of a different kind
                        of multicurrency world in the future. It’s not there yet, but there’s debate
                        about that. And again, you have France, as the presidency of the G-20 right
                        now Sarkozy coming to see Obama, to talk about the need for reform of the
                        international monetary system, again, talking about special drawing rights;
                        now, he wants them – somewhat different approach. But you do see sort of
                        this core Franco-American debate through decades about the role of the
                        dollar and what it means politically, not only economically.</p>
                    <p>The – one point, just small point, which I think is illustrative but
                        interesting is the role of the Congress and again, the Jackson-Vanik story
                        highlights this, that what you see there also resonates today perhaps. We
                        have this exchange between Kissinger and George Shultz complaining about the
                        Congress meddling in their grand schemes of U.S. foreign economic policy,
                        Kissinger saying, “I thought this was going to get better after Vietnam,”
                        and Shultz saying to him, “It’s never been worse,” the relations with
                        Congress and the Executive Branch. </p>
                    <p>And it comes down in the Jackson-Vanik amendment; it sort of crystallizes
                        this debate over the role of Congress versus the Executive Branch and
                        foreign economic policy. And I think the thing that really galled Kissinger
                        is that his strategy of détente was tied to the notion of linkage, which is
                        that you could engage the Soviets in a whole broad menu of issues where you
                        had disagreements, and they would give on some and you would give on others,
                        and you could cut across economics and politics. It was just one big basket
                        of things where everything would be sort of quid pro quo in the end. And
                        because he had sort of staked his entire view in dealing with Moscow on that
                        approach, you see it repeatedly at what he says in these citations, in the
                        documents. He’s on the book to deliver. He almost becomes the spokesman for
                        the Kremlin in some of these debates. He said, “The Soviets came through for
                        us on this and this issue, that issue, Berlin, Cuba, all these kinds of
                        things, and we have given them nothing, and we’ve really got to do
                        this.”</p>
                    <p>So his notion of foreign economic policy was he had all the instruments in
                        his hand that it had to be centralized and controlled and linkages had to be
                        plotted by one, sort of, overarching person or agency. And the notion that
                        the Congress would come and some members of Congress would have their own
                        linkages and, because of their constitutional prerogatives, start to impose
                        their own linkages completely messed up the game. And I think it’s an
                        important sort of insight into how U.S. foreign economic policy is made and
                        that the Executive Branch is limited in many ways in terms of how it can
                        really conduct that, which leads to the – I wasn’t going to add this, but
                        since it’s been mentioned, I think it’s – and I was in the policy-planning
                        staff – I did have a question about the one document that was in there by
                        Ernie Preeg and why it was in there, frankly. And Bill, it sort of said – he
                        has a document which Winston Lord, the head of the policy planning staff
                        sends to Kissinger and says, “It’s not fully cleared. This is a kind of a
                        document from a member of my staff, but I think it’s kind of interesting,
                        and you should read it.” In which, the document says basically this notion
                        is to be less interdependent – that’s what Bill said – where it’s entropy;
                        it’s not going to be this interdependence types of things, so we have to
                        plan for that.</p>
                    <p>It’s all interesting. But I think when one – either as historian or policy
                        analyst or even a policymaker, one has to think a little harder about the
                        role that a document like that might play. Bill mentioned – I don’t want to
                        pick on him, but it was just noted that he said, “As predicted by the State
                        Department” this document.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> Fair enough.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HAMILTON:</hi> A policy-planning document like that
                        isn’t the State Department. It wasn’t even clear, and it was sent on the
                        back channel to the Secretary, which I think one has to look at these in
                        terms of bureaucratic politics and other issues besides just the U.S. did
                        this – these aren’t black boxes. And especially in foreign economic policy,
                        I think there – in this particular case, there are two issues. One is what’s
                        the role of the Department of State? This is a document about – mainly about
                        the Department of State. The Department of State’s role in foreign economic
                        policy is actually quite limited. </p>
                    <p>So the question is: What else is out there to tell the full story of our
                        foreign economic policy? What you see is Henry Kissinger playing a big role
                        here, even though he professes not to know much about economics. But I
                        believe much of his roles stem from the fact that the President of the
                        United States, Richard Nixon, said – here’s a quote – “Political
                        considerations must completely override economic considerations in monetary
                        and trade talks.” </p>
                    <p>He had a president who believed that politics were preeminent and that
                        economics were to serve the politics, just as the quote here of Kissinger. I
                        think Kissinger is reflecting his boss, and I believe Kissinger’s influence
                        on Nixon was because he could do the politics of the economics, whereas some
                        of the economic types couldn’t make that work. They even recognized it. They
                        kept coming to him for advice.</p>
                    <p>So at that particular period, Kissinger had a role to play and the State
                        Department did, but that’s because of that dynamic. And I believe, in fact,
                        Kissinger’s role on this diminished quite dramatically as soon as Gerald
                        Ford became president because he didn’t necessarily even understand that
                        sort of linkage of policies that had been portrayed nor did he buy into
                        that. So one has to look at the personality and the role of a certain
                        institution. </p>
                    <p>So if I could, just on the policy planning staff, one has to look at those
                        documents with some care. My view – the relationship between the director of
                        the policy planning staff and the Secretary of State is really the
                        determinant, and there are different models. Some are sort of the
                        Secretary’s main advisor, frankly; they’re with them all the time. It’s not
                        policy planning. It’s sort of here’s what you’ve got to do, and it’s sort of
                        a trusted confidant. And there have been some policy planning directors over
                        years that have had that role. Winston Lord had part of that role with
                        Kissinger mainly on China and on the opening of China and some other areas.
                        He did not have it really in this area. And the other model of the policy
                        planning staff is to write nice papers and to be sort of a think tank in
                        which you do some deeper sort of thoughts and put them in the mix, if you
                        will. And what becomes of them is – it varies.</p>
                    <p>So I think as a member of the policy planning staff, you have sort of – you
                        have a choice. You can either be the extended foresight arm of a bureau – if
                        you’re doing economics, you’re the Bureau of Economic Affairs sees you as
                        that person, as their sort of forward thinker and work with you. Or you can
                        challenge the bureau completely – basically it’s warfare – from a separate
                        agency within the State Department who has direct access to the Secretary,
                        fighting what that particular bureau is mainly setting forth to the
                        Secretary. You can gain tremendous influence that way. You don’t win a lot
                        of friends, but that’s another role of the staff.</p>
                    <p>So I’m just illustrating this because I think one has to look at a document
                        like that and say, “What role did it really play?” It seemed to be out of
                        place, frankly, in the debate, and I don’t believe it – and it didn’t
                        reflect sort of the direction. So I’m not sure where it fits. </p>
                    <p>And so you see this structure of government where it really is such – so many
                        different agencies and the bureaucratic politics of this really does play a
                        role, which infuriates many of our foreign partners. The one story that’s
                        not in here because it came later, but I do believe it – I’ll end on this, a
                        true story – is when Arthur Burns left his job and the Reagan administration
                        came into office, he was appointed ambassador to Germany, and Helmut Schmidt
                        was still the chancellor, and of course they knew each other from all this
                        time. And Schmidt had called Burns into his office and he said, “We Germans,
                        we like to know the concept. We want to know the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Gesamtkonzept</hi> . We want to know your comprehensive concept. What
                        is with all these missiles and for the President talking about good and evil
                        and all this. Tell us the <hi rend="italic">Gesamtkonzept</hi> of American
                        foreign policy, Mr. Ambassador.” And Arthur Burns, without missing a beat,
                        he said, “Mr. Chancellor, I’d be happy to tell you this <hi rend="italic"
                            >Gesamtkonzept</hi> . Would you like the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Gesamtkonzept</hi> from this week or last week?” (Laughter.) And
                        sometimes these documents may give us a clue as to which <hi rend="italic"
                            >Gesamtkonzept</hi> we’re following. </p>
                    <p>Thank you. (Applause.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Let me just start with a congratulations
                        to Kathy. This is really an extraordinary volume. I would love, actually, to
                        use it in a classroom. I think it will give students of politics, students
                        of foreign policy, certainly students of foreign economic policy, a sense of
                        – a bit of a flavor of how decisions are actually made and how different
                        forces contend. </p>
                    <p>To pick up on Dan’s comment, of course, if we were doing the same study with
                        Secretary Shultz in the limelight, you’d get a slightly different set of
                        documents, but you’d have that same sense of contending forces inside an
                        administration or, as Dan points out, sometimes within a department
                        itself.</p>
                    <p>I did, before I get started, want to congratulate Bill Gray on sort of
                        sticking with the theme of today by complimenting the paper volume on being
                        a gold standard. I thought that put things together very nicely – (laughter)
                        – and also putting WikiLeaks in perspective of a random release. So if we
                        have a well-honed release, we should refer to them as KathyLeaks going
                        forward. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> I’d really appreciate it if you didn’t.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Let me excise that from my remarks.
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PARTICIPANT:</hi> It’s already on the net, right?
                        (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Well, what I’d like to do is just very
                        briefly then talk about sort of the context, talk about what I think are
                        some of the parallels with today’s policies – Dan has already opened that
                        door very concretely – and then to just say a bit what was going on in the
                        Congress at this time. As Ed alluded, I misspent much of my youth working on
                        Capitol Hill, including this part of the period, and parenthetically I would
                        say I’m looking forward to the Japan volume from this era, that for those us
                        that were working on foreign economic policy on the Hill, we would start
                        doing that one month, and the next month you were working on U.S.-Japan
                        economic relations, which was a challenge not only to specific industries
                        and so forth, but it was a challenge to the way we thought because Japan was
                        showing a great deal of success by violating all the rules of thumb that I
                        came out of graduate school with – they were protectionist, they were
                        interventionist, they were the socialism that worked kind of thing. So it
                        was an important period to look at how we were reacting inside the
                        Administration and on the Hill.</p>
                    <p>In terms of the context, it was – it is similar in some ways, as Kathy
                        suggested opening up. But at the same times, it was quite different. The
                        Cold War was still very much an important reality. We were running current
                        account deficits, and trade deficits were a shock to everybody. They seem
                        miniscule by today’s standards. While there was an eroding U.S. influence,
                        there was no question the U.S. was the leading economy and was likely to
                        remain so for some time. It was a period where, to some extent, paralleled
                        by today, where foreign policy really dominated economic decision making. </p>
                    <p>The quote that Bill Gray picked out from Henry Kissinger saying, “Oh, we can
                        use our economies to really shape a political agreement,” that that was
                        really the thinking. And I think to some extent it’s still very much
                        embraced by today’s foreign policy elite.</p>
                    <p>We had the first experienced oil shock in 1973, something that is now
                        evermore a concern with recent occurrence in the Middle East. And you saw
                        here the same kind of tension that you see today of, you might say,
                        Wilsonian (inaudible) coupled with Cold War rivalry, and today’s sense it
                        would be, again, sort of the realistic pursuit of important national
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>I think some of the parallels that you see in a very different context is
                        that surplus countries, as they were 20 – during this period are very
                        reluctant to adjust. In this case, it was Japan and Germany were the major
                        surplus countries. They were again the major surplus countries in 1985 when
                        you had the Plaza Accord. They are still surplus companies now joined by a
                        cluster of Asian countries, in particular, of course, the People’s Republic
                        of China.</p>
                    <p>I was struck by the way the trade initiative was described – that is what
                        became the Trade Act of 1974, which originally was to have formed the basis
                        for the Nixon round of trade negotiations – (laughter) – which, of course,
                        didn’t work out quite that way. And I agreed with Kathy’s characterization
                        that, in fact, it took us down several paths that are very much with us
                        today, particularly going after non-tariff barriers and broader kinds of
                        agreements, and that the Tokyo round, as it became, was quite significant in
                        setting the agenda for today’s trade negotiations.</p>
                    <p>But what surprised me is there was only – maybe there was a list of seven or
                        eight priorities, and only one made reference to the Burke-Hartke bill,
                        which was a major force on Capitol Hill at that time. It would have imposed
                        comprehensive trade quotas on all competitive imports. But the piece the
                        really generated response were major changes in the taxation of
                        foreign-sourced income that then and now, if you were a multinational
                        company and you earned money overseas, basically you didn’t have to pay
                        taxes on that money until it was repatriated. And when you did repatriate
                        it, you would be able to take a full credit against any U.S. taxes for taxes
                        that you had paid overseas. </p>
                    <p>Burke-Hartke wanted to make two changes: First of all, no deferrals. That’s
                        still an active debate. So if you make something in – make money in France
                        or Germany or Japan, you had to pay taxes on it that year. And then they
                        were going to treat taxes that you paid elsewhere the way state taxes were
                        treated; that is, as a deduction not a credit. So this really mobilized the
                        multinational community. It created a specific organization, the Emergency
                        Committee on American Trade. It is still with us today. The emergency
                        apparently has persisted. (Laughter.) And according to students of interest
                        groups, it triggered the formation of a large number of Washington offices
                        by multinational companies, larger industrial companies that often viewed
                        Washington as kind of an undesirable foreign post. </p>
                    <p>In terms of the new international economic order, from my perspective,
                        Kissinger’s performance when he finally went to the seventh special session
                        of the General Assembly was really a tour de force. He had thought through,
                        I think, a line that he could walk. It’s fascinating to see the interplay of
                        – you may have been involved in this, Dan – but the interplay of forces
                        inside the Administration and how to mix rhetoric and real policy and so
                        forth.</p>
                    <p>But one of the things he was able to do that I’ve – that was – that I
                        interpreted as being most disarming is that he offered to share a wide range
                        of U.S. technologies with the developing countries. Today, of course, we are
                        ever more aware of how vulnerable those technologies are to being borrowed
                        without payment, let’s say; that it is an active source of virtually every
                        manufacturing company who has proprietary process and product technology to
                        try to protect those as thoroughly as possible. So again, I think this
                        reflected both the strength in the U.S. at that time and the primacy of
                        foreign policy and foreign policy considerations.</p>
                    <p>Well now, jumping ahead, of course, there’s no Cold War. We had a duopoly,
                        really, of nuclear weapons, for all practical purposes. That is no longer
                        the case, and we may see further erosion of that monopoly going forward. </p>
                    <p>Current accounts were miniscule at that point. Before the financial crisis,
                        we actually had a current account that was slightly over 6 percent of GDP.
                        We were reaching that tipping point in terms of foreign debt that, had we
                        not been the reserve currency, might have led to a currency crisis. We are
                        still the largest economy, and I think even at purchasing power parity where
                        China is close, but probably not yet larger. And of course, in terms of per
                        capita income, they would still lag far behind. </p>
                    <p>We’re a major exporter still, not the largest anymore. And we have become –
                        we have moved from a position of being the largest world creditor to, by an
                        enormous margin, being the world’s largest debtor, a position which has
                        economic implications. We don’t just borrow in the abstract. We borrow in
                        the concrete, really, in terms of products. It’s had an effect on the
                        industrial base, which could impact our innovative capacity. But it also has
                        real implications for foreign policy. </p>
                    <p>One of the documents I found interesting was the discussion of, well, if
                        oil’s a problem, are we worried about other metals? Are we dependent on
                        other metals? And by and large, the decision was no, we’re not. It’s the
                        kind of document that may still be done on an annual basis. I don’t know. It
                        certainly should be. But we have moved to a situation in which there’s a
                        great deal of interdependence and dependence in terms of raw materials. The
                        latest that’s made headlines are the so-called rare earths that are critical
                        for both – for all kinds of electronics, extending into modern windmills. </p>
                    <p>And we’ve also changed the whole pattern of international trade in that for –
                        really, for a couple decades we’ve gone to a world in which we trade parts
                        rather than products. Open up a PC and it’s kind of an electronic United
                        Nations, and that makes the maneuverability in terms of the kind of things
                        that President Nixon thought about; let’s have across-the-board trade
                        sanctions and so forth, six months and so forth is, makes it much, much,
                        much more complicated now. </p>
                    <p>Well, you can see how the parallels that Kathy alluded to really jump out at
                        you, that we are wrestling again with serious imbalances. Some of the same
                        people are at the table. It was an historic decision by President George W.
                        Bush to recognize that you couldn’t rely on the G-7, G-8 anymore, that you
                        had to go to the G-20. I think Dan is also right that there’s some real
                        conversations within the members of the G-20 that are not quite as important
                        as some of the others, and that it is a capacity for all kinds of serious
                        negotiations. </p>
                    <p>But it also is a situation in which different countries are really taking
                        much more of a leadership role. Brazil is an interesting case. If you go
                        back to the ’73 to ’76 period, they had a military government. It was a
                        developmental state, or aspired to be. But Brazilians themselves were still
                        quick to tell the old story about Brazil being the future – country of the
                        future and always will be. And all of a sudden, Brazil is quite a force in
                        commodities. It’s a force in foreign policy in the sense of doing something
                        that would have probably been unimaginable in the ’70 to ’76 period, going
                        together with Brazil and Turkey approaching Iran and trying to do something
                        that was really outside the interests of the United States. </p>
                    <p>As I said, the surplus countries are still very reluctant to value. It may be
                        that the shock that President Nixon called by suddenly going off the Bretton
                        Woods gold/dollar standard, imposing export controls – big shock to the soy
                        consumers in Japan, big boost for the Brazilian soybean industry, as it
                        turns out. Very – again, this government is wrestling, I think, with how do
                        we really deal with this. There’s lots of rhetoric, there’s lots of side
                        meetings, there’s occasionally a WTO case. People are thinking about, well,
                        could you do that more fully without the whole exchange rate question. </p>
                    <p>Some people argue for counter-subsidies. Warren Buffet has a proposal that I
                        first heard actually developed by Senator Russell Long, that Warren Buffet’s
                        idea is to have an auction, basically, that you have import permits and you
                        auction them off. Senator Long once asked this question of George Shultz,
                        much to George Shultz’s surprise, and he simply said that, well, he should
                        issue a ticket to everyone that buys something from us and then they can
                        present that ticket when they send it back. And it was the one question that
                        George Shultz didn’t handle all that well.</p>
                    <p>So, of course, it’s as it was in the earlier case. There’s a proper emphasis
                        on the doctor healing thyself; that is, we need to do something here with
                        regard to our own investment policy, our own economic strategy, our own
                        fiscal health and so forth. And it may be that all that is coming.</p>
                    <p>And of course, the commodities question and our approach to development is
                        dramatically different. Again, the context is different. We still do a –
                        spend a lot of time thinking about coordinated foreign assistance. The
                        recently released QDDR does quite a good job of thinking about how that
                        would be done in the field and in Washington. </p>
                    <p>At the same time, we’re in a world where foreign remittances are some
                        multiple of foreign assistance. Foreign direct investment is much more
                        important. We’ve gone from a situation where we thought about how to
                        stabilize global markets so that there were commodity agreements and so
                        forth, something the U.S. was not at all enthusiastic about but was part of
                        the neo-proposals. Now, we’re in a situation where there’s something of a
                        global competition for commodities. Still concern about the less – the least
                        developed countries as they engage in world markets for them to develop not
                        agreements but more of an internal resiliency so that they can respond to
                        shifts in global markets.</p>
                    <p>Well, let me just say one or two words about what was happening on Capitol
                        Hill at that time and why they started to impinge on Secretary Kissinger’s
                        view that, putting the Constitution aside, foreign economic policy should
                        also be the purview of the president and his key advisor (laughter), that
                        you were already beginning the era or really past the era where you would
                        hear the occasional senator or member of Congress pound on the table and
                        say, “Where’s the American desk down there at the State Department?” And in
                        part, they were responding to shifting realities inside the U.S. economy.
                        They tend to – Congress tends to be the economic court of last resort. </p>
                    <p>You already saw the AFL-CIO lead the free trade coalition in the course of
                        the 1960s. You saw the ambitions of members of Congress begin to impede on
                        what had been pretty much a consensus on trade policy. Wilbur Mills, who was
                        then the chair of the Ways and Means Committee and was often referred to as
                        Wilbur Mills, the third most powerful man in Washington, comma, decided that
                        he wanted to run for president. And that affected a trade bill in a way that
                        tailored itself to the economic interests of New Hampshire in general, and
                        Manchester’s mills and shoe industry in particular. </p>
                    <p>So you saw this erosion of support, and it reflected, of course, really, the
                        recovery of Japan and Europe in terms of their returning to being the
                        industrial powerhouses, or beginning to return to that level that they had
                        been prior to World War II. It was – we were in such an anomalous position
                        with, many would say, half-world GDP and maybe 80 percent of hard currency
                        reserves, and of course, that had long since eroded.</p>
                    <p>And in fact, – well, the focus – Kathy’s focus on the trade bill of 1974 had
                        to do principally with the Jackson-Vanik amendment. In fact, I think the
                        decision to go off the gold standard and eventually go to floating exchange
                        rates, where you were directly responding to congressional concern about the
                        trade deficit – again, in many ways, originating with Russell Long, chair of
                        the Finance Committee – that that really eroded some of the support for
                        measures like the Burke-Hartke bill or other more protectionist measures,
                        and that what – that same pressure, however, showed up in the changes of the
                        – what she referred to as the fair trade, the anti-dumping and
                        countervailing duty elements and to some extent, and trade adjustment
                        assistance.</p>
                    <p>So I think the – going forward, you’re going to see the Congress ever more
                        engaged in foreign economic policy because that’s a reality of the pressures
                        they feel in their home districts. However, the foreign – the political
                        economy of trade has continued to change. Most of the companies that were
                        strongly concerned about Japan in the 1980s are now seriously invested in
                        China or elsewhere around the world. They are really, in a sense, a force
                        for global integration, both in terms of the patterns of their investment
                        and trade, but also in their influence here in the United States. </p>
                    <p>Well, let me stop there and thank you again for inviting me. It’s been – it
                        was a pleasure going through that document. (Applause.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> I don’t want to let our panel off the
                        hook yet. What I’d like to do is to open up to the questions from the floor,
                        to open up the discussion more broadly. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Some of the research from the Vietnam era
                        has been very interested in the lessons of the past that Vietnam War-era
                        decision makers were influenced by. I’m wondering what your thoughts are
                        about how people of this era – what sort of lessons from the past they were
                        drawing, how they were influenced, if they were influenced by history, the
                        depression and those issues.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> Well, I would jump in. I would say that in
                        terms of the post-World War II structure before you get to Vietnam, that was
                        very much influenced by the lessons people felt they learned from the
                        failures of the inter-war period, whether it was the GATT, International
                        Monetary Fund, so we weren’t going to have competitive devaluations, the
                        World Bank. They learned a lesson that Keynes wrote about – we’re not going
                        to impose debilitating sanctions; instead, we’re going to help
                        reconstruction.</p>
                    <p>In terms of Vietnam, it’s really not so much the economic side, but you hear
                        people were still very influenced by the idea of Munich. And it was a wave
                        of concern also in the United States about the growing influence of
                        communism. It’s hard to look back for young people today and realize that,
                        in fact, that was viewed as a threatening alternative system and had
                        considerable appeal in much of the world. One of the papers in this
                        document, in fact, alludes to the, quote/unquote, “Leninist model,” which
                        helped justify presidents, et cetera in developing countries keeping the
                        reins of power close to their side. </p>
                    <p>I think there may have been for some people a sense that they missed World
                        War II and that Vietnam was their ability to stand for a similar kind of
                        important battle. But that’s – I’m not a scholar on that period at all.
                        That’s just kind of my intuition from random readings, as William Gray would
                        say.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> I think that my take on these policy
                        makers is that they’ve learned the lessons of the past. The past lessons of
                        the past continue to be the lessons of the past or the present, if that
                        makes any sense at all. They’re still working off the 1930s: protectionism
                        is bad, fixed exchange rates are good. I mean, they are still working on the
                        same set of precepts that motivated policy makers in the 1940s when they put
                        the economy back together after World War II in the first place.</p>
                    <p>One irony of this period that I always liked in terms of forgetting the past
                        was – as Dave knows, my dissertation was actually on the reconstruction of
                        the international economy after World War II in the 1940s when, in the
                        negotiations setting up the International Monetary Fund, there was a big
                        debate between the British and the Americans over the responsibility of
                        creditor nations in the global economy. So if you’re a country that sells a
                        whole lot of stuff and doesn’t buy a lot of stuff, what responsibilities do
                        you have to sort of put the international economy back into whack? I mean,
                        the idea is that surplus countries should buy more stuff from abroad to sort
                        of put – restore equilibrium to the global economy. And the Treasury
                        Department and Harry Dexter White were like, no, surplus countries should
                        have no responsibilities whatsoever. This is the 1940s, because, of course,
                        we were a massive surplus country. </p>
                    <p>Oh, come the 1970s, and America is, like, surplus countries should adjust,
                        surplus countries are bad, because we’re a huge deficit country. And we – in
                        30 years, we’ve completely forgotten our own past, basically, and our own
                        past arguments, obviously because we have – our position has completely
                        flipped. </p>
                    <p>And I find these things funny. (Laughter.) So that was what amused me about
                        these documents, actually – our blindness to the past, actually, and sort of
                        the arguments that we’ve made in the past. Ideological – ideology is clearly
                        very fungible, is one lesson I take. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HAMILTON:</hi> Just on the one – there was a reference
                        earlier about Nixon always worried about the leftists and so on. And that, I
                        think, is somewhat of a historical issue, and one has to remember the Cold
                        War context in which he’s thinking that. So it’s not just a conservative
                        U.S. politician worried about the other side, but in the context of the Cold
                        War, the lesson of the earlier period was the real threat to Western
                        democracy starting with the end of World War II. </p>
                    <p>And the reason why there was a Marshall Plan and Truman Doctrine and all that
                        was because of the concern that the Left would win, the communists would win
                        in Italy and start in on Greece and so on, and that that was the – France,
                        and that was the real threat. And so this association with that as being the
                        real threat, as sort of the front guard of what the Soviets were trying to
                        do, I think, played a huge role in how certainly Nixon, but I think others,
                        thought about the role of the Left. Euro-communism, this phenomenon in the
                        late ’70s starting was a huge issue. Kissinger was very vocal on that.</p>
                    <p>But my reaction to your point in looking at these documents is that policy
                        makers and also policy makers from different countries have different
                        lessons from the past. They each come with their own lessons, and those
                        aren’t always the same. And so you see some of the conflicts because they’re
                        all bringing their own baggage, if you will. I think what Kathy just said
                        about the U.S. is right, and I think there’s sort of this – also this mantra
                        that if only the U.S. will be the leader, everything will be okay because we
                        are somehow more virtuous, or we are the – providing the public goods to the
                        system, if you will. And it’s reflected in a number of quotes in there, that
                        we’re the one putting forward everything for everybody else and that these
                        institutions are the way we do that, and that leadership, that term, is the
                        lesson of the past, that U.S. failure to exert leadership and abdicate,
                        frankly, in the inter-war period and so on, was the reason the world got
                        into the mess it was in, and that only the U.S. can exert that leadership.
                        You still see that today. I mean, that is a term that – everyone refers to
                        that. That’s the answer to the U.S. role in the world is to use that – evoke
                        that term. What it means, we can debate.</p>
                    <p>But I think if you look at the other players, though, just to – I mean, just
                        briefly, the French lesson of the past was don’t get dependent on these
                        other crazy countries. Let’s have our own nuclear deterrent. Let’s not rely
                        on the U.S. dollar as the reserve currency. Let’s not start to get involved
                        in this. Let’s have a notion of France. The Gaullist view of France was as
                        an independent sort of force in the world. The German lessons of the past,
                        there are quite a few. </p>
                    <p>But you see it – back to my point – about the way the Germans were acting in
                        this period was never get out in front, never go it alone, don’t be
                        singularized, use your dependence with – through others so that you can –
                        your influence comes mainly because how you can convince others to do the
                        things you want that you need them to do. And that’s a very German style of
                        leadership through that whole period. In fact, there’s still a lot of it
                        today. That’s a very different way.</p>
                    <p>And the British, frankly, not quite, in my view, understanding what the past
                        was telling them, having lost an empire but having failed to choose
                        essentially between a diminishing commonwealth as a frame of their
                        reference, the European communities, which they never really – they still
                        don’t quite know if they’re – that’s really what they are, or the special
                        tie to the United States. So where are they? And I think that’s – that was
                        always the British debate through this entire period, is either failure to
                        choose or maybe trying to balance those choices. And you get them all in a
                        room together, then you see these sort of historic reflexes come about.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> If I could follow up on that – Bill, go
                        ahead.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> I had a very slight refinement on this.
                        We’ve heard a lot of helpful response already to this question. I’m sure
                        there’s many more issues you want to ask about. But it occurs to me that one
                        further way of looking at the 1930s, which I agree is definitely on
                        everyone’s mind – Helmut Schmidt is constantly talking about the 1930s. He
                        seems to think that nobody else remembers what the problems were in that
                        period.</p>
                    <p>But one thing I think that’s kind of interesting about the phrase that’s
                        often used, a warning against beggar thy neighbor policies, is this fear
                        that people – that countries will take decisions that are in their own
                        narrow, immediate interest and that that, in turn, will set off a cascading
                        result with ultimately negative consequences for everyone. But I think the
                        reason that’s so frightening for people is this implies the idea that there
                        might be some actions which countries might find it expedient to take in the
                        short run. </p>
                    <p>So in other words – you mentioned public goods. I think that in some ways,
                        the Germans feel that they are having to admonish everyone to take the sort
                        of morally correct stance, and at cross-purposes perhaps with their economic
                        interests. And the Germans themselves feel that they’re taking positions
                        which are not necessarily in their own immediate interest but are good for
                        the system. That includes a willingness to let their currency revalue many
                        times against the others.</p>
                    <p>So I guess I would say that, in some ways, this sense of – this sense that
                        the past predicts that people will not cooperate leads to an almost intense
                        desire to make sure that everyone is persuaded to be better than their own
                        worst instincts.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> I wanted to follow up on this discussion
                        because, as you’re noting, there is a tendency to try to learn lessons from
                        the past and our thinking is shaped by the baggage that we bring to this
                        that happens during our own formative under – period of understanding. And
                        you’re pointing back to a period – I understand in the 1970s, you’re
                        pointing back to a period over 35 years earlier. Well, we’re now about 35
                        years later, and I’m wondering what lessons American decision makers have
                        learned from this period. Today’s decision makers are folks who were in a
                        formative role or playing a junior role in the period in the 1970s, and now
                        they’re wrestling with these questions of foreign and economic policy.</p>
                    <p>What baggage, what lessons are they carrying with them from this ’73 to ’76
                        period? And I suppose I’m wondering not simply about American decision
                        makers, but also European decision makers, since they were key partners for
                        America.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HUGHES:</hi> I would say that maybe not today, but in
                        1985 Secretary Baker’s decision, looking at the politics of the situation,
                        concerned about a possible congressional reaction to a growing trade
                        deficit, he pulled together the G-5 again, leaving Italy and Canada to the
                        side, said, “I don't know what’s going to happen, but we better get serious
                        about it.” And in this case, both Germany and Japan, being the big surplus
                        countries, agreed to stimulate their domestic economies.</p>
                    <p>I think that example, coupled with Nixon’s shock, has influenced the Obama
                        Administration to seek a result like the Plaza Accord, where there’s an
                        agreement rather than a shock that leads to a better rebalancing of the
                        current accounts. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> I’ll speak in favor of – I’ll return to
                        the G-7, the G-20 thing and say that perhaps one of the lessons of this
                        period is that – Dan is absolutely right that the G-7 is based upon the
                        Library Group model that was initiated by Schmidt and Giscard when they were
                        finance ministers, and of course, George Shultz, who played a key role in
                        the coming of the G-6 and actually is the unofficial envoy of the United
                        States Government to those governments as they created the G-6, also was
                        part of the Library Group.</p>
                    <p>And so, I mean, they – but even beyond that, it was – you sort of see hints
                        in the documents of policy makers sort of thrashing around for a new place
                        in which to have discussions about what was going on. The IMF wasn’t cutting
                        it. The GATT wasn’t an organization. I mean, there’s no WTO, so the GATT
                        isn’t even really an organization. It was kind of a pseudo organization.
                        There’s just nowhere where – to get together, for the most important
                        industrialized nations to get together to coordinate policy that cuts across
                        also policy lines, where you can discuss not just exchange rates but also
                        trade policy and North-South policy. And that’s what the G-7 functions as,
                        sort of an economic directorate, essentially, I think is how you envision
                        it.</p>
                    <p>And the – clearly, that’s one of the lessons that was learned well, that this
                        sort of – that the global economy is too all mixed up together in a bucket
                        to sort of hide it off into separate institutions, and that you need a forum
                        where the ministers can get together and discuss these cross-cutting issues.
                        So I think that that’s one lesson to draw from this period, that these sort
                        of economic directorates, something they didn’t envision – well, they kind
                        of envisioned in the 1940s but they couldn’t get it through – that this sort
                        of directorate – again, a horrible word and they’d probably protest against
                        it, but works.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. HAMILTON:</hi> I would just say that on the multi-polar
                        world, I mean, we did – I mean, you did see – as I said, I think the
                        beginnings of that concept – in fact, Kissinger really tried to even make it
                        a conceptual approach, has developed, always, though, with the idea that the
                        U.S. somehow was the pull above the others or the hub, as I tried to say,
                        that it’s the one orchestrating and having the relationship with the others.
                        And I do believe there’s still very much of that view in the United States
                        today.</p>
                    <p>And I think Kathy’s point is right. If you think about diplomacy, I think
                        often the analysis I see is focused on formal multilateral institutions. And
                        while they play a certain role, you have to get deeper into how decision
                        makers work, and it’s usually smaller groupings case by case or informal or
                        shifting, depending on the issues or the constellation of players you have
                        to have in the room, rather than the formal mechanisms that we’ve all put
                        together. </p>
                    <p>And I think an analysis that goes deeper and looks at those – what I call the
                        international non-organizations, it’s really networks. The network diplomacy
                        is really something. You see the beginnings of that here, and that has taken
                        off in the last few decades. There are all sorts of networks that are
                        happening not only among diplomats, but among different agencies of
                        government who are connecting with their counterparts, talking to them every
                        day more than they’re talking to their own domestic counterparts. You think
                        about how the Treasury interacts today. They don’t want the State Department
                        anywhere near them when they’re actually having these discussions. And so
                        it’s sort of functional networks that have exploded in terms of how not only
                        economic policy is conducted, but I think most diplomacy these days, and I
                        think that’s it. </p>
                    <p>My last point would be on the thing that’s changed, I think, is this
                        directorate – is that again, you saw, despite this notion of a multi-polar
                        world, China and the Soviet Union weren’t in it. And the three that were
                        left – Japan, Europe, the United States – they did think that was the
                        directorate. And I think what has certainly changed today is while that core
                        is still indispensible for almost any global activity that’s going to get
                        anything done, it’s insufficient today. And I think that’s a major change.
                        It’s – I argue it’s still indispensible. Many would dismiss even that
                        argument. But it’s no longer sufficient. </p>
                    <p>And so the question of why the informal networks become more important then
                        is that then you’ve got to get some other people in the room, depending on
                        what the issues are. And if you’re locked into these formal mechanisms,
                        which carry legitimacy in many areas but aren’t effective, that’s the
                        dilemma I think daily operational diplomacy has. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> I think I’m proving that as a historian,
                        it takes me longer to mull over these things and come up something in
                        response. But I think that there is something we haven’t touched on so far
                        about this issue of the lessons of the ’70s.</p>
                    <p>First of all, I think in a general sense, there’s less panic in response to
                        enormous economic disturbances. I think that the contrast between 1973-74
                        and 2008 is really striking. I think that there’s a lot more confidence in
                        some ways in the ability of global capital, is my guess, to use a really
                        vague term.</p>
                    <p>I think in maybe a slightly more specific term, the U.S. has learned to live
                        with floating exchange rates. And these are – this is an example of a
                        specific issue which really worried a lot of people in the 1970s. Would we
                        know how – would corporations know how to adjust – won’t this be kind of a
                        just jumbled, distorted world?</p>
                    <p>I’m not sure that Europeans learned to live with it as comfortably, and I
                        think in some ways the efforts to create the euro are an expression of a
                        lack of trust in an economic environment that’s not rooted in some way. I
                        think that the Germans really want as stable an economic area as possible.
                        They think they achieved it with the euro and then now they’re really
                        panicking because it turns out that the euro has brought with it its own set
                        of risks for the German taxpayers, in any event.</p>
                    <p>So I would say that it’s interesting to ask what the 1970s have brought us. I
                        often feel that a lot of concerns about commodities, about global financial
                        order, really appear quite – make the 1970s appear quite relevant. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Bob in front, and then we’ll work our way
                        back to you.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Just a quick observation/question about the
                        contrast between this period and the more recent global economic crisis.
                        When we talk about a global capitalist system today, it really is a unitary
                        system. In the ’70s, you really did have an alternative, a state socialist
                        system, and you did have a Cold War that nobody’s really talked about
                        explicitly. I wonder the extent to which the presence of a common enemy,
                        which was widely viewed as an enemy, whether in Japan, Europe, or the U.S.,
                        facilitated multilateral cooperation in a way that in the post-Cold War era
                        is not quite so easy. There isn’t really a common economic or strategic
                        enemy that the G-7 countries would focus on three and a half decades later. </p>
                    <p>Do you think that’s significant? Really, no one has specifically used the
                        term “Cold War,” I think, thus far. And of course, this is right in the
                        middle of the Cold War. How does that affect the story? Or is that just
                        something in the distant background, that if you take it out of the story
                        would not have really changed the decisions?</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PROF. GRAY:</hi> I’ll jump in on that real quick. One
                        example that comes to mind is Italy in 1976. And we haven’t really discussed
                        very much the Puerto Rico summit of 1976. But this is – it’s seen in the
                        volume here as emerging from concerns expressed by Alan Greenspan,
                        surprisingly. And Greenspan convinces others in the Ford administration that
                        Italy is sinking quickly, and the reason that Italy is a problem is because
                        of the communists. </p>
                    <p>So I think that in that sense, the Cold War threat is not a military threat,
                        but rather a threat that Western societies and their substance might be
                        undermined by the seizure of power of unscrupulous communist parties. Can
                        they be trusted? Now we know that Euro-communism actually was working at
                        some distance to the communist party of the Soviet Union. But the concern
                        was very real in both the Ford administration and also Helmut Schmidt’s
                        people were also very concerned about Italian development.</p>
                    <p>So I definitely think that this facilitated the emergence of a second
                        economic summit coming just seven months after the first one, and that in
                        turn helped to solidify the overall concept of getting together to discuss
                        issues that are both external to the G-7 but also internal to the G-7.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Actually, what I wanted to raise was – I
                        don’t claim, as Kathy would know, to know all that much about international
                        economic policy. But I found her presentation earlier very interesting and
                        the presentations here as well. And I think some questions were raised in
                        some of these presentations, and I’d like to give Kathy an opportunity to
                        respond to them if she would like to.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> Nah. (Laughter.) Well, there weren’t a
                        lot of presentations. (Laughter.)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">PARTICIPANT:</hi> Well, give us a few salient points.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> A few salient points. Well, I responded
                        to Dan’s points about the creation of the G-7 being not exclusively – that
                        the French sort of provided cover, as it were, for the Germans, and I think
                        it’s a point that’s well taken. And again, I do think that one can go deeper
                        into it too. And I feel that there’s a lovely quote from Arthur Burns early
                        on in which he talks about the need to get together with the major economies
                        and discuss all these issues together. And actually, he’s suggesting when we
                        discuss political issues, if memory serves, as well, sort of do some
                        tradeoffs, do linkage with our allies, essentially.</p>
                    <p>So – and the Year of Europe is also, in a way, a weird way, kind of a way to
                        get the dialogue going with the Europeans again. And in the Year of Europe
                        initiative too, Henry Kissinger’s sort of casting around for another way to
                        sort of get to the major players in the global economy and the world and the
                        Western alliance together. So, Dan, your point is well taken on that.</p>
                    <p>What other responses did I have? Actually, Dan’s point about the Ernie Preeg
                        paper from December 1973 from the policy planning staff – so this is a paper
                        that clearly doesn’t go very far. We know that Kissinger saw it. We know
                        that he thinks it was interesting, and he asked Winston Lord to come by and
                        see him. But you’re right; it doesn’t – it’s a bit of an outlier with
                        respect to the rest of the volume. And it’s – and Dan is right to caution us
                        to remember not to – to sort of – to be careful about saying the Department
                        of State believes this and the National Security Council believes that,
                        because it’s not a lockbox. </p>
                    <p>And I guess, in a way, that’s kind of why I included it, because just to say
                        that the Department of State isn’t necessarily of one mind on these things,
                        and I was – when I learned how to do foreign relations volumes, I was always
                        cautioned by the former (inaudible) to make sure that I followed the policy
                        and not down too many blind paths of policies that didn’t go anywhere. But
                        sometimes, I think it’s constructive to sort of see other opinions sort of
                        cropping up in bureaucracy even though, of course, they ultimately don’t
                        influence policy.</p>
                    <p>Will asked about the cables, Department of State cables. I wish I were as
                        good a person as you think I am, Will, in that – (laughter) – I was really
                        worried about sort of the needs of researchers and I just thought, well, if
                        you can get it off of the NARA website – I’m just really not that good a
                        person. I didn’t include a lot of State Department cables because I didn’t
                        think they had any influence on policy, to be quite frank with you. And when
                        I approached this volume, I really set out to – I really – it’s not that I
                        thought that the Department of State didn’t have influence in – obviously,
                        in foreign and economic policy, but I didn’t think the posts really had a
                        whole lot that I thought needed to be said.</p>
                    <p>And I tried to approach this volume in a way that I think is kind of
                        different from my predecessors. I didn’t just – it had the word “economic”
                        in it. I didn’t just sort of toss it into the volume. I tried to sort of
                        focus more narrowly. And I tried to get away from – I think some of the
                        previous volumes had a lot those economic reportage (ph), like, “The German
                        economy is great,” “The German economy is bad.” Like, I just didn’t really
                        see sort of how that played into the policymaking process.</p>
                    <p>So there’s awesome stuff in the cables and it’s great supplementary stuff.
                        But I found that oftentimes the posts aren’t being pulled into the
                        policymaking process, that it’s really – it’s very, very centered in the
                        White House, even when part of that White House moves over to the Department
                        of State. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Actually, I’m going to call us to a halt
                        for right now, just to give us a few minutes for coffee before we reconvene.
                        But before we do, I wanted to say thank you to Kathy and to Dan and to Kent
                        and to Will for a fascinating set of presentations and discussion. Thank
                        you. (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="subchapter" xml:id="hormats">
                    <head>Keynote Address by Under Secretary Robert Hormats</head>
                    <p>George Mason University School of Public Policy, Arlington, Virginia <lb/>
                        March 7, 2011</p>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item><list>
                                <head>MODERATOR</head>
                                <item>Ed Rhodes, Dean, George Mason School of Public Policy</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                                <item> Dr. Robert Hormats, Under Secretary of State for Economic,
                                    Energy, and Agricultural Affairs</item>
                                <item>Dr. Kathleen Rasmussen, Division Chief, Asia &amp; General,
                                    Office of the Historian</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>
                        <ref
                            target="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.history.state.gov/conferences/2011-foreign-economic-policy/FEP_Under_Secretary_Hormats_Keynote.mp3"
                            >Download Audio</ref> (27.7 MB MP3)</p>
                    <p rend="italic">Note: This transcript and linked audio recording contain
                        comments made during a roundtable discussion of the “Foreign Economic
                        Policy, 1973-1976” volume of the <title>Foreign Relations of the United
                            States</title> (FRUS) series. The comments of Robert Hormats and
                        Kathleen Rasmussen reflect their individual points of view and do not
                        necessarily reflect the views of the Department of State or the United
                        States Government.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">DEAN RHODES:</hi> Okay, if we can reconvene. We have two
                        highlights left for us. The most important highlight, of course, is Dr.
                        Hormats, who has agreed to give the keynote address. But following that,
                        you’ll all have earned some wine and cheese and other goodies next door, so
                        there is a reception to follow, and we hope everyone will stick around.</p>
                    <p>It gives me enormous pleasure to – pressure as well – pleasure to introduce
                        Dr. Hormats. As all of you know, Dr. Hormats is Under Secretary of State for
                        Economic, Energy, and Agricultural Affairs. He was appointed in 2009. Prior
                        to this appointment, he has, of course, had a most impressive string of
                        appointments in the public sector and important service in the private
                        sector as well. He was vice chairman of Goldman Sachs, International and
                        before that, of course, he served as Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Economic and Business Affairs and Ambassador and Deputy USTR from – that was
                        back in the late ‘70s and early ‘80s – Senior Deputy Assistant Secretary for
                        Economic and Business Affairs, Senior Staff Member for International
                        Economic Affairs on the National Security Council during the period that
                        we’ve been focusing on today. And there he was economic advisor to Henry
                        Kissinger, Brent Scowcroft and Zbig Brzezinski, which must have been the
                        reason he was recipient of the French Legion of Honor – (laughter) – to have
                        survived, to have worked with those three.</p>
                    <p>I could go on and on. Dr. Hormats earned his Ph.D. from the Fletcher School
                        of Law and Diplomacy up in the Boston area. It is a great pleasure to have
                        the opportunity, Mr. Secretary, to have you with us today. Thank you.
                        (Applause.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Thank you and thanks for
                        this book. I had a chance to go over it over the weekend, and I must say it
                        brings back a lot of old memories. Let me just try to – </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">PARTICIPANT:</hi> Excuse me. Let me just turn – let me
                        turn this up. There we go. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> It’s very nice to be here. I
                        had a chance to go over most of the book over the weekend, and it does bring
                        back a lot of old memories of various issues. So let me try to set the
                        scene, which I think is useful, because – rather than going into all the
                        details. This took place – these conversations took place (inaudible) going
                        through a number of these periods. This is ’73 to ’76 and it was an eventful
                        period, and I’ll try to recapture some of the events that occurred. </p>
                    <p>But it was in the middle of the oil crisis. That was probably the dominant
                        factor in the international economic policy of the United States, but there
                        were a number of other issues, one of which was that the United States had
                        in 1971, in effect, going off the gold standard and had argued that the
                        dollar was overvalued and the overvalued dollar was harming U.S. trade, and
                        therefore we wanted a system that was more flexible. And the Europeans, on
                        the other hand, were fearful that if the United States did get a more
                        flexible exchange rate system it would cause the dollar to be artificially
                        low and it would improve the U.S. trade balance but be detrimental to
                        European trade and therefore adverse to European economic growth.</p>
                    <p>
                        <lb/> There was another element in this period that was going on, and that
                        was the attempt by the United States after the European Union had formed, in
                        effect, a free trade area to get compensation, under what was known as
                        Article 24.6 because these countries all were trying to create a similar
                        external tariff and some would be raising their tariff in order to comply
                        with the European external tariff against American goods. So the United
                        States was engaged in constant wrangling with those countries. </p>
                    <p>And then there was the broader question not just of whether the dollar should
                        be lower in value, which the United States had wanted and had actually
                        achieved in 1971 and’72, but whether the system itself would be as centered
                        on the dollar. And there were those who were expressing the view that the
                        SDR should play a greater role and the dollar was too dominant a player in
                        the international economic system. </p>
                    <p>These were a few of the issues, and there were lots of tensions between the
                        United States and Western Europe. And one way for – and Japan, I might say.
                        Japan had maintained an exchange rate of 360 yen to the dollar since World
                        War II, the end of World War II. And, of course, that was considered, over a
                        period of time, as the Japanese economy recovered, too low an exchange rate.
                        So we were pressing for the Japanese to raise the value of the yen, and
                        ultimately, the United States was able to get the Japanese to do this. So we
                        were in a constant debate with the Japanese over what the exact exchange
                        rate for the dollar and the yen ought to be. </p>
                    <p>In addition to all this, there were a lot of pressures from developing
                        countries, because the concern was that the United States would be subject –
                        not just the United States, but the industrialized world together would be
                        subject to not just an OPEC cartel, which had – to a degree, it wasn’t
                        really OPEC, but it was the Arab members of OPEC had imposed this embargo
                        against the United States and the Netherlands during the ’73-’74 Middle East
                        war. But there was a feeling that OPEC, using its economic strength, would
                        get together with other commodity-supplying countries and would form a
                        coalition, and there would be more commodity wars or, at a minimum, there
                        would be a huge amount of pressure from the industrialized – on the
                        industrialized countries from the emerging economies utilizing their
                        commodity strengths.</p>
                    <p>So one goal of the United States – and you can see it throughout this book –
                        was to, in effect, split off the commodity-producing countries and the
                        poorer countries from one another. And one of the ways we did this was what
                        was known as the North-South Dialogue or had various incarnations. But the
                        developing countries are talking on a new international economic order or a
                        new global order; and our view was, of course, the new global order was
                        North versus South. And so we were trying constantly to jockey with these
                        countries to, in effect, placate them so that they wouldn’t form a coalition
                        against the United States, which they never did because they really were not
                        of the same mind. And many of the developing countries had been more
                        adversely hurt by the oil embargo than the industrialized countries because
                        it pushed the price of oil up so much, and they had to depend on oil, and it
                        pushed the price of food up because the price of oil went up the price of
                        food went up because of transportation and fertilizer costs and such
                        things.</p>
                    <p>So we had this constant ring of various complicated issues during this
                        period. And during this period I was economic advisor to Henry Kissinger, so
                        I sat in on almost all the discussions that focused on all these issues and
                        was constantly sending him memos on the various issues that are described in
                        this book. Moreover, during this period, one of the things that we had in
                        mind was that the industrialized countries should work more closely together
                        with one another and therefore came up with the idea toward the end of 1975.
                        And it wasn’t initially an American idea; it was really the idea of
                        Chancellor Schmidt and French President Giscard d’Estaing to get the
                        industrialized countries together to discuss how do we deal with the oil
                        issue, how do we deal with the exchange rate issue, how do we deal with the
                        trade issue, was there a view on the developing country problem.</p>
                    <p>And initially the idea was for the French to call the meeting, and they –
                        which they did. The Germans would come, the Brits would come, the Americans
                        would come. Japan – they were a little unsure whether Japan could come
                        because Japan was sort of an outlier at that point. But it was a big
                        economy, it was second-biggest in the world, and therefore there was a
                        general conclusion Japan should come and would have to be there. But Japan
                        was very reticent about playing much of a global role. So it wasn’t – it
                        knew it had to come, but it really was a little bit shy about being as pushy
                        on some of these issues as the French or the Germans or the Americans or the
                        Brits were. </p>
                    <p>And then there was the question of Italy. Originally, it started out as the
                        G-5, not a G-6 or certainly not a G-7. And why did Italy get in there? The
                        Italians got in because there was – and we tend to forget this, but there
                        was a very strong communist movement in Italy at the time. They got a third
                        of the votes. It wasn’t a Moscow kind of communist party, but there were
                        communists nonetheless, and it was the middle of the Cold War. So Prime
                        Minister Moro, who was prime minister of Italy, made an impassioned plea to
                        the United States and to Germany and to France to get in and be part of it
                        because if the West did demonstrate support for him, he would be weaker in
                        dealing with the communists. Well, the French weren’t quite sure they wanted
                        Italy in there. They didn’t have a very favorable view of the Italian
                        economy at that point. But the United States, again as sort of the champion
                        of the Western Cold War – and the Germans, I must say – insisted on Italy
                        coming. So Italy – Prime Minister Moro was invited. He, unfortunately, was
                        killed by radicals and found in the trunk of his car about three months
                        afterwards, so – but Italy did get in and has been a member ever since.</p>
                    <p>Canada – the French vehemently opposed Canada, did not want Canada in. We
                        tried everything we could because we didn’t it to be so pro – so
                        Europe-centered. So we supported having Canada in, and the French refused to
                        invite them. But the U.S. got its revenge because the following year, when
                        we had the summit in Puerto Rico, the U.S. unilaterally invited the
                        Canadians, and the Canadians have been members ever since. And then it
                        became the G-7.</p>
                    <p>So all these things took place during this period. And I have sort of
                        reviewed some of the issues, but let me just go on to a few issues in
                        greater detail, one of which was the question of exchange rates. This – I
                        cannot tell you how emotional an issue this was between the United States
                        and, largely, the French, although the Europeans in general, but the French
                        more than any others. The French resented this – the preeminent role of the
                        dollar, and DeGaulle had called the dollar’s role an exorbitant privilege
                        because the United States could borrow in its own currency, whereas none of
                        the other countries could. So the French were constantly trying to get a
                        system established and get the Americans to accept a system whereby there
                        would be some kind of either fixed rates or close to fixed rates – some
                        narrow finding so that the United States didn’t have the freedom of allowing
                        its exchange rate to devalue, whereas the United States didn’t want
                        necessarily a very rapidly fluctuating system but didn’t want to be bound to
                        an overvalued exchange rate, which the U.S. thought would be harmful to
                        creating jobs in this country. </p>
                    <p>So there was a bitter battle between Giscard d’Estaing and ultimately
                        Secretary – well, Schultz wasn’t the Secretary then; he was the Sherpa. He
                        was the organizer for this summit. So we had Secretary Simon as the Treasury
                        Secretary and then Kissinger was Secretary of State, and ultimately became
                        Secretary of State when President Ford – toward the end of Nixon and
                        throughout the whole Ford Administration, and Scowcroft was the National
                        Security Advisor. So we had meeting after meeting after meeting to figure
                        out how we wanted to deal with the French and how we wanted to deal with the
                        Europeans and how to deal with the exchange rate. And the exchange rate
                        became a very political issue, and it was not an issue that was just left to
                        the Treasury, although the Treasury had a role to play. The Treasury – there
                        was a major foreign policy issue here. And ultimately, the goal that – the
                        rubric that was worked out was “fixed but flexible,” which really, you can –
                        (laughter) – interpret for yourself what it meant. Ultimately, what it meant
                        was that there would be some stability in the exchange rate, but from time
                        to time if need be, under certain conditions which were never fully
                        appropriately spelled out, there could be flexibility. </p>
                    <p>And then there was something that was even more interesting, which was an
                        exchange rate – a reserve indicator, which was essentially if you built up
                        reserves at a rapid rate – and again, there was never any precision here –
                        then you had to appreciate your currency. And if you lost reserves at a
                        rapid rate – again, no benchmark – you had to devalue your currency. And it
                        was a way of avoiding – no one wanted the IMF to tell anyone what to do with
                        their exchange rate, but knew that they wanted a system that had no rules,
                        that this was more or less where they came out. And this was sort of a
                        decision made in the Rambouillet summit. The Rambouillet summit was the
                        first of the G – as I say, the G summits. And it was ultimately six
                        countries quite near – right near Paris. </p>
                    <p>And I was the note taker, the – Kissinger had briefed. It was supposed to be,
                        first, only heads of state, and then only heads of state with the foreign
                        ministers sitting near, and then only heads of state with the foreign
                        ministers and the finance ministers sitting there. And then Kissinger began
                        to realize you had better have some record here because these Cabinet
                        members – (laughter) – are not going to take any records. So I was the note
                        taker, and the note takers were given a little – the French didn’t want any
                        note takers. They just thought this was too lowly a thing to have
                        20-some-year-old kids in the room with all these heads of state. But
                        ultimately, we were given a little desk and we did take notes. And Kissinger
                        insisted on everyone on his staff being able to take notes. </p>
                    <p>And then you had to transcribe them before you went to sleep. So we didn’t
                        really get much sleep because there were, like, seven hours of meetings and
                        we had to transcribe the notes. And there were no computers in those days.
                        You had to type them out on your own typewriter or dictate. Then no
                        secretary was willing to stay up, so you really had to take – you had to
                        really type them out yourself. But you had to have them ready the next day,
                        and then you had them negotiate the communiqué. And now the communiqué is
                        negotiated over, like, a three-month period. Those days there was one draft
                        and you had to stay up pretty much all night negotiating the communiqué, so
                        you got almost no sleep for about two-and-a-half, three days. But it was
                        well worth it. </p>
                    <p>In any case, there was one – and we managed to work out language which was
                        more or less acceptable on the exchange rate issue. That was – that gave the
                        French enough so that they could say there was some measure of fixity but
                        gave the United States enough so that we could say there was enough
                        flexibility in the system, and that was really the big result of
                        Rambouillet. There were others. </p>
                    <p>One of the other issues that took place was how you dealt with, as I say, the
                        oil producing and commodity producing countries. And there was a general
                        notion that the United States should and the West should – provide some
                        benefits for them and try to avoid solidarity. Well, the French – the
                        Europeans were worried. They were much more on the side of placating the oil
                        producers because they depended far more on imported oil than we did. And
                        they really were, accept for Holland, targets of the embargo. So what the
                        French wanted to do was have what they considered a dialogue between oil
                        consumers and oil producers. Well, the United States bitterly opposed this
                        because we figured, then, the oil producers will use their leverage. They
                        had already used their leverage to try to get Israel to give up land in
                        order for them – the oil producers, the Arab oil producers – to start
                        producing oil again. And the United States – (inaudible) found that
                        unacceptable. </p>
                    <p>And second, the United States found it more than unacceptable; we found it
                        counter to any country’s interest, because once you give up anything, the
                        United States – the argument was, well, the United States would just pull
                        its troops out of Egypt. The United States had troops in Egypt during the
                        war in Sinai. We refused to pull them out on the grounds that the oil flow
                        would be restored, because we said all you do is enhance the power of those
                        people who want to use oil as a lever. So we refused to negotiate with them
                        at all on anything. And over a period of time, these countries decided that
                        it would be a wise thing not to continue to embargo because it had adversely
                        affected the global economy, and therefore their interests, and then they
                        began to realize that if the price went up, there would be substitutes.
                        Literally, they realized how quickly we forgot about these oil shocks.
                        (Laughter.) But they – but there would be substitutes. </p>
                    <p>So the – we – I went on these shuttle trips that Kissinger had on the Middle
                        – in the Middle East where we spent a lot of time – mostly – most of the
                        time negotiating about Middle East policy, but part of the time talking
                        about how bad our economies were going to be if they continued this oil
                        embargo. And we spent a lot of time with the King of Saudi Arabia. And
                        President Sadat, who was really the hero of this, who was assassinated later
                        on, he was the predecessor of Mubarak. So we spent a lot of time and went to
                        Syria and went to all these places just trying to sort of explain our view
                        and calm these countries down about the American presence, which they found
                        very troublesome. I mean, we were arming the Israelis. We didn’t actually
                        have physical troops in Israel, but we had ships – American ships in the
                        Gulf which were – and the question was really whether we would continue to
                        supply Israel or we would stop supplying Israel in return for the Arabs
                        lifting the embargo.</p>
                    <p>So one of the things we tried to do in the United States was reduce our
                        dependence on imported oil in order so we wouldn’t – to avoid our being
                        vulnerable to this kind of thing yet again. And we tried something – we
                        tried a lot of things. None of them worked. One of them was – well, some of
                        them worked a little bit. One of them was a minimum selling price, which is
                        to say if the price of oil – and I forget what it was – it went up from a
                        few – like 60 cents to $4, and then $4 to $5. It was nothing compared to
                        what it is today. But what we were trying to do is find a floor price, or
                        what we call a minimum selling price, so that we would provide an incentive
                        for the producers to produce more oil in the United States on the grounds
                        that if the price of oil went below the minimum selling price, the federal
                        government wouldn’t buy the oil in the market. So that would provide an
                        incentive for producers to produce more, knowing that they had a minimum
                        selling price or what tended to be known as a floor price. </p>
                    <p>That didn’t go because, of course, it was a contingent liability on the
                        federal government that it would buy the oil at a given price if the price
                        went below the market. So there was a lot resistance to that. It would never
                        have mattered because the price never went down below what we thought the
                        minimum selling price would be. But it was a signal to the industry that
                        they should produce more oil here. </p>
                    <p>The other thing we did do, which we have today, is the Strategic Petroleum
                        Reserve. It’s known as the SPRO, which would enable us to store oil in
                        Mississippi and Louisiana in these big salt domes. And originally, it was
                        500 million barrels a day. The idea was that 90 percent of your inflow, but
                        not every country was able to do this. Not every country has salt domes.
                        Where are the Dutch going to put oil? They don’t have those things. So – but
                        the United States did it, Japan did it, Britain – which is an oil exporter –
                        did some of it, which it just shut in the oil, and a few other countries did
                        it. So we developed this international energy agency and this notion of a
                        Strategic Petroleum Reserve for countries that were able to do it as a way –
                        a buffer in case we were ever again threatened with an embargo. So that was
                        one of the outcomes. </p>
                    <p>The other outcome was that Americans did, for a period of time, reduce their
                        dependence on oil – reduce their use of oil substantially. But then the
                        price went down again, and American consumption went up. So these are a
                        couple of the elements of what went on then. On trade, we ultimately did
                        reach an agreement to start the trade round again, to try to reduce overall
                        global tariffs. The Europeans did agree on this Article 24.6, which is to
                        say they did agree to a formula for compensation in the form of countries
                        that paid a higher tariff, but that charge a higher tariff in its American
                        goods, would have to lower tariffs or in some other areas to compensate us.
                        On the other hand, we avoided a big fight. So this is basically where we
                        came out. This is sort of a quick distillation of a lot of the things here. </p>
                    <p>We – I mean, as you can see, during this period there were numerous meetings
                        on economic issues. And in most of these cases, we, before each meeting, the
                        NSC person would write up for the – if the President came or his Cabinet
                        members came. But this book tends to eliminate – although, once in a while
                        refers to them – meetings with the President that occurred. Those tend to be
                        in the presidential library, not in this thing. But once in a while, they do
                        creep into this. So you really have to go to the Nixon and the Ford
                        libraries to get where the President’s involved. </p>
                    <p>But in most cases, what was done here was that the NSC staff person would
                        write out the options for the meeting, what the options were, what the
                        alternatives were, and then they would be debated, and then the NSC staff
                        person would sort of write up the conclusions and send them out to the
                        member – people who participated in the meetings. So there would be a clear
                        record of what the decision was, and if the President was there, what the
                        President said, if the Secretary of State, who chaired – Kissinger was not
                        actually Security Advisor during most of this. So he would chair most of
                        these meetings. And then he became National Security Advisor and Secretary
                        of State. So he would continue to chair these meetings. </p>
                    <p>I don’t know if you went through it. Once in a while – at one point, Simon
                        comes into the room and Kissinger wasn’t there, so Simon sits at the head of
                        the chair – the head of the table. So Kissinger walks in and says, “Get out
                        of my chair.” I mean, so it was very clear that Kissinger dominated this
                        process. And therefore, his staff had a lot to do. But the key point
                        organizationally was in every circumstance, the decision, the study
                        memorandum – they were called NSMs, National Security study memorandums –
                        before they went to the meeting, everyone had a chance to comment on whether
                        the questions had been posed fairly and accurately, and whether the options
                        and the various consequences of individual options were spelled out fairly. </p>
                    <p>In other words, you’d have option one would be do this. And then the pros and
                        cons would be such and such. And option two would be this, and here would be
                        the pros and cons, so that it was – the aim was to make sure that the
                        alternatives were spelled out clearly and that there was a fair assessment
                        of the pros and cons of each, not to say that everyone would agree on each
                        of the options. That was never – or rarely the case, but it was supposed to
                        be a fair or very transparent process. And then at the end, before the final
                        National Security decision which encapsulated the results was out, the
                        individual Cabinet members could look and make sure it was a fair rendition
                        of what was said in the meeting. So it aimed to create a sense of legitimacy
                        about the process, which was very important, and sense of order to the
                        process. </p>
                    <p>Anyway, this is sort of a quick overview of this system and what it proves.
                        So I’m happy to answer any questions. It’s hard to go through all of it
                        because there’s a lot of stuffing in our few pages – a thousand pages – yes,
                        1,089 pages. Yeah.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> We had some discussion today before you
                        came, and this is certainly a statement when one studies Kissinger.
                        Kissinger always made quite a bit of the fact that he didn’t know anything
                        about economics or didn’t know very much. From your perspective and your
                        experience of him, did he really understand the economic angles? Did he
                        would learn over time? Did he change at all? Did he really know all the time
                        and pretend that he didn’t know?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> No, he really – I mean, I
                        think he changed a lot. I think the oil crisis really focused his attention
                        on economics a lot more than was the case beforehand. I mean he had – it
                        wasn’t that he didn’t know anything. I mean, he had been at Harvard. He
                        talked about economic issues, more from a strategic point of view. And in
                        fact, I had one of his courses that he taught with Stanley Hoffmann and Sam
                        Huntington. It was called – the course was called “War.” (Laughter.) That
                        wasn’t the real name of the course, but that’s what it was nicknamed, War.
                        And – but a fair amount, not the part he taught – they were – each would
                        teach one week and the other would the other week, and then they’d have
                        three altogether, and then back again. But Huntington focused a lot on the
                        economic parts of this. As you can read – it was before <hi rend="italic"
                            >Clash of Civilizations</hi> . But he wrote a lot of books on
                        international history. And one of them – one of the key elements of his
                        book, the book he used – I forget the name of it – was essentially how
                        economic issues was a – were factors in the war. And then Kissinger was very
                        familiar with the origins of World War II because he had written on that,
                        and the Treaty of Versailles and the reparations. So he had a pretty good
                        idea of that period. And don’t forget, he’d been in Germany as a translator,
                        so he knew a lot about what was going on in European economies. And he – and
                        in fact, he had met – while he was over there, he knew – he got to know
                        Erhard, who was sort of the father of the German economic miracle. </p>
                    <p>And then he met with [Jean] Monnet, and on a couple of occasions he and I
                        went to see Monnet. We had – 1971 or 2 – ’72 there was something called the
                        Year of Europe, when we tried to repair the fragment – the fractured
                        relations that took place because of the unilateral American decision to get
                        off the gold standard. So Monnet was sort of our advisor. He was then about
                        80, but still very lucid. I mean, he had an apartment on Avenue Foch, fine
                        wine, good lunch, and very good advice. He’s still – he was – he lived in
                        the U.S. for a while. He spoke perfect English. He really knew us. He was
                        like de Tocqueville. He had a very good sense of how the American economy
                        worked and how the American political system worked and why the Europeans
                        felt – were suspicious of us, essentially.</p>
                    <p>But yeah, the answer is after a while he learned more about economics as time
                        went by. And then in the end – and he would test you. I mean, if you – to
                        find out how strongly your views – how strong your views were on given
                        points. He would sort of throw out propositions that he knew weren’t right
                        to see if you were willing to agree with him, even though he knew they were
                        wrong, just to sort of test whether you knew what you were talking about or
                        not. That was always the test. </p>
                    <p>Yes. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">DR. RASMUSSEN:</hi> You talked a lot about America
                        exerting leadership during this period. And with the (inaudible) 1971, a lot
                        of scholars have since interpreted that sort of a mastication of American
                        leadership. In the ’73 to ’76 period, you have the Europeans increasingly
                        taking the lead on response to the March 1973 currency crisis. You
                        referenced Giscard’s leadership that had turned into the Conference on
                        International Economic Cooperation. Craig Schmidt, because of the G summit
                        mechanism – did policymakers at the time consciously think about the need to
                        exert American leadership? And if so, how did you do it when other countries
                        were themselves trying to exert a leadership role? </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Well, I think – that’s an
                        interesting question. I think on the organizational thing, it was certainly
                        Schmidt and Giscard, although George Shultz, who was not in the government
                        at that point, played a very active role, too. And Harold Wilson – but see,
                        the difference is Schmidt and Giscard had both been finance ministers, so
                        they really were interested. And [Gerald] Ford had never been a finance
                        minister, and didn’t – and I think there was some consternation about Ford
                        getting into a financial discussion with these guys, because they really
                        knew what they were talking about. (Laughter.) And it wasn’t his area, nor
                        Harold – nor was it Harold Wilson’s. He was the British prime minister at
                        the time. And Denis Healy was the Chancellor of the Exchequer, who was very
                        good. He knew this stuff inside and out, and was sort of always chafing that
                        Wilson would talk, and he was just sitting there on the sidelines. But over
                        a period – and Moro didn’t really know much about these issues either. </p>
                    <p>But I think on the – that was where the Europeans really were most energetic
                        in their leadership. On the question of what the new currency system would
                        look like, the guy who was the most dominant was Paul Volcker. He was the
                        under secretary at the time. So all these meetings, as you’ll read this,
                        you’ll find Volcker was the – Volcker and the French Finance Minister, who
                        was then Giscard d’Estaing – before it was Giscard and then became – he
                        became President of France. They were really the two – and then Schmidt. So
                        – but Volcker was really the sort of intellectual, the dominating intellect
                        in the whole question of the system. And then Ed Yeo replaced Volcker later
                        on. But – and Yeo wasn’t nearly the sort of intellectual dynamo that Volcker
                        was. But Volcker played a very key role, and you’ll see that in the
                        book.</p>
                    <p>On the North-South issue, it was clearly Kissinger. Kissinger – and the
                        energy issue was clearly Kissinger, because he was just worried that the
                        Europeans would give in to the Arabs and let oil be used as a lever, and he
                        was determined that wouldn’t happen. So he really engineered the whole
                        North-South response and the whole energy response. And the fact there’s an
                        IEA and the strategic reserves is Kissinger. And the guy who also deserves
                        credit – he’s now no longer with us – is Tom Enders, who was the
                        then-Assistant Secretary of State, and you’ll see him mentioned, too. He was
                        just sort of bigger than life. He was about 6’7”. He was really dominant.
                        He’d gone to school in France, so he was bilingual. He was very good. Ken
                        will remember him. I mean, he was really a tour de force at that point. Tour
                        – (laughter) – double entendre. </p>
                    <p>But, yeah, he – they were – so on the structural issue, it was the Europeans.
                        But on North-South, energy, and the exchange rate issue, it was all – it was
                        the Americans who were still – and nothing happened without the Americans. I
                        mean, the Europeans could be obstreperous, but – and intellectually, they
                        had their own point of view. I mean, they were – and they were very good.
                        They had – they went through – there were several finance ministers in here
                        after Giscard became President. But they were – they held their own, but
                        they just – nothing the U.S. didn’t want could happen. We couldn’t make what
                        we wanted happen, but we could – but we could block things that we didn’t
                        like. And it was not – I mean, it was sort of a cooperative thing, but – and
                        we – and no one forgot that we were in the Cold War, because every – the
                        feeling was any division between the industrialized countries would just be
                        seized on by the Soviet Union. So that really – it didn’t mean there weren’t
                        spats. But Nixon was always very clear, and then Ford after him. </p>
                    <p>Ford’s in most of this book, not Nixon. They both understood that they
                        couldn’t go – didn’t want to go to an international meeting divided. They
                        wanted to make sure that these issues were resolved. So on some issues, they
                        probably gave a little more than they otherwise would so there wouldn’t be
                        an out-and-out fight. So the U.S. never really – except on the currency
                        issue – never really pushed its advantage to the ultimate where it got
                        everything it wanted. It always gave the Europeans enough so that they
                        didn’t leave unhappily – unhappy. </p>
                    <p>Yes. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> You were talking earlier about how there
                        were some similarities between the situation then and the situation now,
                        commodities being a question once again, uncertain financial relationships
                        and so forth. Are there lessons you would take from the ’73-’76 period that
                        you might suggest to Secretary Clinton? </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Yeah, that’s an interesting
                        question. The key point we concluded, although it’s triply valid now, is
                        that you really had to work with the emerging economies, because they really
                        weren’t monolithic. There were differences among them, and you couldn’t
                        treat them all the same way. They had to be – we had – the big leader of the
                        sort of North-South, I would say, confrontational approach was Algeria,
                        (inaudible), and then Venezuela. That hasn’t changed much. The Shah – Iran
                        was different because the Shah was in power. But it was a few countries that
                        took a more radical view. But most of them really didn’t want to radicalize
                        the North-South divide. So I think the basic point is you have to work with
                        these countries on an individualistic basis to identify where their
                        interests are and where ours are, which means a very sophisticated
                        diplomacy.</p>
                    <p>Now, the Cold War wasn’t that sophisticated because either they were your
                        allies or not. So these countries really didn’t have any appetite for a big
                        dustup with the United States, most of them, because most of them realized
                        that the United States was protecting – many of them didn’t have democratic
                        systems at that point. In Latin America, many of them didn’t. So they –
                        their – the American – the U.S. was sort of their protector. In Africa,
                        there were those sort of supportive of the Soviet Union and supportive of
                        the United States. So you didn’t have the sort of diversity of attitudes and
                        ideologies and economic models that you have today. But basically, that was
                        one.</p>
                    <p>The other is that you really – the lesson we still haven’t learned is we have
                        to reduce our dependence on imported oil. We’re a lot worse off now than we
                        were then in terms of our dependence on imported oil. We haven’t learned a
                        damn thing, in my judgment, from that period. Every time there is the oil
                        prices going up – ’73-’74, and then the fall of the Shah and then the first
                        Iraq oil crisis and you – and then the – of the other confrontations in the
                        Middle East, the other – the additional Iraqi threat to Kuwait, where they
                        put all their troops on the border during the Clinton Administration. None
                        of those things have really – they all spiked up the price of oil. But the
                        price goes down, so Americans have this notion that somehow we don’t really
                        have to do anything, the price will go down, the government really doesn’t
                        have to take any tough actions, we don’t have to take any tough actions. And
                        that’s a lesson we haven’t – we, unfortunately, haven’t learned.</p>
                    <p>On exchange rates, I think now the notion of flexible exchange rates is
                        pretty well – except for a few countries, notable exceptions – the notion of
                        currency flexibility is pretty well established. Those are the things I’d
                        mention. </p>
                    <p>The other one was that process is important in the way governance is
                        conducted. Rob Rubin wrote about this in his book, and I think that’s one of
                        the things that you see. You can tell some of these meetings were not very
                        well organized, and you sort of came in and threw out ideas. But for the
                        most part, the key to making good policy is to structure the decision making
                        process in an orderly way, so that everyone – so that all the options are
                        examined and the various pros and cons of each option are examined, and then
                        you make a decision that everyone has a sense of participation in, even if
                        they don’t get what they want. And then there’s a very clear articulation of
                        the outcome so that everyone knows what they’re supposed to do or not do.
                        And that has been more or less adhered to for a fairly long time. There have
                        been – there are a few exceptions, but not that many. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Well, that actually – the question of
                        process brings to mind, I think, a question that (inaudible). Working
                        conditions under Henry Kissinger, Brent Scowcroft, and (inaudible) Zbigniew
                        Brzezinski. Would you care to comment on what it was like working for these
                        very competent individuals?</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Well, it was – I mean, you
                        didn’t get a lot of sleep. But was it was lot – it was always a lot fun. I
                        went on this – on the shuttles with Kissinger, because there was an economic
                        – there was always an economic component, and he didn’t want to deal with it
                        and he didn’t have time to deal with it. Like – I’ll give you an example. In
                        the ’73 war, Israel had taken – Egypt has oil wells called the Elmore Gant
                        Oil Fields. They’re in Sinai. They’re still – they still produce, like,
                        90,000 barrels a day, something like that, which is for Egypt a lot of oil.
                        And the Israelis got them and, of course, were pumping all the oil they
                        could pump. So they were over-pumping. If you pump oil too rapidly, it
                        depletes the pressure. So our – one of our goals was to get the Israelis, as
                        the – we knew the Israelis were going to give up Sinai; they didn’t want
                        Sinai. They couldn’t defend it. It wasn’t a strategic benefit for them at
                        all anyway. And the IDF just didn’t want to be in Sinai. So we knew they
                        were going to give it up. But the – they were pumping all this oil out and
                        the Egyptians were getting very upset because they said, “When we get the
                        oil wells back, we won’t have any oil pressure so we can’t get any oil, and
                        we need that oil.” So one of the – one of my tasks was to go get the
                        Israelis to stop doing this and to pump 90,000 barrels and no more. So that
                        was, like, a one-week negotiation. They were getting every drop they could
                        out of it. And so I explained this, and they said, “Oh, we know we’re
                        over-pumping it,” but ultimately they (inaudible). (Laughter.) And, I mean,
                        they had engineers (inaudible). </p>
                    <p>The other thing was we gave Sadat a lot of money to help him feel comfortable
                        about doing a number of things. One was that their army was surrounded. The
                        Egyptian army was surrounded by Israelis, so we had to negotiate some
                        honorable way the Egyptians – the Israelis would pull back and the Egyptians
                        could claim a victory as opposed to a defeat, which was very important to
                        Sadat. And then we gave them money that he could – so he could get his
                        country going again. </p>
                    <p>So Kissinger didn’t like the notion of negotiating large amounts of money
                        with him, and so he would lead me to do this. So we went over how much money
                        we were going to give them, and sort of wrote it out, and was – it was all
                        accounted for. I mean, we had to do that. But then the question is how it
                        would be allocated. And that was purely up to Sadat. So I explained to him
                        how much money it was and how it had to be accounted for and all of that.
                        “Oh, I’ll use it for this (inaudible).” And it’s not like the U.S., where
                        you had to get it all appropriated. So Kissinger – then you had to report to
                        Kissinger what is he going to do. </p>
                    <p>But basically, he kept you working a lot. And you had – every night before
                        you went to bed, you had to do the – a cable that he would send the
                        President, and that he would send the next morning, because that was before
                        they woke up in Washington time, so the White House would get it before they
                        woke up and the President would have it on his desk. That was imperative
                        that you report to the President. And he kept the President with him and the
                        President was up to date and all that. But of course, someone had to write
                        that before they went to bed. It wasn’t him. (Laughter.) And then he would
                        look at it in the morning and edit it and then send it out. </p>
                    <p>So you learned to pay attention to what was said and the nuances. And then
                        you had to get up two hours before him – than he did to do the briefings of
                        what had happened during the night. So you – maybe you got two hours or
                        three hours of sleep, I mean, for like two weeks. Maybe you could sleep on
                        the airplane, but not much. </p>
                    <p>But it was – but he always – but the one thing about it: We had a – he had
                        his 70th birthday party a while ago, and the people who were on his NSC
                        staff did a book; we did a book for him. Everyone wrote a letter about him.
                        And the one thing about this was that everyone commented – virtually
                        everyone commented on the fact that he’d given them more responsibility at a
                        younger age than they ever imagined they could ever – they could have, and
                        helped them to sort of learn a lot about how to get things done and to use
                        good judgment at an early age, because if you didn’t use good judgment – you
                        were never penalized for mistakes, although he would get angry. But if you
                        used poor judgment, you were out. If he didn’t think your judgment was good
                        – you could be inaccurate; people make mistakes. But if he really questioned
                        your judgment or your integrity, or you told him things that you didn’t –
                        that you really had not researched, you just sort of gave him informal
                        advice that you hadn’t thought about – I guess that’s the nicest way to put
                        it – if he felt, he found that out, that you had not thought it through or
                        you gave him inaccurate advice without doing a deliberative attempt to
                        determine what was right, you didn’t really last very long. He saw that. He
                        saw through that very clearly. </p>
                    <p>And the same with Scowcroft. Scowcroft had a very different – a much
                        lower-key approach, but he had that same very tough approach to individuals.
                        And as a result, a number of people left the Kissinger staff quite quickly.
                        And – but the people he kept, he had – he would give you enormous amounts of
                        responsibility, and take your – well, you can see these memos. I mean, he
                        would let you write memos to the President. And rarely – I would say he
                        edited them, but very rarely. I mean, he would just sign them. You’d write a
                        memo to Kissinger and then there would be underlying – the underneath was
                        the Kissinger memo to the President, and he would almost always sign it. If
                        you made a mistake – I mean, he hated typos, because he considered those
                        lazy – that you were lazy; you didn’t proofread it. And he was right. And it
                        drives me crazy when I see some of the memos that go the Secretary. I mean,
                        people just don’t proofread them, and it just – there’s no excuse for that.
                        You can make a mistake, but if you make a mistake by not reading the memo
                        that’s going to the President or the Secretary – sometimes, you’re tired and
                        you make mistakes that way. That didn’t trouble him too much. But sort of a
                        constant pattern of sloppiness, he just found that crazy.</p>
                    <p>And Brzezinski was different. Brzezinski would like to throw out ideas. He
                        was much more of an idea man and less of a structured deliverer of organized
                        policy. But he had a lot of good ideas. He was very, very smart, very
                        talented. </p>
                    <p>Do one more? Okay, go ahead. We’ll do two more. Okay, go ahead. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> I was wondering if you could describe it,
                        but the fault lines in policy battles. And we had some earlier discussion
                        about people who are more – very laissez faire-oriented versus people like
                        Kissinger who were more pragmatic in terms of at least mouthing certain
                        words to placate the Third World, or whether it was a (inaudible) agency
                        turf battles were for (inaudible) policies. What was it that drove
                        disagreements within the U.S. Government? </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Oh, interagency battles. The
                        Third World’s basically – he did understand we need not just to placate
                        them. They weren’t naïve. He understood that you had to do something for
                        them. I think the –there were different – certainly differences in
                        interagency positions, and they were worked out. Most of them were worked
                        out in a fairly harmonious way. I mean, you don’t see there – you don’t see
                        some, really, a lot of bitterness. I think Secretary Simon called the Shah
                        and not – and then Kissinger said – and then Kissinger confronted him with
                        this – how’d you – why’d you call him a nut? So Simon says, “Well, it was
                        taken out of context.” So Kissinger said, “Well, in what possible context
                        could you have called the man a nut?” (Laughter.) So there were things of
                        that nature. </p>
                    <p>But mostly I think people got along pretty well. I would say there were some
                        issues. Ed Yeo, who was – who took over from Volcker – I think was a little
                        more confrontational and little more defensive of the Treasury position.
                        Volcker was very open, so there were always a lot of issues with Yeo sort of
                        not sharing his views, not playing nicely in the same sandbox. But most of
                        the time, there was – there were differences of view, but they were mostly
                        fought out in a fairly amicable way. And Ford, who was President during most
                        of this, was very calm in his demeanor and did not like these big fights and
                        fights. And if there were fights between the Cabinet members, he would be
                        quite firm in making sure they didn’t continue. </p>
                    <p>So last question. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> All right. One of the challenges for
                        foreign relations scholars is trying to establish linkages among different
                        policy areas that we tend to study separately – for example, détente with
                        the Soviet Union or the opening to China. So we’ve been discussing today,
                        kind of amongst ourselves a little bit, what interaction there might have
                        been between these kinds of issues, mostly within the industrial West and
                        other aspects of American grand strategy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Well, what’s the question? </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> Well, for example, does détente or the Cold
                        War have an impact on American policy in the economic realm? Does the
                        opening to China have –</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Oh, yeah.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">QUESTION:</hi> -- that sort of (inaudible).</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="strong">UNDER SECRETARY HORMATS:</hi> Oh, yeah. Oh, for sure. I
                        think that if you look at the opening – let’s just take the opening to
                        China, which we had these – I worked on a lot of the books that we opened –
                        used. They were called the Marco Polo books. (Laughter.) They were these two
                        big books that we used as – to brief the President for the trip to China,
                        these big thick books. And a lot of the early signals to China – in fact,
                        most of the early signals to China that we wanted to normalize, except in a
                        few instances where Kissinger and Zhou Enlai would exchange these somewhat
                        cryptic little suggestions, was that we would open up trade. And the first
                        signal was – for most of the time there was no trade permitted. Americans
                        couldn’t buy any Chinese goods at all, zero, none. And then we opened up and
                        we allowed Americans to buy $100 worth of Chinese goods, but not directly
                        from China, through Hong Kong. And mostly they were brushes. The Chinese
                        make brushes with pig’s bristles and toothbrushes and things like that, or
                        silks, certain kind of silks, $100 you could buy. And if you were in Hong
                        Kong, you went the bazaar, you could buy $100 worth of Chinese things and
                        they wouldn’t be confiscated, which they would have been earlier than that. </p>
                    <p>And then so we – and then we also allowed a few other things, little by
                        little by little. And then at one point we went to see the Chinese to
                        explain how we were opening up in these – calling their attention to these
                        little signals. So at one point, Zhou Enlai – we explained to Zhou Enlai –
                        Kissinger explained to Zhou en-lai what we’d done. So Zhou Enlai said,
                        “These are two big countries, and you use $100 worth of trading to
                        demonstrate your desire to have a closer relationship?” (Laughter.) And he
                        sort of – he did it in this very wry – he spoke very good French, so he
                        would sometimes – French, he did this in French so no one could – so people
                        could get it. It made the point that it was sort of minor and
                        insignificantly relevant. </p>
                    <p>But the basic point is that you’ve got to blend economics and the foreign
                        policy and the national security elements collectively. And therefore, the
                        fact is that we – I don’t think anyone imagined – the only one I can really
                        imagine who could envisage the way China would look today was probably Deng
                        Xiaoping. He understand this. He was really a great visionary. I don’t think
                        Zhou Enlai would have gotten it. (Inaudible) probably would have, people
                        like that. But basically the notion of closer economic relations was
                        considered really a critical element of strengthening our economic ties with
                        China. And even more important was the fact that they – all these countries
                        had really committed themselves to undermining the Western economic system
                        during the ‘60s and ‘70s. Khrushchev said “we’ll bury you,” and the Chinese
                        regarded the IMF and the World Bank as anathema. The first thing they did
                        was to join the IMF and the World Bank, as the Russians – the Soviets did.
                        And then the WTO, or the GATT and then the WTO. </p>
                    <p>So what was quite interesting is that these countries had really had a
                        parallel but dysfunctional system, which was the common term. And then the
                        various international groups that the communist countries maintained among
                        themselves, all of which were fictional and dysfunctional, they all craved
                        joining the WTO and the IMF and the World Bank because they realized they
                        got real benefits out of plugging into the global system. And I think the
                        key point just to leave you with is if we’re going to continue to develop
                        relations with these countries, then we need to continue to integrate them
                        into the global system. And you need institutions, and it goes back to the
                        point Monnet made in the 50s, which was you need – it’s good to have
                        leaders, inspirational leaders, but you really need strong institutions to
                        sustain things. And I think if there’s a lesson now, it is that the amount
                        of time we spent building up institutions after the war and then during the
                        energy crisis, the IEA, for instance, or strengthening the WTO, all of these
                        institutions really do play a greater role in pulling countries together.
                        (Applause.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
