<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">National Security Policy and SALT I, 1969-1972</title>
                <title type="short">National Security Policy and SALT I, 1969-1972</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <scriptStmt>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>U.S. Department of State and Williams College</author>
                        <title>National Security Policy and SALT I, 1969-1972</title>
                        <date when="2012-03-03">March 2-3, 2012</date>
                    </bibl>
                </scriptStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="overview">
                <head>“National Security Policy and SALT I, 1969-1972”</head>
                <p rend="centerstrong">The Office of the Historian at the U.S. Department of State
                    and Williams College Present the Second Conference of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Foreign Relations of the United States</hi> Special Conference Series</p>
                <p rend="centerstrong">“National Security Policy and SALT I, 1969-1972”<lb/> March
                    2-3, 2012</p>
                <p>The Office of the Historian at the U.S. Department of State and Williams College
                    are pleased to announce a conference marking the publication of the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32">SALT I, 1969-1972</ref> and the
                        <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v34">National Security Policy,
                        1969-1972</ref> volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations of the
                        United States</hi> series. This conference marked the culmination of a
                    broader initiative to commemorate the <ref
                        target="/historicaldocuments/frus-history">150th anniversary</ref> of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series and was held at Williams
                    College in Williamstown, Massachusetts from March 2-3, 2012.</p>
                <p>These two <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> volumes contain extensive
                    documentation of many important national security and foreign policy initiatives
                    that laid the foundation for U.S. foreign policy in the post-hegemonic era that
                    began in the 1970s. The <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v32">SALT
                        I, 1969-1972</ref> volume provides detailed records of arms control policy
                    formulation and implementation. The documentation illuminates both the
                    substantive issues involved in the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks as well as
                    the negotiations’ relationship to the broader context of linkage and détente
                    that shaped high-level decision-making. The compilation includes transcripts of
                    taped White House meetings between high-level policymakers and documentation of
                    the Kissinger-Dobrynin back-channel in addition to records illustrating the
                    interagency process that defined U.S. policy and SALT delegation instructions.
                    The volume also contains coverage of White House efforts to secure Congressional
                    support for the final agreements.</p>
                <p>The <ref target="/historicaldocuments/frus1969-76v34">National Security Policy,
                        1969-1972</ref> volume also covers several significant issues, including the
                    evolution of U.S. missile defense initiatives, efforts to adapt national
                    strategy to a new era of strategic parity with the Soviet Union and the growth
                    of a Chinese nuclear deterrent, the October 1969 Joint Chiefs of Staff Readiness
                    Test, the creation of an all-volunteer armed force, and the challenges of
                    balancing resources and commitments in an atmosphere of declining domestic
                    support for defense spending. Like the SALT I volume, the National Security
                    Policy volume incorporates a wide variety of U.S. Government records to
                    thoroughly document policy formulation at the highest levels.</p>
                <p>To explore the major themes of these two volumes, we planned a conference agenda
                    with several complementary components. Paul Wolfowitz and Jeremi Suri delivered
                    opening and closing keynote addresses. One panel, moderated by Edward Brynn of
                    the Office of the Historian, included the volumes’ compilers and general editor
                    discussing their experience preparing the volumes with General Robert Pursley,
                    who served as Secretary of Defense Melvin Laird’s military advisor between 1969
                    and 1972. We also assembled three interdisciplinary panels, comprised of
                    historians and political scientists, to assess the significance of the events
                    documented in the two volumes as well as the scholarly importance of the
                    documents that they contain. The first of these panels focused on deterrence in
                    an era of parity, covering issues such as nuclear strategy, arms control,
                    missile defense, and intelligence capabilities. A second panel examined problems
                    of perceptions, including intelligence collection and analytical capacities and
                    the difficulties of signaling intentions to allies and adversaries. The third
                    panel covered evolving constraints on U.S. policy, especially declining
                    political, intellectual, and budgetary support for maintaining Cold War
                    capabilities and strategies.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>LOCATION</head>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="http://www.williams.edu/">Williams College</ref> (Griffin
                        Hall). <lb/>
                        <ref target="http://www.williams.edu/visitors/">Maps and Directions</ref>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>SCHEDULE</head>
                    <p>March 2, 2012 (closed)</p>
                    <p>Keynote Address by Hon. Paul Wolfowitz, American Enterprise Institute for
                        Public Policy Research</p>
                    <p>March 3, 2012, 8:30 a.m.-4:45 p.m.</p>
                    <table rend="schedule">
                        <row>
                            <cell>8:30 - 10:15 a.m.</cell>
                            <cell><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L2xLZMk-390">Panel:
                                    Deterrence in an Era of Parity</ref><list>
                                    <item>Moderator: Prof. James McAllister, Williams College</item>
                                    <item>Dr. William Burr, National Security Archive</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Sir Lawrence Freedman, King's College London</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Brendan Green, Williams College</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Joshua Rovner, U.S. Naval War College</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10:15 a.m.</cell>
                            <cell> Coffee Break</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10:30 a.m. - 12:15 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E1dJY3GLnRw">Panel:
                                    Problems of Perception</ref><list>
                                    <item>Moderator: Dr. Stephen Randolph, Office of the
                                        Historian</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Richard Immerman, Temple University</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Robert Jervis, Columbia University</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Melvyn Leffler, University of Virginia</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Keren Yarhi-Milo, Princeton University</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>12:15 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell>Lunch Buffet</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>12:30 - 2:00 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qjzm6zbWrkw">Lunch
                                    Panel: Compiler and Participant Perspectives on <hi
                                        rend="italic">FRUS</hi></ref>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Moderator: Amb. Edward Brynn, Office of the
                                        Historian</item>
                                    <item>Prof. M. Todd Bennett, East Carolina University</item>
                                    <item>Dr. Edward Keefer, Office of the Secretary of
                                        Defense</item>
                                    <item>Dr. Erin Mahan, Office of the Secretary of Defense</item>
                                    <item>Gen. Robert Pursley, USAF (ret.)</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2:00 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell>Coffee Break</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2:15 - 3:45 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5hAbKyG4j0Y">Panel:
                                    Evolving Constraints</ref><list>
                                    <item>Moderator: Prof. Mark Lawrence, University of Texas</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Beth Bailey, Temple University</item>
                                    <item>Prof. Thomas Schwartz, Vanderbilt University</item>
                                    <item>Dr. Chris Tudda, Office of the Historian</item>
                                </list>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3:45 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell>Coffee Break</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4:00-4:45 p.m.</cell>
                            <cell><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7fUwdcyxDU">Keynote
                                    Address: "SALT I: A Historical Turning Point?"</ref> by Prof.
                                Jeremi Suri, University of Texas</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
